<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R Package Manager on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/r-package-manager/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R Package Manager on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 13:13:58 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/r-package-manager/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Installing R Packages in SQL Server Machine Learning Services - I</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-06-23-installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 13:13:58 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-06-23-installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post was supposed to be a single post about how to install R packages in SQL Server Machine Learning Services, but once again I completely misjudged the scope of the topic. So this one post turned into a series of posts about how to install R packages in &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt; and this is the first post in the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see other posts in the series go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/sql_server_ml_services_install_packages&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install R Packages in SQL Server ML Services Series&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may know, I am in the process of writing the follow-up post to &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-05-20-sp-execute-external-script-and-sql-compute-context/&#34;&gt;sp_execute_external_script and SQL Compute Context - I&lt;/a&gt;. However, I have a hard time getting into the flow of things, so I use any excuse I can, to not have to write. So when &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dane-bax/&#34;&gt;Dane Bax&lt;/a&gt;, a colleague of mine, contacted me a couple of days ago with a &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt; problem, I jumped at the chance to help him, and also write a post about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dane-bax/&#34;&gt;Dane&lt;/a&gt; works for a sister company of &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/Derivco&#34;&gt;Derivco&lt;/a&gt; as a data scientist and at both &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/Derivco&#34;&gt;Derivco&lt;/a&gt; and the sister company - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microgaming.co.uk/&#34;&gt;Microgaming&lt;/a&gt; we are now looking at using SQL Server Machine Learning Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His problem was that he wanted to use a CRAN package - &lt;code&gt;bsts&lt;/code&gt; - which is not part of a standard SQL Server R installation. He tried a couple of things to get it installed but got errors, so he decided to get in touch with me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
