<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Debezium on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>/categories/debezium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Debezium on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 19:05:33 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/debezium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Stream Data to Event Hubs from Databases Using Kafka Connect &amp; Debezium in Docker - I</title>
      <link>/2022/01/10/how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---i/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 19:05:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/01/10/how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the first of two looking at if and how we can stream data to Event Hubs from Debezium. Initially I had planned only one post covering this, but it turned out that the post would be too long, so therefore I split it in two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started with the post, &lt;a href=&#34;/2022/01/02/how-to-use-kafka-client-with-azure-event-hubs/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Use Kafka Client with Azure Event Hubs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In that post, I looked at how the Kafka client can publish messages to - not only - &lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/strong&gt; but also &lt;strong&gt;Azure Event Hubs&lt;/strong&gt;. In the post, I said something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An interesting point here is that it is not only your Kafka applications that can publish to Event Hubs but any application that uses Kafka Client 1.0+, like Kafka Connect connectors!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, for you who know me, I said that without having tested it properly, but: &lt;em&gt;how hard can it be? What could possibly go wrong?&lt;/em&gt;. Well, I was called upon it by a guy who had read the post. He told me he had tried what I said at one time or the other, and it hadn&amp;rsquo;t worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post (the first), we look at configuring Kafka Connect to connect to Event Hubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Deploy the Debezium SQL Server Connector to Docker</title>
      <link>/2021/08/07/how-to-deploy-the-debezium-sql-server-connector-to-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 06:02:12 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/08/07/how-to-deploy-the-debezium-sql-server-connector-to-docker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been doing a couple of conference talks lately (virtual, of course) about streaming data from SQL Server to Kafka. The title of the presentation is &lt;strong&gt;Free Your SQL Server Data With Kafka&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the presentation, I talk (and show) various ways of getting data from SQL Server to Kafka. One of the ways I cover is Microsoft CDC, together with Debezium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I do the presentation, I always have a SQL Server installed locally, and I run Kafka in Docker. Without fail, every time I set up the environment, I cannot remember how to deploy the Debezium SQL Server Connector into Docker. Therefore I decided to write this post to have something to go back to for next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>