<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>streamprocessing on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/streamprocessing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in streamprocessing on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 09:02:50 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/streamprocessing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 43, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-10-29-interesting-stuff---week-43-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 09:02:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-10-29-interesting-stuff---week-43-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🚀 This week, we delve into game-changing developments like Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s AutoGen, which accelerates AI development with automated features. Explore the remarkable growth of LLM-based autonomous agents and their potential to achieve human-like intelligence. Learn about TimeGPT, a cutting-edge model for time series forecasting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about RisingWave 1.3, an open-source streaming database with advanced features. Plus, get ready for an exciting blog series on Generative AI and Kafka. Lastly, join Niels at the &lt;strong&gt;AI/ML &amp;amp; Data Infusion Roadshow Durban&lt;/strong&gt; for an exceptional tech event. Stay updated with the latest tech trends - read on! 💡&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 36, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-09-10-interesting-stuff---week-36-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 09:25:38 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-09-10-interesting-stuff---week-36-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, discover event-driven systems with Dapr in Kubernetes, delve into AI compilers by Microsoft Research, and learn about OpenTelemetry for observability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uncover Formula 1 streaming data pipelines with Python, Kafka, RisingWave, and Confluent Cloud&amp;rsquo;s role in real-time insurance quotes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me at Data Saturday Cape Town on September 30th, and save the date for AI &amp;amp; Data Infusion Roadshow Durban on November 11th.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 22, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-06-04-interesting-stuff---week-22-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 09:09:44 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-06-04-interesting-stuff---week-22-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post, I share some interesting links and insights on generative AI for analytics, Microsoft Fabric, and real-time streaming. You will see links about using natural language queries to access data in Amazon RDS using OpenAI and LangChain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to leverage Microsoft Fabric to simplify and enhance your data solutions with Power BI and other Azure products and how to use Kusto Query Language and Kqlmagic in Fabric notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to compare and choose stream processing platforms for your use cases and detect and filter PII data from unstructured data streams using Confluent and machine learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the full post for more details and examples.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
