<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blogging on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/categories/blogging/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blogging on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2018 09:38:50 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Test Post and Feed Apologies</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-08-18-test-post-and-feed-apologies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2018 09:38:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-08-18-test-post-and-feed-apologies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-08-18-goodbye-jekyll-welcome-hugo/&#34;&gt;Goodbye Jekyll, Welcome Hugo!&lt;/a&gt; post I wrote how I have changed blog engine from Jekyll to Hugo, and how everything seemed to work. Saying that obviously jinxed it, as after I deployed to the hosting site my Atom feed was completely hosed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have now spent 4 hours trying to fix everything, but I am not sure I have succeeded. So this is a test post to see if things look OK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye Jekyll, Welcome Hugo!</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-08-18-goodbye-jekyll-welcome-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2018 05:03:30 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-08-18-goodbye-jekyll-welcome-hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2013 I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-02-moving-to-a-new-blog-engine/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about how I moved from a self hosted &lt;strong&gt;WordPress&lt;/strong&gt; blog to a static blog; &lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OctoPress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. OctoPress spoke to my &amp;ldquo;geeky&amp;rdquo; side, as the foundation of it is the static blog-generator &lt;a href=&#34;https://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jekyll&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which in turn is Ruby based. In fact, OctoPress is more or less just some extra Ruby plugins on top of Jekyll, and to generate sites with OctoPress / Ruby you need Ruby installed on you machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that by changing the blog platform, I might write more posts just due to the &amp;ldquo;geekiness&amp;rdquo; of the blog engine. Fast forward to the end of 2016, and the number of posts I had written since the switch came to a grand total of three. Those three includes the post where I announced the switch. Yeah, switching increased indeed my productivity - NOT!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does this have to do with anything?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing, Testing, Anyone Out There?</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2016-12-28-testing-testing-anyone-out-there/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 14:18:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2016-12-28-testing-testing-anyone-out-there/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What can I say, I am crap at this &amp;ldquo;blogging&amp;rdquo; thing! Three years ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-02-moving-to-a-new-blog-engine/&#34;&gt;resuscitated my blog&lt;/a&gt;, after a hiatus of one year. I also switched blog engine from WordPress to &lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OctoPress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (which at that stage was version 2). At the time of the switch, I had had a one year hiatus of blogging (I am not a very prolific blog writer :)), and I remember I was very tempted to write in that &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-02-moving-to-a-new-blog-engine/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, that if I cannot keep up blogging I will quit. Boy, am I glad I did not write that!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing Octopress on Windows</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-06-install-octopress-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2013 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-06-install-octopress-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In an earlier &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-02-moving-to-a-new-blog-engine/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote how I had changed blog-engine from WordPress to &lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OctoPress&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. At the moment I am running Windows as my main OS (mostly due to work related requirements), and - as OctoPress is very much Ruby and Python based - there are certain things to be aware of when installing this on Windows. Furthermore, my blog is now hosted on &lt;strong&gt;Windows Azure&lt;/strong&gt; - so, with all this in mind, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d put together a blog post about the set-up of OctoPress on Windows, running on Windows Azure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving to a New Blog Engine</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-02-moving-to-a-new-blog-engine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2013-10-02-moving-to-a-new-blog-engine/</guid>
      <description>Every so often I get an itch, and I want to try out a new blog-platform. The time has now come to leave my self-hosted WordPress and move on to something &amp;ldquo;geekier&amp;rdquo; (I am a geek after all).
I have just now finished moving my few posts from WordPress to the new engine: OctoPress. In a future blog post on the new blog I will try to explain why I made the move, and why OctoPress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2009-08-09-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2009 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2009-08-09-twitter/</guid>
      <description>As the saying goes; &amp;ldquo;It is hard to learn an old dog new tricks&amp;rdquo;, but&amp;hellip; Even though I am a really old dog, I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to learn a bit about &amp;ldquo;social networking&amp;rdquo;, and therefore I created an account on Twitter a couple of days ago. Hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to be more active on Twitter than what I&amp;rsquo;ve been here at the blog. Well, that should not be too hard, seeing how infrequent I post here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
