<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RevoScaleR on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/revoscaler/</link>
    <description>Recent content in RevoScaleR on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 16:57:01 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/revoscaler/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Installing R Packages in SQL Server Machine Learning Services - II</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-06-30-installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 16:57:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-06-30-installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the second post in a series about installing R packages in SQL Server Machine Learning Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see all posts in the series go to 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/sql_server_ml_services_install_packages&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install R Packages in SQL Server ML Services Series&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why this series came about is a colleague of mine 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dane-bax/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dane&lt;/a&gt; pinged me and asked if I had any advice as he had issues installing an R package into one of their SQL Server instances. I tried to help him and then thought it would make a good topic for a blog post. Of course, at that time I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it would be more posts than one, but here we are.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 15</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-04-15-interesting-stuff---week-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 10:20:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-04-15-interesting-stuff---week-15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog-post is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2017 - Python Executing Inside SQL Server</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-20-sql-server-2017---python-executing-from-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 20:49:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-20-sql-server-2017---python-executing-from-sql/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 19, 2017 Microsoft held an on-line conference &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Data Amp&lt;/strong&gt; to showcase how Microsoft’s latest innovations put data, analytics and artificial intelligence at the heart of business transformation. The keynotes speakers were 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_Guthrie&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scott &amp;ldquo;Red Shirt&amp;rdquo; Guthrie&lt;/a&gt; who is an &lt;em&gt;Microsoft Executive Vice President&lt;/em&gt; (fairly high on the food-chain), and 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://social.technet.microsoft.com/Profile/Joseph%20Sirosh&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joseph Sirosh&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;em&gt;Corporate Vice President&lt;/em&gt;, head of the Information Management and Machine Learning group. Joseph probably knows a thing or two about data, and Scott - well, Scott knows &lt;strong&gt;A LOT&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the keynotes, Scott and Joseph shared how Microsoft’s latest innovations put data, analytics and artificial intelligence at the heart of business transformation. A big enabler for this is &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2017&lt;/strong&gt; (the &amp;ldquo;artist&amp;rdquo; formerly known as SQL Server V.Next), which introduces a lot of very cool new &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote speeches were followed by recorded short:ish sessions drilling down into certain aspects of Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s new offerings. If you are interested in the various presentations at &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Data Amp&lt;/strong&gt;, they all are on 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://channel9.msdn.com/Events/Data-Science/Microsoft-Data-Amp-2017&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Channel 9&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What caught my eye was the announcement of how &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2017&lt;/strong&gt; now supports Python as an extensible script engine. When Microsoft introduced support for R in SQL Server 2016, rumors immediately surfaced how other engines also would be supported, where Python was high on the list (

&lt;a href=&#34;https://julialang.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; another one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing that I am somewhat into &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server R Services&lt;/strong&gt; (the SQL Server 2016 flavor) 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-03-04-microsoft-sql-server-2016-r-services-installation/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-03-18-microsoft-sql-server-r-services---internals-i/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-02-microsoft-sql-server-r-services---internals-ii/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-13-microsoft-sql-server-r-services---internals-iii/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and more posts to come, I really had to have a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post is a brief introduction to executing Python code in &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2017&lt;/strong&gt;, in essence I just want to be able to execute some sort of Python code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microsoft SQL Server 2016 R Services Installation</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-03-04-microsoft-sql-server-2016-r-services-installation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2017 10:19:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-03-04-microsoft-sql-server-2016-r-services-installation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks beck I wrote a 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-25-microsoft-r-server/&#34;&gt;blog-post where I compared CRAN R with Microsoft R Server&lt;/a&gt;. The comparison was basically how large data sets are handled. In the post I mentioned that SQL Server 2016 (and later) is the delivery mechanism for Microsoft R Server on the Windows platform. In this post we will look at how to install and enable SQL Server R Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is the first in a series of posts about SQL Server R Services and to see other posts (including this) in the series, go to 

&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/sql_server_2k16_r_services&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQL Server R Services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
