<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Niels Berglund</title>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com"/>
  <updated>2021-07-04T09:04:04+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://nielsberglund.com/</id>
  <generator uri="http://gohugo.io/">Hugo</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 27, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/07/04/interesting-stuff---week-27-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-07-04T09:04:04+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/07/04/interesting-stuff---week-27-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2021/06/30/looking-to-the-future-for-r-in-azure-sql-and-sql-server/">Looking to the future for R in Azure SQL and SQL Server</a>. If you follow my blog, you know that I have written a lot about <a href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/sql-server-machine-learning-services/">SQL Server Machine Learning Services</a> (SQLML) and R in SQL Server throughout the last couple of years. The post linked to lays out the plans for R in SQL Server in upcoming SQL Server versions. The short version of the post is that Microsoft will go away from the proprietary R and Python packages in SQLML in favour of the open-source versions. If you are interested and want more than what is in the post, my good friend <a href="https://tecflix.com/instructors/rafal-lukawiecki">Rafal Lukawiecki</a> has written an <a href="https://tecflix.com/news/microsoft-open-sources-sql-server-machine-learning-and-discontinues-ml-server">excellent post</a> explaining in detail the changes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://nemeiskiy-lef.medium.com/implementing-distributed-transaction-in-net-using-saga-pattern-1641172c122">Implementing distributed transaction in .NET using Saga pattern</a>. One of the biggest issues when moving from a monolithic system to a distributed microservices system is handling transactions. One solution to distributed transactions in a microservices system is using the <a href="https://microservices.io/patterns/data/saga.html">Saga</a> pattern. In this post, the author does an excellent job explaining the Saga pattern and how to implement it in .NET.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/continuous-integration-deployment-ml/">Continuous Integration and Deployment for Machine Learning Online Serving and Models</a>. This post from Uber looks at how they implement CI/CD and model serving in their environment. This is a must-read if you are in the ML world!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/easily-manage-database-migrations-with-evolving-schemas-in-ksqldb/">Online, Managed Schema Evolution with ksqlDB Migrations</a>. In the database world, managing changes to the schema is (somewhat) easy. Well, at least you probably have some workflows for that. In the streaming world, it may not be that &ldquo;straightforward&rdquo;. In this post, the author looks at the tooling available for managing schema evolution in ksqlDB.</li>
<li><a href="https://itnext.io/eventual-consistency-with-spring-for-apache-kafka-cfbbed450b5e">Eventual Consistency with Spring for Apache Kafka: Part 1 of 2</a>. This post looks at how Spring for Kafka is used to manage a distributed data model across multiple microservices. You find <a href="https://itnext.io/eventual-consistency-with-spring-for-apache-kafka-part-2-of-2-23bedd512ccf">Part 2 here</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/data-enrichment-with-kafka-streams-foreign-key-joins/">Crossing the Streams: The New Streaming Foreign-Key Join Feature in Kafka Streams</a>. In relational databases, you more often than not have multiple one-to-many relationships (foreign keys). This is not well supported in KTables and streams in Kafka. At least it was not until Kafka 2.4, where non-key joining between KTables was introduced. The post I link to looks more in detail at how foreign-key joins are implemented in KStreams. This is only available in KStreams, but according to the post, we may expect to see it in the next release of ksqlDB; 0.19 - Yay!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 26, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/27/interesting-stuff---week-26-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-06-27T09:21:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/27/interesting-stuff---week-26-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/06/23/need-for-data-centric-ml-platforms.html">Need for Data-centric ML Platforms</a>. When we do ML projects, it comes naturally to have a model-centric approach to the project. This Databricks blog post argues that having a data-centric view increases the chances for success. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.sqlshack.com/azure-data-explorer-and-the-kusto-query-language/">Azure Data Explorer and the Kusto Query Language</a>. This blog post is part one of a two-part series looking at Azure Data Explorer (ADX) and Kusto; its query language. This post introduces ADX and looks briefly into what you can do with Kusto. After having read this post, I look forward to part two!</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer/update-on-geospatial-functions/ba-p/2446350">Update on geospatial functions</a>. In last weeks <a href="/2021/06/20/interesting-stuff---week-25-2021/">roundup</a>, I mentioned a post about geospatial functions in Apache Pinot. The post I link to is also about geospatial functions, but this time in Azure Data Explorer. Man, you can do some cool stuff with geospatial queries!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/06/22/get-your-free-copy-of-delta-lake-the-definitive-guide-early-release.html">Get Your Free Copy of Delta Lake: The Definitive Guide (Early Release)</a>. Databricks has for a long time been talking about the Lakehouse architecture and how their Delta Lake table format can help create Lakehouses. This post announces the first book about Delta Lake and Lakehouses. I have already downloaded the book, and I suggest you do the same.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming-data-architecture">Streaming / Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/distributed-domain-driven-architecture-data-mesh-best-practices/">Saxo Bank&rsquo;s Best Practices for a Distributed Domain-Driven Architecture Founded on the Data Mesh</a>. I have covered posts about the Data Mesh in quite a few previous roundups, and this post is another one around data meshes. It looks at how Saxo Bank in Denmark has moved to a domain-driven data architecture with Kafka as an integral part and the lessons learned/best practices. The post also contains very, very useful references! The post is a must-read if you are interested in data architecture!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Neils_Berglund_IAmSpeaking.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>I Am Speaking</em></p>

<p>As I mentioned in the <a href="/2021/06/13/interesting-stuff---week-24-2021/">roundup</a> for week 24, I am speaking about Apache Kafka and Azure Data Explorer at the <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/"><strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong></a>. So right now, I am researching and prepping for that.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/20/interesting-stuff---week-25-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-06-20T07:52:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/20/interesting-stuff---week-25-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/06/17/announcing-photon-public-preview-the-next-generation-query-engine-on-the-databricks-lakehouse-platform.html">Announcing Photon Public Preview: The Next Generation Query Engine on the Databricks Lakehouse Platform</a>. This post looks at the new vectorized query engine on Databricks; Photon. It is included as part of a new high-performance runtime designed to run SQL workloads faster and reduce the total cost per workload.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/apache-pinot-developer-blog/introduction-to-geospatial-queries-in-apache-pinot-b63e2362e2a9">Introduction to Geospatial Queries in Apache Pinot</a>. Geospatial data has become increasingly important when analyzing Big Data. Deriving insights from timely and accurate geospatial data can enable mission-critical use cases in organizations and give them a competitive edge. Geospatial support has recently been added to Apache Pinot, and this post looks at the challenges of analyzing geospatial at scale and how it is implemented in Apache Pinot.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.gentlydownthe.stream/">Gently down the stream: A gentle introduction to Apache Kafka</a>. This is a fantastic introduction to Kafka! Nothing more needs to be said!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/rethinking-distributed-stream-processing-in-kafka/">Consistency and Completeness: Rethinking Distributed Stream Processing in Apache Kafka</a>. As the title implies, this post looks at how Consistency and Completeness are implemented in Apache Kafka and Kafka Streams. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/derivco_derivco-tech-thursday-webinar-activity-6811654769594253312-PGbL/">Revolutionise how you develop software with GitHub</a>. This is not so much what I am doing, but what a colleague and mate is doing. <a href="https://gordonbeeming.xyz/">Gordon Beeming</a>, Microsoft MVP and Devops guru, is doing a <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> Tech-Thursday Webinar Thursday, June 24. Gordon looks at some new GitHub features in the webinar, allowing you to deliver more value to your customers. The webinar is public, and you can sign up <a href="https://derivco.co.za/tech-thursday-webinar/">here</a>. Don&rsquo;t miss it!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 24, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/13/interesting-stuff---week-24-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-06-13T10:39:45+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/13/interesting-stuff---week-24-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://thechief.io/c/editorial/introduction-to-chaos-engineering/">Introduction to Chaos Engineering</a>. The post linked here looks at the origin, principles, and benefits of Chaos Engineering. Chaos Engineering is when you try to disrupt and break an application system to build resilience. Notice that the post is behind a paywall.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ververica.com/blog/flink-powered-model-serving-real-time-feature-generation-at-razorpay">Flink-powered model serving &amp; real-time feature generation at Razorpay</a>. This post, which is from back in December 2020, looks at how Apache Flink is being utilized as a way to overcome challenges around feature generation and machine learning model serving in real-time. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/06/09/how-to-build-a-scalable-wide-and-deep-product-recommender.html">How to Build a Scalable Wide and Deep Product Recommender</a>. A Wide and Deep Learning Model consists of two parts; a machine learning part (linear model) and a neural network part. This type of model is often used in recommender systems, and the blog post linked looks at how you can do it using Databricks.</li>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/automate-machine-learning-using-databricks-automl-a-glass-box-approach-and-mlflow-2543a8143687">Automate Machine Learning using Databricks AutoML — A Glass Box Approach and MLFLow</a>. During the <a href="https://databricks.com/dataaisummit/north-america-2021">Data + AI Summit 2021</a>, Databricks announced their Databricks AutoML platform. This post looks at using Databricks AutoML Platform to automatically apply machine learning to a dataset and deploy the model to production using the REST API.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://tech.ebayinc.com/engineering/block-aggregator-real-time-data-ingestion-from-kafka-to-clickhouse-with-deterministic-retries/">Block Aggregator: Real-time Data Ingestion from Kafka to ClickHouse with Deterministic Retries</a>. This post discusses the message-processing engine eBay developed to avoid data loss or duplication during delivery from Kafka to ClickHouse. I found the post very interesting as we are looking at similar things at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> right now.</li>
<li><a href="https://thecodinginterface.com/blog/serverless-kafka-with-aws-lambda/">Serverless Event Driven Systems with Confluent Cloud and AWS Lambda</a>. This post presents an end-to-end example of a Serverless event-driven architecture using Confluent Cloud for stream processing paired with AWS Lambda for event responsive logic using the Serverless Application Model (SAM) framework.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/create-kafka-messages-from-within-control-center-for-better-kafka-management/">How to Better Manage Apache Kafka by Creating Kafka Messages from within Control Center</a>. This post is the first in a series looking some new features to Control Center, introduced in Confluent Platform 6.2.0. Some very cool stuff here!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In <a href="/2021/06/06/interesting-stuff---week-23-2021/">last weeks roundup</a>, I mentioned I was looking into <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-explorer/data-explorer-overview"><strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong></a> as I was thinking about creating some presentations for upcoming conferences. I did submit a couple of topics to some conferences, and I had two conferences accepting talks! Woohoo! The conferences and talks are:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/"><strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong></a>: <strong>How to do Real-Time Analytics Using Apache Kafka and Azure Data Explorer</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/future-data-driven-summit-event-tickets-157885366381"><strong>Future Data Driven</strong></a>: <strong>Analyze Billions of Rows of Data in Real-Time Using Azure Data Explorer</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p>So now having the above talks accepted, I really need to get going with prep. I am stoked!</p>

<p>Oh, and I am still doing the <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/product/big-data-analytics-with-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-by-niels-berglund/"><strong>Big Data &amp; Analytics with SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong></a> training class for the <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/"><strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong></a>, and if you <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/product/big-data-analytics-with-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-by-niels-berglund/">sign up</a> for the class you get free access to the summit itself!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/06/interesting-stuff---week-23-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-06-06T08:28:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/06/06/interesting-stuff---week-23-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/06/02/jump-start-your-data-projects-with-pre-built-solution-accelerators.html">Jump Start Your Data Projects with Pre-Built Solution Accelerators</a>. There is pressure on data science teams/data engineers/etc., to deliver value fast. However, it takes time to research, build data pipelines, models, etc., and this can suck up momentum. To help to overcome these obstacles, Databricks introduces in this blog post <a href="https://databricks.com/solutions/accelerators"><strong>Databricks Solution Accelerators</strong></a>. These accelerators are fully-functional pre-built code to tackle the most common and high-impact use cases for data scientists, data engineers, etc.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.flowdirector.io/new-smart-app-kafka-to-kafka-bridge-788883a68e63">New Smart App: Kafka to Kafka Bridge</a>. This post introduces the <strong>Kafka to Kafka Bridge</strong>. The bridge allows you to create message bridges between topics of the same or different Kafka brokers. We have developed something similar here at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, but I will definitely check this out!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/streaming-data-with-confluent-and-ksqldb-for-new-use-cases-with-ais/">Detecting Patterns of Behaviour in Streaming Maritime AIS Data with Confluent</a>. This is part two in a blog series on streaming a data feed Apache Kafka (the first part is <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/streaming-etl-and-analytics-for-real-time-location-tracking/">here</a>). This post looks at how <strong>ksqlDB</strong> can be used to do aggregations and pattern matching against a data feed. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Apart from working on my <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/product/big-data-analytics-with-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-by-niels-berglund/"><strong>Big Data &amp; Analytics with SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong></a> training class for the <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/"><strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong></a>, I have started looking into <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-explorer/data-explorer-overview"><strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong></a>.</p>

<p>Azure Data Explorer is a fast, fully managed data analytics service for real-time analysis on large volumes of data streaming from applications, websites, IoT devices, and more. I am looking into it because I am thinking of creating some presentations for upcoming conferences and maybe a training class. Watch this space!</p>

<p>Oh, and don&rsquo;t forget - if you <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/product/big-data-analytics-with-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-by-niels-berglund/">sign up</a> for my training class, mentioned above, at the <strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong>, you get free access to the summit itself!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 22, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/30/interesting-stuff---week-22-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-05-30T06:33:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/30/interesting-stuff---week-22-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h1 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h1>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/ai/from-conversation-to-code-microsoft-introduces-its-first-product-features-powered-by-gpt-3/">From conversation to code: Microsoft introduces its first product features powered by GPT-3</a>. Back in September 2020, Microsoft announced it had <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2020/09/22/microsoft-teams-up-with-openai-to-exclusively-license-gpt-3-language-model/">exclusively licensed GPT-3</a> -  the autoregressive language model that uses deep learning to produce human-like text. The linked-to post discusses the first incarnation of GPT-3 in Microsoft&rsquo;s Power Apps. Very, very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/05/27/introducing-databricks-machine-learning-a-data-native-collaborative-full-ml-lifecycle-solution.html">Introducing Databricks Machine Learning: a Data-native, Collaborative, Full ML Lifecycle Solution</a>. The <a href="https://databricks.com/dataaisummit/north-america-2021"><strong>Data + AI Summit 2021</strong></a> took place the week just gone by. The post I linked to talks about one of the announcements made during the summit; the launch of <strong>Databricks Machine Learning</strong>, an enterprise ML solution that is data-native, collaborative, and supports the entire ML lifecycle. I am pretty &ldquo;chuffed&rdquo; to see how the solution includes, among other things, a feature store!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/Ov5XgYzyGkU">Engaging Database Partials with Apache Kafka for Distributed System Consistency ft. Pat Helland</a>. When using various data from different systems, for example, for reports, obtaining the correct data when you need it in real-time can be difficult. In this videoed podcast, Pat Helland - (Principal Architect, Salesforce) - explains how to make educated partial answers when you need to use the Apache Kafka® platform.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/data-summit-2021.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Big Data &amp; Analytics</em></p>

<p>As mentioned in previous roundups, I deliver an Analytics on SQL Server Big Data Cluster training class at the <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/"><strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong></a>! So right now, I am creating content for the course. I am so looking forward to it!</p>

<p>If you are interested, <a href="https://youtu.be/Ov5XgYzyGkU">sign up</a> for the class. When signing up, you also get free access to the Summit! Hope to see you there!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 21, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/23/interesting-stuff---week-21-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-05-23T08:34:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/23/interesting-stuff---week-21-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/05/19/evolution-to-the-data-lakehouse.html">Evolution to the Data Lakehouse</a>. Data lakehouses have been a hot topic the last year or two, and Databricks, with its lakehouse implementation Delta Lake has been at the forefront. The post linked to looks - as the title implies - at the evolution from data warehouses to data lakes to data lakehouses. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/wix-engineering/6-event-driven-architecture-patterns-part-1-93758b253f47">6 Event-Driven Architecture Patterns — Part 1</a>. This post is the first of two. The author looks at key patterns of event-driven messaging designs that have facilitated creating a robust distributed system that can easily handle increasing traffic and storage needs. The second part of the series is <a href="https://medium.com/wix-engineering/6-event-driven-architecture-patterns-part-2-455cc73b22e1">here</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://mert.codes/harder-better-faster-stronger-apache-pinot-as-a-kafka-consumer-and-datastore-for-fast-7df25bcc7d02">&ldquo;Harder, Better, Faster, Stronger&rdquo;: Apache Pinot as a Kafka Consumer and Datastore for Fast On-the-Fly Aggregations</a>. You who read my blog have probably noticed that I am quite partial to Kafka and Apache Pinot. Well, in this blog post, we get the best of both worlds. It covers how to use Apache Pinot to do aggregations in &ldquo;near&rdquo; real-time. I found the post very interesting.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/error-handling-patterns-in-kafka/">Error Handling Patterns for Apache Kafka Applications</a>. In one of the teams I worked at in <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, we had a saying when we were going to do something we were not 100% sure of: <em>How hard can it be, what can possibly go wrong?</em>. In some cases, quite a lot could go wrong, and if we look at distributed systems, what can go wrong often goes wrong. This blog post covers different ways to handle errors and retries in event streaming applications.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/data-summit-2021.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Big Data &amp; Analytics</em></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to <a href="http://bit.ly/dps_2021">sign up</a> for my <strong>Big Data &amp; Analytics with SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong> class at the <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2021/"><strong>2021 Data Platform Summit</strong></a>!</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/16/interesting-stuff---week-20-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-05-16T08:36:10+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/16/interesting-stuff---week-20-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/netflix-cdc-events-cassandra/">Change Data Capture for Distributed Databases @Netflix</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">Infoq</a> presentation, the presenter covers the challenges associated with capturing CDC events from Cassandra, discussing the Flink ecosystem and the use of RocksDB. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://scattered-thoughts.net/writing/why-query-planning-for-streaming-systems-is-hard/">Why query planning for streaming systems is hard</a>. This post looks at some of the issues of doing query plans for streaming systems. Really interesting, and I would like to hear more about this.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/leboncoin-engineering-blog/cooling-down-hot-data-from-kafka-to-athena-5918a628bd98">Cooling down hot data: From Kafka to Athena</a>. The post linked to looks at how to move data from online Kafka Clusters to a data lake for long term data retention, analytics, legal requirements, and as input for machine learning.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/confluent-for-kubernetes-offers-cloud-native-kafka-automation/">Introducing Confluent for Kubernetes</a>. This post looks at Confluent for Kubernetes (CFK), a cloud-native control plane for deploying and managing Confluent in private cloud environments. It provides a standard and simple interface to customize, deploy, and manage Confluent Platform through declarative APIs.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>A couple of days ago, I received some very good news:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/data-summit-2021.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Big Data &amp; Analytics</em></p>

<p>As you see in <em>Figure 1</em> I will be giving a training class at the 2021 Data Platform Summit. The class is <strong>Big Data &amp; Analytics with SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>. So right now, I am creating the content for that class - it will be awesome.</p>

<p>If you are interested, <a href="http://bit.ly/dps_2021">sign up</a> for the class. When signing up, you also get free access to the Summit! Hope to see you there!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 19, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/09/interesting-stuff---week-19-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-05-09T07:07:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/09/interesting-stuff---week-19-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/optimal-feature-discovery-ml/">Optimal Feature Discovery: Better, Leaner Machine Learning Models Through Information Theory</a>. This post talks about an approach at Uber called Optimal Feature Discovery. It searches for the most compact set of features out of all available at Uber for a given model, both boosting accuracy and reducing feature count at the same time.<br /></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/serverless-data-api/">Why a Serverless Data API Might be Your Next Database</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article discusses database as a service (DBaaS) and serverless data API for cloud-based data management.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://chathura-ekanayake.medium.com/eda-implementation-integration-scenarios-66895923439">EDA implementation — Integration scenarios</a>. The post linked to is a follow up to <a href="https://chathura-ekanayake.medium.com/applying-event-driven-architecture-in-digital-transformation-projects-acbcb27440af">Applying Event-Driven Architecture in Digital Transformation Projects</a>, which discussed a generic architecture for event-driven architecture (EDA) based systems. This post explores implementation approaches for such event-driven systems by focusing on specific products and their interactions.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/streaming-etl-with-confluent-kafka-message-routing-and-fan-out/">Streaming ETL with Confluent: Routing and Fan-Out of Apache Kafka Messages with ksqlDB</a>. This post looks at how we can use ksqlDB for message routing. I quite liked the post, and I will definitely see if we can implement some of this at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 18, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/02/interesting-stuff---week-18-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-05-02T07:55:53+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/05/02/interesting-stuff---week-18-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/sql-server/inference-of-ml-models-in-sql-server-via-external-languages/ba-p/2216226">Inference of ML Models in SQL Server via External Languages</a>. SQL Server 2019 introduced the notion of External Languages, whereby we can execute calls against an external language, (Java, Python, etc.), from inside SQL Server. This post looks at scoring of ONNX models where ONXX has been registered as an external language. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-analytics">Data Analytics</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/apache-pinot-developer-blog/deploying-apache-pinot-at-a-large-retail-chain-42aed2921a38">Deploying Apache Pinot at a Large Retail Chain</a>. The post linked to here looks at the use of Apache Pinot at a large retailer and how it is used to some of the big challenges around data analytics.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/announcing-ksqldb-0-17-0-new-features-and-updates/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.17.0</a>. The title of this post says it all; it looks at the latest release of ksqlDB! Reading the post, there are quite a few interesting new features in this release. Personally, I am quite excited about the ability to do table scans! At <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, we have waited for that for a while.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-to-survive-a-kafka-outage/">How to Survive a Kafka Outage</a>. Another post where the title says it all. The post looks at various types of potential Kafka outages and options to handle the outages.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 17, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/25/interesting-stuff---week-17-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-04-25T08:21:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/25/interesting-stuff---week-17-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://lakefs.io/hudi-iceberg-and-delta-lake-data-lake-table-formats-compared/">Hudi, Iceberg and Delta Lake: Data Lake Table Formats Compared</a>. This blog post compares the lake formats Hudi, Iceberg, and Delta Lake on their platform compatibility, performance &amp; throughput, and concurrency. Interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/explorium-ai/benchmarking-sql-engines-for-data-serving-prestodb-trino-and-redshift-1c5f16d6e5da">Benchmarking SQL engines for Data Serving: PrestoDb, Trino, and Redshift</a>. The linked-to post benchmarks the SQL engines, Redshift, Trino &amp; Presto. Read the post for some interesting findings.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://scattered-thoughts.net/writing/2021-q1-roundup/">2021 Q1 roundup</a>. The author of this post is a freelance researcher, and he is doing quite a lot of work related to streaming. This post is a roundup of what he has done during the first quarter of this year. There are some very interesting pieces in there!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-2-8-0-features-and-improvements-with-early-access-to-kip-500/">What&rsquo;s New in Apache Kafka 2.8</a>. This post, as the title implies, announces the latest version of Apache Kafka: 2.8. Ok, so what is the big deal with that? The big deal is that this version is the first version where you can run Kafka without ZooKeeper! This is not recommended for production, but you can definitely test it out!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 16, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/18/interesting-stuff---week-16-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-04-18T11:52:42+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/18/interesting-stuff---week-16-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://rockset.com/blog/rocksdb-is-eating-the-database-world/">RocksDB Is Eating the Database World</a>. This blog post looks at RocksDB, what it is and how it works. When reading the post, I was surprised by how many distributed databases used RocksDB as the layer to abstract access to local storage.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2021/04/microsoft-zero3-offload">Microsoft Releases AI Training Library ZeRO-3 Offload</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article looks at Microsoft&rsquo;s ZeRO-3 Offload, which is an extension of the DeepSpeed AI training library. ZeRO-3 Offload improves memory efficiency while training very large deep-learning models. It allows users to train models with up to 40 billion parameters on a single GPU and over 2 trillion parameters on 512 GPUs. Impressive!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-sql">Azure SQL</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2021/04/12/azure-sql-digital-event-innovate-today-with-azure-sql/">Azure SQL digital event: Innovate today with Azure SQL</a>. The post linked to here is an invitation to an Azure SQL event. The event looks at how to build an effective cloud database management strategy. I will definitely attend!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/-50rsy0qK9M">Kafka Connect 101: Configuration, Connectors, Converters, and Transforms</a>. This is an excellent video doing what the title says; it covers how Kafka Connect works! I found it very informative! Oh, and BTW - Tim and I are not related!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 15, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/11/interesting-stuff---week-15-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-04-11T10:05:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/11/interesting-stuff---week-15-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster">SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2021/04/07/whats-new-with-sql-server-big-data-clusters-cu10-release/">What&rsquo;s new with SQL Server Big Data Clusters—CU10 release</a>. This post announces the release of SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster CU10 and some of the new and improved functionality. As soon as I have time, I will install it and &ldquo;take it for a ride&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/data-discovery-the-future-of-data-catalogs-for-data-lakes-7b50e2e8cb28">Data Discovery: The Future of Data Catalogs for Data Lakes</a>. The post linked to here discusses how we can prevent our data lakes from becoming data swamps. The key to this is data discovery and data catalogs. I like this post, and it has given me a lot to think about.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/apache-pinot-developer-blog/introduction-to-upserts-in-apache-pinot-987c12149d93">Introduction to Upserts in Apache Pinot</a>. In version 0.6 of Apache Pinot, a new feature was made available for stream ingestion, allowing you to upsert events from an immutable log. You may be familiar with upserts from the database world, however in Apache Pinot, an upsert is somewhat different than what you have in a database, and this post looks at what it is and why it is exciting.</li>
<li><a href="https://whylabs.ai/blog/posts/integrating-whylogs-into-your-kafka-ml-pipeline">Integrating whylogs into your Kafka ML Pipeline</a>. WhyLogs is an open-source data quality library that uses advanced data science statistics to log and monitor data used in AI/ML applications. This blog post looks at how we can integrate WhyLogs in Kafka to evaluate, monitor and detect statistical anomalies in streaming data. This is very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 14, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/04/interesting-stuff---week-14-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-04-04T12:11:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/04/04/interesting-stuff---week-14-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning-data-science-ai">Machine Learning / Data Science / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/data-for-ai/building-real-time-ml-pipelines-with-a-feature-store-9f90091eeb4">Building Real-Time ML Pipelines with a Feature Store</a>. The term Feature Store is gaining popularity in the Machine Learning world. It is - as the name implies - something that stores feature data. However, it also runs pipelines that transform raw data into feature values, and it serves feature data for training and inference purposes. Most feature stores are batch-oriented, but they must move beyond batch and also become able to handle real-time data. This blog post looks at transitioning from batch to real-time.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/04/02/data-ai-summit-is-back.html">Data + AI Summit Is Back</a>. This post leads to a link for registration for the North American leg of <a href="https://databricks.com/dataaisummit/north-america-2021">Data + AI Summit</a>. The schedule looks awesome, and I&rsquo;ll definitely register!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pinterest-engineering/open-sourcing-querybook-pinterests-collaborative-big-data-hub-ba2605558883">Open sourcing Querybook, Pinterest&rsquo;s collaborative big data hub</a>. Pinterest is a data-driven company, and it is more important than ever for teams to be able to compose queries, create analyses, and collaborate with one another. To enable that, Pinterest built Querybook. This post looks at what Querybook is and how they got to the point of open-sourcing it.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2021/03/31/top-questions-from-customers-about-delta-lake.html">Top Questions from Customers about Delta Lake</a>. Databricks Delta Lake is a hot topic, and many people have questions about it. This post aims to answer some of those questions.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-without-zookeeper-a-sneak-peek/">Apache Kafka Made Simple: A First Glimpse of a Kafka Without ZooKeeper</a>. There has been lots of talk about removing ZooKeeper as a dependency for Kafka. Finally, we are almost there, and the upcoming Kafka release will have the ability to run without ZooKeeper - yay! The blog post linked to looks at the implications of the removal and its impact on - among other things - scalability and performance (spoiler alert: improvements!). Very cool &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/monitor-kafka-clusters-with-prometheus-grafana-and-confluent/">Monitoring Your Event Streams: Integrating Confluent with Prometheus and Grafana</a>. Managing and monitoring a system like Kafka, is not and easy feat. But there are help; this is part 1 of a three-part blog series that will explain how to effectively monitor your event streams. This post looks at integration with third party tools such as Prometheus and Grafana.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 13, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/28/interesting-stuff---week-13-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-03-28T09:41:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/28/interesting-stuff---week-13-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/event-driven-utopia/5-reasons-why-you-should-use-microsoft-dapr-to-build-event-driven-microservices-cb2202c579a0">5 Reasons Why You Should Use Microsoft Dapr to Build Event-driven Microservices</a>. Dapr is a portable, event-driven runtime, and it helps developers build event-driven, resilient distributed applications. As the name implies, the post linked to looks at some of the reasons to use <a href="https://dapr.io/">Dapr</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2021/03/alibaba-dapr/">Alibaba Cloud Uses Dapr to Support Its Business Growth</a>. I doubt that the Alibaba crowd read the post above, but they use Dapr extensively. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> post looks at some of the reasons why Alibaba chose Dapr. Quite interesting read!</li>
<li><a href="http://muratbuffalo.blogspot.com/2021/03/sundial-fault-tolerant-clock.html">Sundial: Fault-tolerant Clock Synchronization for Datacenters</a>. The post linked to here gives an excellent explanation of time synchronization challenges and fundamental techniques to achieve precise time synchronization in data centers.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/sql-server/configure-sql-server-ag-read-scale-for-sql-containers-deployed/ba-p/2224742">Configure SQL Server AG (Read-Scale) for SQL Containers deployed on Kubernetes using Helm</a>. This post looks at how to setup Always On Availability Group (AG) between SQL instances deployed as SQL containers on Kubernetes. As a SQL old-timer, I still can&rsquo;t believe we can run SQL on Linux and in Kubernetes!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/nerd-for-tech/catching-data-in-a-data-mesh-principles-part-i-2b2e11e9e33a">Catching Data In a Data Mesh: Principles (Part I)</a>. This post is part of a series intending to give an in-depth view of how the Data Mesh architectural paradigm helps to build a data platform. This is part one, explaining the thinking about the mesh and the guiding principles for the implementation. After reading this post, be sure to read <a href="https://medium.com/codex/catching-data-in-a-data-mesh-applied-part-ii-114cae4d139a">part two</a> as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://rpradeepmenon.medium.com/making-data-lakehouse-real-yet-effective-f09e84fae0fa">Making Data Lakehouse real yet effective</a>. In previous roundups, I have linked to posts about data warehouses, data lakes, data lakehouses, etc. The post I link to here tries to explore and explain how all this hangs together.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/feature-store-data-platform-for-machine-learning-455122c48229">Feature Store: Data Platform for Machine Learning</a>. Feature stores are a relatively recent &ldquo;innovation&rdquo; in the Machine Learning world. A feature store is a data system that runs data pipelines that transform raw data into feature values, stores and manages the feature data, and serves feature data consistently for training and inference purposes. The post I link to here surveys the leading feature stores. As a side note: if you want to read more about feature stores, browse over to <a href="https://www.featurestore.org/">Feature Store for ML</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-search-and-analytics-with-confluent-cloud-azure-redis-spring-cloud/">Integrating Azure and Confluent: Real-Time Search Powered by Azure Cache for Redis, Spring Cloud</a>. This article looks at an architecture pattern that transforms an existing traditional transaction system into a real-time data processing system. Don&rsquo;t get hung up on the components used (Redis Cache, Spring Cloud), as what the article covers is applicable for different tech-stacks as well.</li>
<li><a href="https://levelup.gitconnected.com/event-driven-architecture-demo-29f5649144b7">Event-Driven Architecture Demo</a>. As the title says, this post looks at a completely event-driven system, incorporating Kafka and GraphQL. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 12, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/21/interesting-stuff---week-12-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-03-21T09:15:37+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/21/interesting-stuff---week-12-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<p>.NET</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/azure-sql/configurable-retry-logic-for-microsoft-data-sqlclient/">Introducing Configurable Retry Logic in Microsoft.Data.SqlClient v3.0.0-Preview1</a>. This is so cool! One of the harder things to get right when writing applications accessing databases is retries. The post I  link to here discusses the new retry feature in the .NET SqlClient library. Very awesome!</li>
<li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/opentelemetry-net-reaches-v1-0/">OpenTelemetry .NET reaches v1.0</a>. As the title of the post implies, this blog-post discusses version 1 of OpenTelemetry .NET. It is cool to see that .NET supports OpenTelemetry!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/ft-product-technology/financial-times-data-platform-from-zero-to-hero-143156bffb1d">Financial Times Data Platform: From zero to hero</a>. This blog post &ldquo;drills&rdquo; down into how Financial Times created and evolved their data platform.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/introducing-dbt-the-etl-elt-disrupter-4351adc34123">Introducing dbt, the ETL &amp; ELT Disrupter</a>. Admittedly, this post&rsquo;s title is somewhat click-bait:y, but the post is interesting nevertheless. It looks at <a href="https://www.getdbt.com/">dbt</a>, (Data Build Tool), which is a command-line data pipeline tool that allows collecting and transforming data for analytics really fast, and really easy!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://rockset.com/blog/building-a-real-time-customer-360-on-kafka-mongodb-and-rockset/">Building a Real-Time Customer 360 on Kafka, MongoDB and Rockset</a>. The post here looks at how one can build a holistic view of a customer, (Customer 360 Profile), and have the view being real-time. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 11, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/14/interesting-stuff---week-11-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-03-14T07:26:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/14/interesting-stuff---week-11-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/building-a-data-platform-in-2021-b759f6470426">Building a Data Platform in 2021</a>. This post looks at building a modern, scalable data platform to power analytics and data science projects. It was a handy read for me, as we are looking at these things in <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> at the moment.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theseattledataguy.com/what-is-starburst-data-and-why-you-should-use-it-data-engineering-consulting/">What Is Starburst Data And Why You Should Use It – Data Engineering Consulting</a>. Trino, (the &ldquo;artist&rdquo; formerly known as PrestoDB) is an open-source distributed SQL query engine for running interactive analytic queries against data sources of all sizes ranging from gigabytes to petabytes. As Trino was developed as a bare-bones SQL Engine, you&rsquo;ll have to manage scaling, security, monitoring, and create new connections on your own. That is where Starburst Data comes in, it makes quite a few things a lot easier for using Trino, and this post looks more in detail at what Starburst Data can do.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-analytics-with-kafka-and-pinot/">Under the Hood of Real-Time Analytics with Apache Kafka and Pinot</a>. Recently I have linked to posts about Apache Pinot, and I do so here again. This post looks at the inner workings of Kafka and Pinot when using them together. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/kafka/">Disaster Recovery for Multi-Region Kafka at Uber</a>. Uber has one of the largest deployments of Apache Kafka in the world, processing trillions of messages and multiple petabytes of data per day. They want to provide a scalable, reliable, performant, and easy-to-use messaging platform on top of Apache Kafka. This article highlights how they solved recovering from disasters like cluster downtime, and it also describes how they built a multi-region Apache Kafka infrastructure.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/integrate-kafka-and-jaeger-for-distributed-tracing-and-monitoring/">Integrating Apache Kafka Clients with CNCF Jaeger at Funding Circle Using OpenTelemetry</a>. A key challenge in a Kafka based microservice architecture is understanding the system as a whole due to the decentralized nature and constant evolution of new and existing services. This post covers the basics for understanding what options are available for Apache Kafka telemetry when it comes to distributed tracing.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-to-tune-rocksdb-kafka-streams-state-stores-performance/">How to Tune RocksDB for Your Kafka Streams Application</a>. When building Kafka Streams applications holding state, Kafka Streams uses local state stores that are made fault-tolerant by associated changelog topics stored in Kafka, and RocksDB backs these stores. The blog post linked to covers key concepts that show how Kafka Streams uses RocksDB to maintain its state and how RocksDB can be tuned for Kafka Streams&rsquo; state stores.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 10, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/07/interesting-stuff---week-10-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-03-07T06:44:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/03/07/interesting-stuff---week-10-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/internals-of-the-poh/">Internals of the POH</a>. A new kind of heap was added in .NET 5, called the POH (Pinned Object Heap). This blog entry explains the internals of it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-systems">Distributed Systems</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://muratbuffalo.blogspot.com/2021/02/foundational-distributed-systems-papers.html">Foundational distributed systems papers</a>. It is well known that if someone wants to develop competence and expertise in their fields, reading technical research papers is - almost - a must. <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> has compiled a list of foundational papers in the distributed systems area in the blog post here. Go ahead and read!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://db.cs.cmu.edu/seminar2021/">VACCINATION DATABASE TECH TALKS - 2021</a>. The &ldquo;Vaccination Database Tech Talks&rdquo; is an on-line seminar series at Carnegie Mellon University with leading developers and researchers of database systems. Each speaker will present the implementation details of their respective systems and examples of the technical challenges that they faced when working with real-world customers. I have had a look at some of them, and they are really interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ai-machine-learning">AI/Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/how-microsoft-icebreaker-addresses-the-cold-start-challenge-in-machine-learning-models-dc68fdb0fee1">How Microsoft Icebreaker Addresses the Cold-Start Challenge in Machine Learning Models</a>. This post looks at a framework for intelligent acquisition of training data. This, in turn, allows the deployment of machine learning models that can operate with little or no-training data.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kafka-summit.org/">KAFKA SUMMIT 2021</a>. It is this time of the year again; conference time. The page linked to here is the registration page for Kafka Summit 2021. It allows you to register for the three different (virtual) summits this year. I have registered for the <a href="https://www.kafka-summit.org/events/kafka-summit-europe-2021/about">Europe Summit</a>. I suggest you do the same!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 9, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/02/28/interesting-stuff---week-9-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-28T09:46:34+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/02/28/interesting-stuff---week-9-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/beyond-rest-1b76f7c20ef6">Beyond REST</a>. This <a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/">Netflix</a> blog post discusses how Netflix use <a href="https://dev.to/mrfrontend/graphql-microservices-architecture-by-apollo-1m75">GraphQL microservices</a> as a backend platform, facilitating rapid application development. It looks very interesting. I wonder if we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> could use this?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="analytics">Analytics</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/apache-pinot-developer-blog/building-a-climate-dashboard-with-apache-pinot-and-superset-d3ee8cb7941d">Building a Climate Dashboard with Apache Pinot and Superset</a>. Hmm, somehow, I must have missed this blog post from back in September 2020. Anyway, better late than never. The post discusses how Apache Pinot can easily ingest, query, and visualize millions of events. In this case, the events are climate events, sourced from the NOAA storm database.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/pinterest-engineering/fighting-spam-with-guardian-a-real-time-analytics-and-rules-engine-938e7e61fa27">Fighting spam with Guardian, a real-time analytics and rules engine</a>. The post linked here looks at the evolution of Pinterest&rsquo;s spam-fighting rules and query and what they&rsquo;ve learned throughout the process.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.theseattledataguy.com/how-to-modernize-your-data-architecture-part-1-data-analytics-strategy-consulting/">How To Modernize Your Data Architecture Part 1 – Data Analytics Strategy Consulting</a>. This post is the first in a series about data architecture. It discusses what to avoid when building a data architecture and which questions to ask when building a future data</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/from-data-lakes-to-data-reservoirs-aa2efebb4f25">From Data Lakes to Data Reservoirs</a>. The post linked to here looks at how you can &ldquo;tame&rdquo; your data lakes. How you can create clean, beautiful, and protected data resources with Apache Spark and Databricks Delta Lake.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/the-building-blocks-of-a-modern-data-platform-92e46061165">The Building Blocks of a Modern Data Platform</a>. If you wonder what a &ldquo;modern data platform&rdquo; means, then this post is for you. The post breaks down what a modern data platform means in practice today. This includes the three core characteristics, six fundamental building blocks, and the latest data tools. I found this post extremely valuable.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/running-kafka-at-scale-at-pinterest/">Lessons Learned from Running Apache Kafka at Scale at Pinterest</a>. The post linked to shares how Pinterest runs Kafka and discusses some of the challenges they&rsquo;ve faced and how they addressed them.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 8, 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2021/02/21/interesting-stuff---week-8-2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-21T08:56:02+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2021/02/21/interesting-stuff---week-8-2021/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI / data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.dapr.io/posts/2021/02/17/announcing-dapr-v1.0/">Announcing Dapr v1.0</a>. As the title implies, this post announces version 1.0 of the Distributed Application Runtime, (Dapr). Dapr lowers the bar for entry to build microservices applications, running on self-hosted infrastructure or Kubernetes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server-big-data-cluster">SQL Server Big Data Cluster</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2021/02/16/whats-new-with-sql-server-big-data-clusters/">What&rsquo;s new with SQL Server Big Data Clusters</a>. Microsoft released SQL Server 2019 CU9 recently, and subsequently, there is a CU9 release for SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster, (BDC). The post linked to discusses some of the new features in this release. I guess I better upgrade my existing BDC installation and take CU9 &ldquo;for a spin&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/logging/">Fast and Reliable Schema-Agnostic Log Analytics Platform</a>. This post by Uber looks at their platform for log analytics and how it has evolved. It is a really interesting post, and I think we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> definitely can learn a thing or two from what they have done.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-15-features-updates/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.15</a>. I last week&rsquo;s <a href="/2021/02/14/interesting-stuff---week-7-2021/">roundup</a>, I wrote about Confluent Platform 6.1 being released, and with that exciting new ksqlDB features. This post announces a new ksqlDB version and lists some of the features in this version.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/42-ways-zookeeper-removal-improves-kafka/">42 Things You Can Stop Doing Once ZooKeeper Is Gone from Apache Kafka</a>. There has been work underway for quite a time now to remove Kafka&rsquo;s dependency on ZooKeeper. We are getting closer and closer to this being achieved, and the post linked to looks at some of the &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; we no longer need to &ldquo;worry&rdquo; about when the ZooKeeper dependency is gone.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-15-reads-more-message-keys-supports-more-data-types/">Keys in ksqlDB, Unlocked</a>. Above, I linked to the post announcing ksqlDB 0.15. The post here looks at one specific new feature in the 0.15 release; support for many more types of data in messages keys, including message keys with multiple columns. Awesome!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In last weeks <a href="/2021/02/14/interesting-stuff---week-7-2021/">roundup</a>, I mentioned how I was about to finish a post about installing SQL Server on an Azure VM. Here it is:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/02/14/how-to-install-sql-server-on-an-azure-vm/">How To Install SQL Server on an Azure VM</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I am now prepping for a <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Cape-Town-Ms-Dev-User-Group/events/276127124/">user group presentation</a> to talk about SQL Server and Kafka. As part of that prep, I&rsquo;ve played around with Docker, and I may do a post around that.</p>

<p>Oh, speaking about that user group presentation, if you are interested, please <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Cape-Town-Ms-Dev-User-Group/events/276127124/">signup</a>, and join the fun!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

