<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Niels Berglund</title>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com"/>
  <updated>2022-07-31T08:02:01+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://nielsberglund.com/</id>
  <generator uri="http://gohugo.io/">Hugo</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 30, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/31/interesting-stuff---week-30-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-31T08:02:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/31/interesting-stuff---week-30-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/chess-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Chess</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/2022/07/25/data-chess-game-databricks-vs-snowflake-part-1/">Data chess game: Databricks vs. Snowflake, part 1</a>. There is no doubt that Snowflake and Databricks compete in becoming the leading cloud data platform vendor. This post looks at these two vendors from different backgrounds (data lake and warehousing) and how they are now &ldquo;duking&rdquo; it out in the lakehouse.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/07/25/recap-of-databricks-lakehouse-platform-announcements-at-data-and-ai-summit-2022.htm">Recap of Databricks Lakehouse Platform Announcements at Data and AI Summit 2022</a>. The linked post summarises the major Databricks Lakehouse Platform innovations and contributions to open source and data and AI projects announced at the Data and AI Summit 2022.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Scalable-Data-Analytics-Azure-Explorer/dp/1801078548">Scalable Data Analytics with Azure Data Explorer: Modern ways to query, analyze, and perform real-time data analysis on large volumes of data</a>. A while ago, I was asked to do an editorial review of a book about <strong>Azure data Explorer</strong>. Well, the link here is to that book. If you are into ADX, then this book is a must-read.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-ci-cd-with-github/">4 Must-Have Tests for Your Apache Kafka CI/CD with GitHub Actions</a>. This post looks at applying GitOps principles to the development lifecycle of a Kafka client application using GitHub Actions: for testing locally and in Confluent Cloud, with and without Schema Registry, and for schema evolution.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/07/28/the-heart-of-the-data-mesh-beats-real-time-with-apache-kafka/">The Heart of the Data Mesh Beats Real-Time with Apache Kafka</a>. We all have heard about the &ldquo;data mesh&rdquo; by now. A requirement of the data mesh infrastructure is that it is real-time, reliable, and scalable. This post explores how Apache Kafka, as an open and scalable decentralized real-time platform, can be the basis of a data mesh infrastructure and – complemented by many other data platforms like a data warehouse, data lake, and lakehouse – solve real business problems.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 29, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/24/interesting-stuff---week-29-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-24T11:50:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/24/interesting-stuff---week-29-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/dps-2022.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Conference</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://rmoff.net/2022/07/20/how-to-write-a-good-tech-conference-abstract-learn-from-the-mistakes-of-others/">How to Write a Good Tech Conference Abstract - Learn from the Mistakes of Others</a>. I guess the title says it all. Things to think about when writing conference abstracts. This post by <a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a> is very valuable, but it should have come somewhat earlier. Why - you ask? Well, the conference &ldquo;season&rdquo; is upon us, and I have submitted quite a few abstracts. Unfortunately, the majority have been rejected. Maybe the result would have been better following the advice in this post. Anyway, rejections are part of the game - onwards and upwards!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/data-pre-processing-for-azure-data-explorer-with-apache-spark/ba-p/2727993">Data pre-processing for Azure Data Explorer with Apache Spark</a>. So, you want to load data into <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>. No problem, ADX has quite a few &ldquo;nifty&rdquo; ways to get the data into it. However, sometimes the data would need some complex data engineering upfront. Something that even ADXs powerful data-transformation capabilities cannot do. If that&rsquo;s the case, this post comes in handy. It looks at how to do it using PySpark and the notebook experience in Azure Synapse Analytics. Have Fun!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/2022/07/19/confluent-addresses-major-real-time-application-roadblocks-with-q3-update/">Confluent addresses major real-time application roadblocks with Q3 update</a>. This post looks at how Confluent partnered with Hashicorp to introduce a Terraform provider. The integration exposes Confluent cloud APIs for automated deployment and management of mission-critical data streaming resources. This is just the right time for us at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> as we are introducing Confluent Cloud right now!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/introducing-confluent-platform-7-2/">Introducing Confluent Platform 7.2: Enhanced Cloud-Native Security and Geo-Replication</a>. This post announces the release of Confluent Platform 7.2. The release covers three major areas: simplified cluster ops, improved data sharing, and improved stream processing capabilities via ksqlDB 0.26.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Above I was &ldquo;moaning&rdquo; about my abstracts being rejected. But, as you can see from the picture up top, &ldquo;all is not lost&rdquo;. I am presenting at <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/"><strong>Data Platform Summit 2022</strong></a>, and the session is <strong>ksqlDB - the Real-Time Streaming Database</strong>. So, right now I am prepping for the presentation!</p>

<p>Data Platform Summit is an awesome conference, it is this year as well virtual. So no traveling needed, hurry up and sign up <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/booking/">here</a>. Its is <strong>FREE</strong>!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 28, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/17/interesting-stuff---week-28-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-17T12:50:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/17/interesting-stuff---week-28-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/risk-management.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@cdc?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">CDC</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/%22risk-management%22?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a>
  </em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://whitepages.tygraph.com/2022/07/continuous-export-for-azure-application-insights-using-azure-data-explorer-kusto/">Continuous export for Azure Application Insights using Azure Data Explorer (Kusto)</a>. If you &ldquo;live in Azure-land&rdquo;, you probably use Application Insights to collect data for analysis. The analysis in App Insight is based on the Kusto engine but does not have all bells and whistles. To do more advanced analytics of your App Insights data, you should export your data to <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> (ADX). This post discusses a pattern for continuously streaming data from Application Insights data to ADX.</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-explorer/flow-usage">Usage examples for Azure Data Explorer connector to Power Automate</a>. I love <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> (heh- who would have thunk), but there is some &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; that frustrates me. Among them is that it is hard (neigh impossible) to do things based on scheduled tasks, triggers, etc. Well, neigh impossible until you read this Microsoft doc. This document looks at how to &ldquo;hook up&rdquo; <a href="https://powerautomate.microsoft.com/">Microsoft Power Automate</a> to ADX, and it also includes several typical Power Automate connector usage examples. Very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwyttaal5U3r9jnHSaGT75sRqSfNDrX11">Azure Data Explorer L300 Workshop</a>. A couple of weeks ago, the Azure Data Explorer PM (Program Manager) team held a workshop spread over three days (around 2 - 3 hours per day). The workshop covered <strong>a lot</strong>, and the good thing was that it was recorded. The link here is to the YouTube playlist of the workshop. If you are interested in ADX, you <strong>must</strong> have a look!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/07/14/using-spark-structured-streaming-to-scale-your-analytics.html">Using Spark Structured Streaming to Scale Your Analytics</a>. This post looks at how a Databricks customer leverages Structured Streaming and the Databricks Lakehouse Platform to scale its analytics and keep its data products up to date.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/share-find-understand-data-streams-stream-catalog/">How to Find, Share, and Understand Your Data Streams with Stream Catalog</a>. If you want to get the most out of your data, it is vital to be able to discover, understand, organize and reuse your data. These requirements have led to the notion of a data catalogue. The post linked to looks at the Confluent Stream Catalog, what it is and what you can do with it.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/ml-prediction-on-streaming-data-using-kafka-streams-1e4ebd21008">ML Prediction on Streaming Data Using Kafka Streams</a>. This post looks at how you can boost the performance of your Python-trained ML models by serving them over a Kafka streaming platform in a Scala application.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/risk-management-with-confluent-databricks-data-streaming-analytics/">How streaming data and a lakehouse paradigm can help manage risk in volatile trading markets</a>. In financial markets, managing risk is a must. It is the key to success if you can do it well. The post linked to, looks at how you can ingest and process large amounts of raw data to compute real-time portfolio valuations, risk metrics, and more using integrated technology from Confluent and Databricks. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 27, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/10/interesting-stuff---week-27-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-10T09:58:43+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/10/interesting-stuff---week-27-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/mvp-renewal-2022-2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">MVP Renewal</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture-big-data">Data Architecture / Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/from-data-warehouse-to-data-lake-to-data-lakehouse-44ca03e0d624">From Data Warehouse to Data Lake to Data Lakehouse</a>. As the title implies, this post looks at Data Warehouses, Data Lakes and Data Lakehouses. It starts with an overview of the different Data Store technologies to see the whole picture and to understand what has changed and what has not. The post then looks at what&rsquo;s for what, what you need, and the advantages and limitations of Data Warehouses, Data Lakes, and Data Lakehouses. Oh, and as a part of the post, the author builds a Data Lakehouse. Very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/30/open-sourcing-all-of-delta-lake.html">Open Sourcing All of Delta Lake</a>. So, as the title says, Databricks Delta Lake has now been fully open-sourced. This post looks at the reasoning behind it and what it means for the data community going forward.</li>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/the-data-engineering-pipeline-6f7a306fcfdc">The Data Engineering Pipeline</a>. Data Engineers are at the heart of the engine room of any data-driven company. In this post, the author provides a high-level overview of the Data Engineering Pipeline, including best practices and tools to help drive data-driven organizations.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/aviation-flight-data-analytics-azure-synapse-platform-debananda-ghosh/">Aviation flight data analytics with Azure Synapse platform</a>. This post looks at flight data analytics use cases specific to the aviation industry. The interesting thing for me here is the usage of Synapse Data Explorer, the &ldquo;brother&rdquo; of <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>. It is fascinating to see how much &ldquo;cool stuff&rdquo; can be done with a powerful analytics engine - Synapse Data Explorer - and the query language Kusto!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/07/05/data-streaming-for-data-ingestion-into-data-warehouse-and-data-lake/">Data Streaming for Data Ingestion into the Data Warehouse and Data Lake</a>. This post is the second in a series exploring concepts, features, and trade-offs of a modern data stack using a data warehouse, data lake, and data streaming together. You find the first part <a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/06/27/data-warehouse-vs-data-lake-vs-data-streaming-friends-enemies-frenemies/">here</a>. In this post, the author looks at how data streaming technologies are a perfect fit for data ingestion into data warehouses, data lakes, etc. This post came at the precisely right time as we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> are looking at this (ingestion into data lakes) now.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In the beginning of July MVP&rsquo;s around the world are on tenterhooks, as it is MVP renewal time: &ldquo;will I be an MVP for another year?&rdquo;. After the &ldquo;judgement&rdquo; you then see the LinkedIn feed be flooded by MVP&rsquo;s posts how happy they are that have been renewed. Last year was a bit silly seeing all the posts, since everyone was renewed automatically, and we knew about it beforehand.</p>

<p>With all that said, as you can see from the pictures at the top, I was renewed! Yay!!</p>

<p>At the same time of renewal, but entirely independent, I received this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/mvp-swag-2022-1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>MVP SWAG</em></p>

<p>Yup, MVP SWAG: hoodie, coffee cup and a Thank You card! Very cool, THANK YOU, Microsoft and the MVP Program!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 26, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/03/interesting-stuff---week-26-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-03T10:03:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/03/interesting-stuff---week-26-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/data-vault.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Data Vault</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2022/06/30/introducing-the-sql-server-2022-blog-series/">Microsoft SQL Server Blog</a>. If you follow what happens in the database world, you probably know that Microsoft SQL Server 2022 is now in Public Preview. This version of SQL Server promises to be a pretty impressive release, so I suggest two things: <a href="https://info.microsoft.com/ww-landing-sql-server-2022.html">download the preview</a> and test it out, and bookmark the SQL Server 2022 Blogging Series page in the linked post to follow along and see future blog posts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.playfab.com/blog/take-advantage-of-azure-data-explorer-with-playfab-data-connections">Take advantage of Azure Data Explorer with Playfab data connections</a>. PlayFab is a complete backend platform for live games with managed game services, real-time analytics, and LiveOps, and you can read more about it <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/gaming/playfab/what-is-playfab">here</a>. This post announces how there is now an <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> connector for PlayFab. Based on what we are doing in <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, PlayFab sounds like something we really should look into, and having <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> connectors makes it even more so.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/2022/06/28/databricks-strikes-back/">Databricks strikes back</a>. Databricks held its <a href="https://databricks.com/dataaisummit/">Data+AI Summit 2022</a> last week (June 27 - 30). The post linked to was published the same day as the Summit started, and it looks at the full range of announcements during the conference (yes, the author of the post was pre-briefed by Databricks). Some very cool &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; there!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/24/prescriptive-guidance-for-implementing-a-data-vault-model-on-the-databricks-lakehouse-platform.html">Prescriptive Guidance for Implementing a Data Vault Model on the Databricks Lakehouse Platform</a>. Another Databricks-related post, this one by Databricks themselves. The post discusses Data Vault&rsquo;s and how to implement them within the Bronze/Silver/Gold layer. It also looks at how to get the best performance of Data Vault with Databricks Lakehouse Platform.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@robgolder/kafka-streams-state-store-30110bf4f24">Kafka Streams: State Store</a>. Kafka Streams stateful processing enables grouping related events that arrive at different times. Operations such as joins, reduce, counts, and aggregations can then be performed on them. That is all well and good, but the previously mentioned functionality would require state to be stored. This post dives into how state is stored in KStreams, and I found it very informative!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/26/interesting-stuff---week-25-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-26T09:33:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/26/interesting-stuff---week-25-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/microsoft-open-hack-2022-1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Microsoft Open Hack</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/24/data-warehousing-modeling-techniques-and-their-implementation-on-the-databricks-lakehouse-platform.html">Data Warehousing Modeling Techniques and Their Implementation on the Databricks Lakehouse Platform</a>. This post talks about the different data modelling techniques supported by the Databricks Lakehouse Platform and how each fits within each layer of the Bronze, Silver, and Gold architecture. For me, this post is very timely as we are right now implementing a Data Lakehouse here at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/wix-engineering/migrating-to-a-multi-cluster-managed-kafka-with-0-downtime-b936655f888e">Migrating to a Multi-Cluster Managed Kafka with 0 Downtime</a>. This post discusses how they at <a href="https://www.wix.com/">Wix</a> migrated 2000 microservices from on-prem Kafka clusters to Confluent Cloud. The post looks at critical design decisions and best practices for this type of migration.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/announcing-ga-launch-of-kafka-trigger-extension-on-azure/ba-p/3499015">Announcing GA launch of Kafka Trigger extension on Azure Functions</a>. As the title implies, this post announces the GA release of Kafka triggers. Kafka triggers enable you to invoke functions in response to messages in Kafka topics and let you write values/messages out to Kafka topics using an output binding. Very, very cool, and this comes at the right time for a project we are starting at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/data-pipeline-principles-use-cases-examples/">Applying Data Pipeline Principles in Practice: Exploring the Kafka Summit Keynote Demo</a>. The Kafka Summit 2022 key-note demo showed how a fictional airline company merges with another airline company and wants a data pipeline built on Confluent to enable analytical and operational workstreams. This blog post deconstructs the demo through excerpts of real code used to create it. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>By now, you probably wonder what the picture at the top has to do with anything. So last week, Microsoft ran an <a href="https://openhack.microsoft.com/">OpenHack</a> here at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>. The topic of the OpenHack was <strong>Modern Data Warehousing</strong>, covering Azure Data Lake Storage, Azure Databricks, Azure Synapse Analytics and other cool stuff. Anyway, the OpenHack ran for three days, and on the last day, Microsoft had an event in our canteen where Derivco&rsquo;s employees had the chance to talk to various people from Microsoft.</p>

<p>Part of this event was the &ldquo;selfie booth&rdquo;, and in the picture, you see me sitting beside <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lee-anne-james-96514023/">Lee-Anne James</a>, who is our contact at Microsoft for all Data and AI. I cannot express enough how awesome she is. She really goes all out for us! Thanks, Lee-Anne!</p>

<p>So I mentioned the &ldquo;selfie booth&rdquo;, and part of the deal was that if you took a selfie and published it on your blog, Twitter, LinkedIn, etc., you got some swag:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/synapse-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Azure Synapse Analytics Swag</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 1</em> you see the swag I managed to score - not bad!</p>

<p>Oh, I also managed to publish a blog post around some &ldquo;weird&rdquo; Git errors:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/06/25/solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-some-repo-is-owned-by-someone-else/">Solution to GIT: &ldquo;unsafe repository (&lsquo;some-repo&rsquo; is owned by someone else)&rdquo;</a>. I recently re-formatted my PC, and after everything was installed again, I got a &ldquo;weird&rdquo; error when I tried to do a <code>git pull</code>. The post looks at why I got the error and how to fix it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>

<p>2022-06-25-solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-somerepo-is-owned-by-someone-else.md</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solution to GIT: &#34;unsafe repository (&#39;some-repo&#39; is owned by someone else)&#34;
]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/25/solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-some-repo-is-owned-by-someone-else/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-25T19:16:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/25/solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-some-repo-is-owned-by-someone-else/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/git.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Git</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@synkevych?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Roman Synkevych 🇺🇦</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/git-repository?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Every 6 - 9 months (or so), I clean up my development PC just to keep it &ldquo;lean and mean&rdquo;. I do it by formatting the hard-drive partition the OS (in this case, Windows) is on, followed by a new install. Recently I had a four-day weekend here in SA. Four glorious days off, a perfect time to &ldquo;nuke&rdquo; my PC and re-install!</p>

<p></p>

<p>Off I go, everything goes to plan (<a href="https://community.chocolatey.org/">Chocolatey</a> is my friend), and after a while, I am done (or as done as one can be). At this stage, I needed to do my <a href="/2022/06/19/interesting-stuff---week-24-2022/">weekly roundup blog post</a> for the week gone by, and as I had done some changes to the GitHub repo from my <strong>MacBook Pro</strong>, I wanted to do a <code>git pull</code> in the repo directory for my blog. Part of the story is that on my dev PC, I have all my repos on a separate partition from the system partition, so the non-system partition was un-affected by the reformat (or so I thought). Imagine my surprise when doing the <code>git pull</code> I got:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/git-unsafe-repo-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Unsafe Repository</em></p>

<p>Hmm, the error we see in <em>Figure 1</em> does not make any sense at all. It is my repo, I created it, so what is the problem?</p>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>

<p>Trying to narrow down the issue, I did a <code>git clone</code> into a new directory of the same repo I couldn&rsquo;t <code>pull</code>, which worked perfectly! I went over to my MacBook and did a <code>pull</code> against the same repo that failed previously, and that worked as well. By now, I was utterly dumbfounded, so I started to do proper research (read Googled), and I came across <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/71901632/fatal-error-unsafe-repository-home-repon-is-owned-by-someone-else/71949648#71949648">this post</a>, which talked about security vulnerabilities in the Git client, and how they had been fixed in version <code>2.35.2</code>. When I checked my version, it was <code>2.36.1</code>, so I might be on to something here.</p>

<p>When reading about the security vulnerability in the link above, I came across this:</p>

<p><em>This version changes Git&rsquo;s behavior when looking for a top-level <code>.git</code> directory to stop when its directory traversal changes ownership from the current user.</em></p>

<p>Hmm, ownership and current user, let&rsquo;s look at the directory where the <code>pull</code> failed:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/git-unsafe-repo-owner-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2:</strong> <em>Directory Ownership</em></p>

<p>When looking at the advanced security settings for the directory, I saw something like in <em>Figure 2</em>, a &ldquo;weird&rdquo; looking owner of the directory. Actually, it is not that weird; it is a security identifier (<code>SID</code>). A <code>SID</code> in the Windows OS identifies a user, user group, or other security principal.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> To get to the advanced security settings, I right-clicked on the directory, chose <strong>Properties</strong>, clicked on the <strong>Security</strong> tab, and in the <strong>Security</strong> tab, I clicked the <strong>Advanced</strong> button.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From what we see in <em>Figure 2</em>, it is evident that the directory owner is not the same as the current user, i.e. me. Before we look at ways to fix the issue, let&rsquo;s understand why the owner is not myself. I created the directory at one point, so the owner should be me.</p>

<p>The answer is that the directory sits on a different partition/hard drive. When I reformatted the machine, the ownership was transferred to the particular <code>SID</code> since I was not &ldquo;around&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So now we know the reason and why it happened; let&rsquo;s fix it.</p>

<h2 id="fix-the-issue">Fix the Issue</h2>

<p>The obvious way to fix the problem is to change the directory owner to me. This can be done in the <strong>Advanced Security Settings</strong> we saw before:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/git-unsafe-repo-change-owner.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 3:</strong> <em>Change Owner</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 3</em>, we see how it is done. I clicked the <strong>Change</strong> button (outlined in blue), which brought up the <em>Select User or Group</em> dialog. I entered my user name in the textbox (outlined in red) and then clicked <strong>OK</strong>. I am now back to being the directory owner, and when doing a <code>git pull</code>, everything works!</p>

<p>This is one way to change the owner. The problem with this is that if you have quite a few repo directories under a &ldquo;root&rdquo; directory (as I do), then it can become a bit tedious to do it: right-click directory, <strong>Properties</strong>, <strong>Security</strong>, <strong>Advanced</strong>, <strong>Change</strong> - for each directory. It would be cool if one could do something more batch-like.</p>

<p>On Windows, we have a pretty neat tool that allows taking ownership of a file or folder using the command-line interface. The tool is <code>takeown.exe</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">$ takeown /f . /r /d Y
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Code Snippet 1:</strong> <em>Take Ownership</em></p>

<p>In <em>Code Snippet 1</em>, we see how I am in the root directory of my Git repos and how I call <code>takeown</code>. The parameters are:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>/f</code>: the directory or file to take ownership of. We see how I have defined <code>/f .</code>, (dot), which indicates the current directory.</li>
<li><code>/r</code>: performs a recursive operation on all files in the specified directory and subdirectories.</li>
<li><code>/d</code>: suppresses the confirmation prompt that is displayed when the current user does not have the <code>List Folder</code> permission on a specified directory and instead uses the specified default value. In my case, I used <code>Y</code>, which indicates to take ownership.</li>
</ul>

<p>Be aware that the above recurses through all directories and files, so it may take a while.</p>

<p>Another way to solve the issue, which does not involve changing ownership, is to tell Git that the directory is safe. To mark a directory safe, you use the <code>git config --global --add safe.directory &lt;option&gt;</code> command. The <code>option</code> can be a path to a directory or <code>*</code>, wherein Git treats any directory as safe.</p>

<p>When running <code>git config --global --add safe.directory</code>, the end result is that a <code>[safe]</code> section is being added to the <code>~/.gitconfig file</code>, and the section indicates what is safe:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">[user]
  email = niels.it.berglund@gmail.com
  name = Niels Berglund
[safe]
  directory = *
</code></pre>

<p>*<em>Code Snippet 2:</em> <em>Git Config File</em></p>

<p>In <em>Code Snippet 2</em> we see my <code>~/.config</code> file after I executed <code>git config --global --add safe.directory *</code>.</p>

<p>Remember that if you add a specific directory as <code>safe</code>, any changes to the directory name or path will cause the error to re-occur. However, if you add all directories as safe (or change ownership), you do not need to worry about name or path changes. It will just work.</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>This post looked at what causes the <em>unsafe repository (&lsquo;some-repo&rsquo; is owned by someone else)</em> Git error. We said that this error occurs when you run a Git client with a version of <code>2.35.2</code> or higher and execute a Git command in a directory owned by someone else than the user executing the command.</p>

<p>The way to solve this is to either change the ownership of the directory/directories or mark them as safe.</p>

<p>Having re-installed Windows, it is now time to do my <strong>MacBook Pro</strong> as well. Wish me luck!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>If you have comments, questions etc., please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 24, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/19/interesting-stuff---week-24-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-19T13:40:48+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/19/interesting-stuff---week-24-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/performance.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Performance</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@toddquackenbush?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Todd Quackenbush</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/performance?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2022/06/10/Quamina-Optimizing">Making Code Faster</a>. This post is a continuation of the post <a href="https://github.com/timbray/quamina">here</a>, which I covered in the roundup for <a href="/2022/05/15/interesting-stuff---week-19-2022/">week 19, 2022</a>. The post discusses various approaches to performance testing of your code. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning/AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://gradientflow.com/distributed-computing-for-ai-a-status-report/">Distributed Computing for AI: A Status Report</a>. The post linked to looks at what role distributed computing plays in AI. The consensus is that it becomes more and more essential to understand distributed computing in AI projects. Also, when hiring for AI, you often compete with &ldquo;pure&rdquo; distributed computing roles.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2022/06/15/recapping-recent-updates-to-client-tools-in-sql-server/">Recapping recent updates to client tools in SQL Server</a>. It has been a while since I have covered tools for SQL Server. Let me rectify that with this link. As the title implies, this post looks at SQL Server tools. What caught my eye was the notebook enhancements in <strong>Azure Data Studio</strong> and the containerization of Azure SQL Database! Cool stuff!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/5-ways-which-adx-can-provide-leading-edge-your-data-platform-dixit/">5 Ways in which ADX can provide a leading edge to your Data Platform</a>. I am pretty &ldquo;fond&rdquo; of <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> as you know if you read my blog. I particularly like the super-fast ingestion and querying and the ability to do real-time analysis! However, there are other advantages of ADX, and the post I have linked to looks at 5 of those.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/cloud-incident-management-at-confluent/">How Confluent Treats Incidents in the Cloud</a>. Since we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> looks at using Confluent Cloud, this post came in real handy. As the title says, the post looks at Confluent Cloud incidents and how they are handled. Very informative!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/12/interesting-stuff---week-23-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-12T15:27:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/12/interesting-stuff---week-23-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/snowflake.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Snowflake</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@mharrisonphotography?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Megs Harrison</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data">Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2022/06/new-intelligent-data-platform/">A New Microsoft Platform in Town: the Microsoft Intelligent Data Platform</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> post looks at the recently introduced Microsoft Intelligent Data Platform. This new platform fully integrates Microsoft&rsquo;s database, analytics, and governance offerings. It encompasses everything already available in the Azure Data space (Azure Data Factory, Azure Data Explorer, etc.) to the Synapse Analytics products, Power BI, and the newly rebranded Purview data governance service.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/08/announcing-the-availability-of-data-lineage-with-unity-catalog.html">Announcing the Availability of Data Lineage With Unity Catalog</a>. This post talks about the Databricks Data Lineage offering using the Unity Catalog. It looks at how the Unity Catalog provides automated and real-time data lineage at a granular level for all workloads (SQL, R, Python, Scala) and across all asset types (notebooks, workflows, dashboards). Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/shippeo-tech-blog/debezium-to-snowflake-lessons-learned-building-data-replication-in-production-a5430a9fe85b">Debezium to Snowflake: Lessons learned building data replication in production</a>. This blog looks at lessons learned when using Debezium to replicate data at scale in near real-time to Snowflake. There are some very useful tidbits in the post, even though we don&rsquo;t use Snowflake at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/elastically-scale-apache-kafka-clusters-in-confluent-cloud/">How to Elastically Scale Apache Kafka Clusters on Confluent Cloud</a>. In last week&rsquo;s <a href="/2022/06/05/interesting-stuff---week-22-2022/">roundup</a>, I mentioned Confluent Cloud&rsquo;s elasticity compared with on-prem Kafka, and we saw how much better it was in Confluent Cloud. The post here covers how we can easily resize a Confluent Cloud cluster and how it works internally. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 22, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/05/interesting-stuff---week-22-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-05T09:58:38+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/05/interesting-stuff---week-22-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/vector.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Vector</strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/geekculture/vector-databases-taking-data-revolution-to-the-next-level-4a0faa437b2c">Vector Databases: Taking Data Revolution to The Next Level</a>. We know about SQL and no-SQL databases and how they are used, and that they are used for structured and semi-structured data. However, we now see more unstructured data, and the question is how we can deal with (search, etc.) this data. Dealing with unstructured data is where vector databases can help. This post looks at vector databases, how they can help us manage unstructured data, and the solutions they offer.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/azure-data-explorer-in-60-minutes-with-the-new-samples-gallery/ba-p/3447552">Azure Data Explorer in 60 minutes with the new samples gallery</a>. The post linked to announces the new Azure Data Explorer samples gallery feature. This feature provides an easy way to upskill and demo Azure Data Explorer with an end-to-end experience on a free, publicly available cluster. If you haven&rsquo;t looked at Azure Data Explorer yet, now it&rsquo;s time to do it.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/implementing-and-optimizing-bounding-box-queries-in-azure-data/ba-p/3416786">Implementing and Optimizing Bounding Box Queries in Azure Data Explorer</a>. This post looks at how we can in Azure Data Explorer create a function that would return objects - in this case vehicles - that are within a given bounding box in a given time period. This is quite a cool usage of bounding boxes!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/10x-apache-kafka-elasticity/">Making Confluent Cloud 10x More Elastic Than Apache Kafka</a>. Elasticity is the cornerstone of cloud-native computing. This post looks at how Confluent took Apache Kafka&rsquo;s horizontal scalability to the next level—in fact, they took it up multiple levels—and made Confluent Cloud 10x more elastic! Quite interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 21, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/29/interesting-stuff---week-21-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-29T13:13:28+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/29/interesting-stuff---week-21-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/snake.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>anaConda</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@sharonmccutcheon?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Sharon McCutcheon</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/how-to-manage-conda-environments-on-an-apple-silicon-m1-mac-1e29cb3bad12">How to Manage Conda Environments on an Apple Silicon M1 Mac</a>. As I mentioned in a <a href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/03/interesting-stuff---week-13-2022/">previous roundup</a>, I have switched over to the &ldquo;dark side&rdquo; for my travel laptop - I did get myself a MacBook Pro. Coming from a Windows background setting it up and configuring it is sometimes a chore, so I tend to save links to blog posts/articles covering setup/configuration of a Mac. This link is such a post, and it looks at how to manage different Python environments using Conda.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.jamesserra.com/archive/2022/05/microsoft-build-event-announcements-4/">Microsoft Build event announcements</a>. Last week (May 24 - 26), Microsoft held its annual Build conference. Many interesting things were announced, and the post linked to looks at some of the data platform announcements. One &ldquo;biggie&rdquo; is that SQL Server 2022 has been released into Public Preview.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.jamesserra.com/archive/2022/05/microsoft-build-event-announcements-4/">Deleting individual records in a table</a>. You who read my blog probably know that I like <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>. You also may know that my background is SQL Server. I mention my SQL Server background because sometimes doing things in ADX is somewhat different from what you&rsquo;d do in SQL Server. An example of this is deleting records. That is what this post looks at. It covers deleting individual records from a table and how it works behind the scenes.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/optimized-autoscale-predictive-planning/ba-p/3413543">Optimized autoscale – predictive planning</a>. Azure Data Explorer has supported autoscaling (out and in) for quite some time. The autoscaling has been reactive, i.e. the scaling is delayed and requires time to alleviate the pressure off the cluster. This post looks at predictive autoscaling. It was recently added, and it tracks main metrics and builds a usage pattern. This allows ADX to plan cluster scale out and scale in ahead of time to further improve cluster performance while reducing cost.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/messaging-on-azure-blog/benchmarking-azure-event-hubs-premium-for-kafka-and-amqp/ba-p/3377483">Benchmarking Azure Event Hubs Premium for Kafka and AMQP workloads</a>. Microsoft recently announced the general availability of Azure Event Hubs Premium. It is a new product tier meant to support high-end event streaming scenarios. This post benchmarks this new product tier against Kafka, and the numbers are quite interesting. It is probably worth having a look at Azure Event Hubs Premium.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-3-2-0-new-features-and-updates/">What&rsquo;s New in Apache Kafka 3.2.0</a>. The title of this post kind if gives it away. Yes, the post looks at some of the new and improved features in the 3.2 release of Apache Kafka. What is of particular interest to me is the new features in KStreams. I hope they will make way for new functionality in ksqlDB as well.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/22/interesting-stuff---week-20-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-22T10:40:58+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/22/interesting-stuff---week-20-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/warehouse.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Warehouse</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jezar?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Jezael Melgoza</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/05/20/five-simple-steps-for-implementing-a-star-schema-in-databricks-with-delta-lake.html">Five Simple Steps for Implementing a Star Schema in Databricks With Delta Lake</a>. At <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, we are starting to implement Databricks and Delta Live tables. This post, looking at simple tips and tricks for getting the best performance from Delta Lake star schema databases used in data warehouses and data marts, comes therefore at the right time.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/05/19/how-i-built-a-streaming-analytics-app-with-sql-and-delta-live-tables.html">How I Built A Streaming Analytics App With SQL and Delta Live Tables</a>. In this post, the author describes how easy it is to build a production-ready streaming analytics application with Delta Live Tables and Databricks SQL.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/05/17/build-scalable-real-time-applications-on-the-lakehouse-using-confluent-databricks-part-2.html">Build Scalable Real-time Applications on the Lakehouse Using Confluent &amp; Databricks, Part 2</a>. In this post, which is a continuation of <a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/01/13/confluent-streaming-for-databricks-build-scalable-real-time-applications-on-the-lakehouse.html">the post here</a>, you learn more about the Confluent Connector for Databricks, streamlining the creation of real-time apps in AWS for data analytics use cases. Even though the examples use AWS, you can easily do this in Azure as well.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 19, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/15/interesting-stuff---week-19-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-15T09:34:48+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/15/interesting-stuff---week-19-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/digital-twin.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>IoT &amp; Digital Twin</strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2022/05/12/Quamina">Meet Quamina</a>. A very interesting post by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Bray">Tim Bray</a> about <a href="https://github.com/timbray/quamina">Quamina</a>, a super fast pattern-matching library!</li>
<li><a href="https://blog.nelhage.com/post/reflections-on-performance/">Reflections on software performance</a>. In this post, the author reflects on some of the lessons learned while writing performant software and working with rather a lot more not-so-performant software. I found the conclusion of the post very interesting: <em>we underrate performance when designing and building software. We have become accustomed to casually giving up factors [of performance] of two or ten or more with our choices of tools and libraries without asking if the benefits are worth it.</em></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/Ky52OQVwckw">Azure Digital Twins and Azure Synapse integration</a>. Azure Digital Twins now integrates with Azure Data Explorer and Azure Synapse, allowing you to find insights from time-series history of digital twins combined and correlated with other data. This YouTube video looks at the integration and also provides a short demo.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-walmart-uses-kafka-for-real-time-omnichannel-replenishment/">How Walmart Uses Apache Kafka for Real-Time Replenishment at Scale</a>. As a retailer, both real-time inventory and real-time replenishment are vital. This post looks at Walmart&rsquo;s journey with Kafka and highlights the real-time replenishment use case they are currently using it for.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 18, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/08/interesting-stuff---week-18-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-08T09:46:54+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/08/interesting-stuff---week-18-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/conference.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Conference Presentation</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@xteemu?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Teemu Paananen</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://blogs.newardassociates.com/blog/2022/mistakes-happen-get-over-it.html">Speaking Tips: Mistakes happen; get over it</a>. So, we have started having &ldquo;live&rdquo; conferences again, WoHoo! It is awesome standing in from a crowd again, presenting and demoing! The downside of presenting live is that we can&rsquo;t &ldquo;hide&rdquo; any mistakes, demos failing etc. This post by my old Developmentor colleague <a href="http://www.newardassociates.com/">Ted Neward</a> discusses handling failed demos, unexpected &ldquo;things&rdquo; happening, etc., during your presentation. If you are a speaker and concerned about failed demos, read the post. Even if you are not a speaker or concerned, go and read it anyway!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://distributed-computing-musings.com/2022/05/vector-clocks-keeping-time-in-check/">Vector Clocks: Keeping time in check</a>. Time is essential when dealing with events, and in a one-node system, time is easy. However, time becomes problematic when dealing with time in a distributed system. This post looks at the use of vector clocks to solve the issue of causality of events occurring on different servers. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/remove-kafka-brokers-from-any-cluster-the-easy-way/">How to Remove Apache Kafka Brokers the Easy Way</a>. Shrinking a Kafka cluster, i.e. removing brokers, has not been for the faint-hearted. Confluent added some functionality for removing brokers in Confluent Platform 6.0, but the process was still somewhat convoluted and error-prone. Confluent Platform 7 (and Confluent Cloud) have improved upon the process, and this blog post looks at how it works.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-summit-london-2022-recap/">Kafka Summit London 2022: The Full Recap</a>. Kafka Summit 2022 was held a week - or so - ago, and it was held live! The post linked to summarises the conference and noteworthy sessions!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 17, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/01/interesting-stuff---week-17-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-01T08:35:51+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/01/interesting-stuff---week-17-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/f1.jpg" alt="" />
<strong>F1</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@gustavocpo">gustavo Campos</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="event-driven-architecture">Event Driven Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/event-driven-arch-challenges/">Event-based Architectures: The Hard Parts</a>. This is an <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> panel discussion where the panellists discuss the real hard parts of event-driven systems. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/f1-telemetry-analysis-with-azure-data-explorer-adx/ba-p/3283911">F1 telemetry analysis with Azure Data Explorer (ADX)</a>. You who follow my blog know that I like <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> and what one can do with it. However, you may not know that I am also quite interested in Formula 1 (F1). So seeing the title of the linked post certainly got my interest! The post looks at how you can emulate F1 telemetry using XBox, and ingest sensor events into Azure Data Explorer for further analysis. I found it very, very cool! Now, maybe I need to get an XBox!</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/internet-of-things-blog/use-azure-data-explorer-to-simplify-the-industrial-iot-data/ba-p/3292116">Use Azure Data Explorer to Simplify the Industrial IoT Data Journey</a>. <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> is the perfect tool to analyze IoT data. It is also well equipped for processing data pre-ingestion using its <em>update policy</em> functionality. This post looks at exactly that: ingesting IoT data into a staging table and then processing the data for ingestion into the final table(s).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/building-a-credit-card-fraud-detection-online-training-pipeline-with-river-ml-and-apache-flink-25549b89583d">Building a Credit Card Fraud Detection Online Training Pipeline with River ML and Apache Flink</a>. This post looks at writing real-time Python and Apache Flink applications to train and use Machine Learning models.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@datacouch/real-time-clickstream-analysis-using-ksqldb-ccd7f8a65bea">Real-Time Clickstream Analysis using KsqlDB</a>. As the title implies, this post looks at performing click-stream analysis using ksqlDB.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 16, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/24/interesting-stuff---week-16-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-04-24T08:44:24+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/24/interesting-stuff---week-16-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/scale.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Scale</strong> Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@saltsup?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Piret Ilver</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/scale?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.madeiradata.com/post/how-to-configure-auto-scaling-in-azure-data-explorer">How to Configure Auto-Scaling in Azure Data Explorer</a>. Azure Data Explorer uses a cluster of compute resources with the ability to scale up or down both vertically as well as horizontally. This blog post looks at how to auto-scale Azure Data Explorer horizontally.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/04/18/supercharge-your-machine-learning-projects-with-databricks-automl-now-generally-available.html">Supercharge Your Machine Learning Projects With Databricks AutoML — Now Generally Available!</a>. Machine Learning (ML) is at the heart of innovation across industries. At the same time, it can be hard to do. Something that can help is AutoML, and this post looks at Databricks AutoML, which is now generally available. It looks very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/is-the-modern-data-warehouse-broken-1c9cbfddec3e">Is The Modern Data Warehouse Broken?</a>. When browsing, I have recently come across posts/articles debating data warehousing. The post linked to is yet another one of these. The post introduces the <em>Immutable Data Warehouse</em>, where the warehouse should represent the real world through the data. It looks interesting, and we are thinking along the same lines at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/event-driven-utopia/unbundling-the-modern-streaming-stack-451f75eaf1d">Unbundling the Modern Streaming Stack</a>. The word <em>Modern</em> seems to be used more and more related to architecture/technologies. An example is above: the &ldquo;Modern Data Warehouse&rdquo;. Anyway, I digress; this post dissects the parts that make up the &ldquo;Modern&rdquo; Streaming stack. It compares the streaming landscape of yesteryear with what it looks like today and where it possibly can go.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/data-pipelines-are-even-easier-with-confluent-cli-v2/">Building a Bridge to the Cloud with Confluent CLI v2</a>. This post announces the release of the new Confluent CLI; <strong>Confluent CLI v2</strong>. The release merges the functionality of the &ldquo;old&rdquo; Confluent Cloud CLI, <code>ccloud</code> with the Confluent Platform CLI, <code>confluent</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 15, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/17/interesting-stuff---week-15-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-04-17T16:52:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/17/interesting-stuff---week-15-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/feather.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@lettis?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Letti Schm</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/collections/1992753/feathers?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-data-science-machine-learning">Data / Data Science / Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-gb/blog/feathr-linkedin-s-feature-store-is-now-available-on-azure/">Feathr: LinkedIn&rsquo;s feature store is now available on Azure</a>. In Data Science / Machine Learning, you have the concept of a <strong>Feature Store</strong>. The Feature Store is a place where features are centralized in an organization so they can be reused, served in a synchronous way between offline and online environments, and served in real-time with low latency. <strong>Feathr</strong> is the feature store that has been used in production and battle-tested in LinkedIn for over 6 years. It has now been open-sourced and made available on Azure. This blog post looks closer at what Feathr is and how you can get started with it.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/data-mesh-observability-pattern-467438627572">Data Mesh Observability Pattern</a>. The Data Mesh Observability Pattern helps you understand the state of your Data Mesh, the movement of its data, and its usage patterns. This blog post looks at how this pattern works and why it is crucial to the success of your enterprise Data Mesh.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/send-data-from-node-red-to-free-azure-data-explorer-kusto/ba-p/3282874">Send data from Node-RED to free Azure Data Explorer (Kusto)</a>. Node-RED is a flow-based development tool for visual programming, and it provides a browser-based editor that makes it easy to wire together flows. The flows are connected through nodes. This article describes how to send data directly from Node-RED to Azure Data Explorer using the new Node-RED to Kusto node.</li>
<li><a href="https://zimmergren.net/obfuscate-strings-in-kql-queries-adx/">Obfuscate strings in KQL queries</a>. This post does what it says &ldquo;on the tin&rdquo;. It looks at obfuscating strings in KQL queries in <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> to avoid displaying sensitive information when someone is reviewing executed queries.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-architecture-and-internals-by-jun-rao/">How Apache Kafka Works: An Introduction to Kafka&rsquo;s Internals</a>. You can be a decent developer without knowing/understanding the inner workings of your chosen technology(s). However, if you want to be great, it is a must to understand the underlying &ldquo;plumbing&rdquo;. This post announces a Kafka Internals course by Jun Rao. Jun was one of the original developers of Kafka and is co-founder of Confluent - he knows what he is talking about. If you are interested in Kafka, I urge you to have a look at that course.</li>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/presto-on-apache-kafka-at-uber-scale/">Presto® on Apache Kafka At Uber Scale</a>. This post looks at how Uber has connected Kafka and Presto together to enable a lightweight, interactive SQL query directly over Kafka via Presto at Uber scale.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 14, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/10/interesting-stuff---week-14-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-04-10T12:49:21+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/10/interesting-stuff---week-14-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/6-time-series-predictive-tasks-you-should-know-about-b899fb83b6bf">6 Time Series Predictive Tasks You Should Know About</a>. Recently I have gotten interested in Time Series analysis because of the Time Series capabilities in <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> and <strong>KQL</strong> (Kusto Query Language). Therefore this post comes at an opportune time as it describes predictive tasks that can be put together with time-series data sets.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/04/05/announcing-generally-availability-of-databricks-delta-live-tables-dlt.html">Announcing General Availability of Databricks&rsquo; Delta Live Tables (DLT)</a>. This post talks about the launch of Databricks&rsquo; Delta Live Tables and how it simplifies streaming and batch ETL for data, analytics and AI applications.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-betting-platform-with-confluent-cloud-and-ably/">Building a Dependable Real-Time Betting App with Confluent Cloud and Ably</a>. As you probably know by now, I work for <a href="/derivco"><strong>Derivco</strong></a>, and at Derivco, we develop software for online gaming. That&rsquo;s why this post is so interesting, as it looks at how to build a dependable real-time betting experience by combining the power of Confluent Cloud with the capabilities of the <a href="https://ably.com/">Ably</a> edge messaging platform.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-data-integration-analytics-confluent-azure-synapse-connector/">Migrating Data to Azure Synapse with Confluent&rsquo;s Fully Managed Connector to Unlock Real-Time Advanced Analytics</a>. This is another really interesting post for us at Derivco, as we are underway to implement an enterprise data lake using Azure. As part of the data lake, we are looking at Azure Synapse. So, reading this post about how Confluent integrates with Azure Synapse and enables real-time data processing and advanced analytics in Azure is very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 13, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/03/interesting-stuff---week-13-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-04-03T09:05:36+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/03/interesting-stuff---week-13-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/mbp-box.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>The Devil Wears <del>Prada</del> Skates</em></p>

<p>What you see in <em>Figure 1</em> is being explained further down!</p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that have to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data">Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/data-engineer-tools-c7e68eed28ad">Tools For Data Engineers</a>. Data Engineers are among the most valued people in modern data-driven organisations that aim to build or enhance products by utilising their most valuable asset: data! To make this happen, Data Engineers must ensure they are using the right tools. This blog post looks at some of the tools a Data Engineer should be familiar with.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theseattledataguy.com/data-platforms-vs-data-warehouses-vs-data-virtualization-and-federated-sql-engine-how-to-store-your-data/?utm_source=pocket_mylist#page-content">Data Platforms Vs Data Warehouses Vs Data Virtualization And Federated SQL Engine – How To Store Your Data</a>. There is a lot of discussion on how an organization should implement its data stacks today. This article discusses some of the popular routes data solution providers are talking about in terms of types of data layers.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/end-to-end-azure-data-explorer-pipeline-deployment-with-arm/ba-p/3248717">End to end Azure Data Explorer pipeline deployment with ARM</a>. You, who follow my blog, know that I am doing quite a lot of Azure Data Explorer &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; now. Setting up and tearing down ADX clusters is getting tedious, so the post linked to brings some good news: The ability to use ARM templates and BICEP scripts for deployment! Expect a blog post shortly about this!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/introducing-stream-processing-use-case-recipes-for-every-industry/">Introducing Stream Processing Use Case Recipes Powered by ksqlDB</a>. ksqlDB is the &ldquo;bee&rsquo;s knees&rdquo; for real-time stream processing. However, it can be tricky to get started, and there are an infinite number of use cases. That&rsquo;s what is being announced in this blog post aims to fix. The post introduces ksqlDB &ldquo;recipes&rdquo; consisting of pre-built code samples and a step-by-step tutorial to tackle the most popular, high-impact use cases for stream processing. Awesome!!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>So, a couple of weeks ago, I was at the SQLBits 2022 conference, where I gave some talks. This was the first &ldquo;live&rdquo; conference since the end of January 2020 (when I did MS Ignite, The World Tour). Since then, doing conference talks from home has been the norm, and I have been using my fully &ldquo;tricked out&rdquo; development PC for the talks.</p>

<p>When going to &ldquo;live&rdquo; conferences, I used my private laptop. A couple of days before leaving for London, I decided to ensure that I had all the necessary &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; on the laptop. Imagine my shock when I realized that the laptop no longer worked; I could not get it to boot! What to do? Fortunately, I have a work laptop, so I quickly copied the necessary slide decks, code, etc., and set off to London. Unfortunately, as it is a work laptop, there is some security &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; on the laptop, which meant that some of the things I was going to do didn&rsquo;t work as expected.</p>

<p>Coming home from London, I realized that I had to get a new laptop since - hopefully - we will now do in-person conferences again. The question was then, what laptop to get. Remember, I am a Windows &ldquo;dude&rdquo;. You probably now know what I got, especially seeing the picture in <em>Figure 1</em>. Yes, I got myself a MacBook Pro M1 (14 inches, 16Gb RAM):</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/mbp-unboxed-full.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2:</strong> <em>Ready for Setup</em></p>

<p>One week later, I have got a bit further than the setup in <em>Figure 2</em>. In fact, I am writing this post using my MBP. Expect a post or two about my experiences with the MBP in the coming weeks.</p>

<p>Oh, if you wonder about the <em>The Devil Wears Skates</em> title in <em>Figure 1</em>. As a hardcore Windows guy, I have been overheard saying that I will switch to Mac when &ldquo;hell freezes over&rdquo;. I guess hell must have frozen over now, and the Devil moves along on skates.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 12, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/03/27/interesting-stuff---week-12-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-03-27T08:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/03/27/interesting-stuff---week-12-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/preview-configure-adx-table-retention-caching-and-batching/ba-p/3262352">(Preview) Configure ADX table retention, caching and batching policies via one-click</a>. This post looks at something I just came across the other day when I edited the lab exercises for my one day Azure Data Explorer training class <em>A Day of Azure Data Explorer</em>. So what the post covers and I found out was how you can configure retention, batching &amp; caching policies for tables &amp; materialized views via one click. Quite cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://sqlofthenorth.blog/2022/03/10/building-the-lakehouse-architecture-with-synapse-analytics/">BUILDING THE LAKEHOUSE ARCHITECTURE WITH AZURE SYNAPSE ANALYTICS</a>. As the title says, this post looks at using the full range of Synapse services to build a lake house architecture on top of Azure Databricks Delta Lake tables.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2022/03/azure-purview-workflows-preview/">Orchestrate Operations, Validations, and Approvals on Data Entities with Azure Purview Workflows</a>. Azure Purview is a data governance service from Microsoft that automates the discovery and cataloging of data. It went into General Availability (GA) in October 2021. Recently Microsoft released as a preview Azure Purview Workflows. This article looks into the Purview Workflows and what you can do with them.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/event-driven-utopia/build-a-real-time-data-analytics-pipeline-with-airbyte-kafka-and-pinot-c9ff3c42dcf2">Build a real-time data analytics pipeline with Airbyte, Kafka, and Pinot</a>. This post looks at using Airbyte, Kafka and Pinot for building analytics dash boards for user-facing analysis. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/why-replace-zookeeper-with-kafka-raft-the-log-of-all-logs/">Why ZooKeeper Was Replaced with KRaft – The Log of All Logs</a>. Anyone interested in Kafka probably now knows how ZooKeeper is being replaced by a Raft based quorum protocol. This post explores the rationale behind the replacement, examines why Raft was utilized and altered to become KRaft and describes the new Quorum Controller built on top of KRaft protocols.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

