<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Niels Berglund</title>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com"/>
  <updated>2020-10-18T08:55:21+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://nielsberglund.com/</id>
  <generator uri="http://gohugo.io/">Hugo</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 42, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/10/18/interesting-stuff---week-42-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-10-18T08:55:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/10/18/interesting-stuff---week-42-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>Kafka, Kafka, and Kafka</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openshift.com/blog/introduction-to-kraken-a-chaos-tool-for-openshift/kubernetes">Introduction to Kraken, a Chaos Tool for OpenShift/Kubernetes</a>. As the title of this post says, it introduces a Kubernetes tool which by you can chaos test your Kubernetes cluster. It looks quite interesting and useful, and I have forwarded the post to the guys at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> looking at Kubernetes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.fullcontact.com/blog/2020/10/08/building-a-lambda-architecture-with-druid-and-kafka-streams/">Building a Lambda Architecture with Druid and Kafka Streams</a>. The post linked to here looks at how to use <a href="https://druid.apache.org/">Druid</a> together with KStreams to build a real-time analytical framework. Really interesting &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-real-time-materialized-views-work-with-ksqldb/">How Real-Time Materialized Views Work with ksqlDB, Animated</a>. The post delivers precisely what the title says: it looks at how materialized views work in ksqlDB. I really like the animations in the post, very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/real-time-api-kafka/">Real Time APIs in the Context of Apache Kafka</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article by the Kafka Guru <a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a> looks at how events together with real-time APIs can be used as the foundation for applications which are flexible yet performant; loosely-coupled yet efficient. Apache Kafka offers a scalable event streaming platform with which you can build applications around the powerful concept of events.<br /></li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/5-things-every-kafka-developer-should-know/">Top 5 Things Every Kafka Developer Should Know</a>. I believe that a developer, to be a good developer, should have an in-depth knowledge of the technologies he/she is working with. If you are using Kafka, then the post linked to here gives you a good start in understanding Kafka.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 41, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/10/11/interesting-stuff---week-41-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-10-11T08:57:28+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/10/11/interesting-stuff---week-41-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster">SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://mohammaddarab.com/stop-and-start-your-aks-big-data-cluster-and-save-money/">Stop and Start your AKS Big Data Cluster and Save $$$</a>. In this post, my good friend <a href="https://twitter.com/mwdarab">Mohammad</a> looks at new functionality in Azure Kubernetes Service, (AKS), whereby you can start and stop Kubernetes clusters at will. Mohammad looks at it from the perspective of SQL Server 2019 Big Data Clusters running in AKS.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/data-rocks/kafka-record-tracing-379ed2b0af51">Kafka record tracing</a>. Do you know how long it takes for messages to flow in your data pipeline? Do you know where the bottlenecks are? Why I ask these questions is that in a distributed system, the answers may not always be that easy to find. The post linked to here looks at solutions to these questions, and it looks at distributed tracing for Kafka.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-cluster-linking-with-confluent-platform/">Introducing Cluster Linking in Confluent Platform 6.0</a>. As the title of this post says, the post is about linking Kafka clusters to each other. From the post: &ldquo;Replicating topics between Kafka clusters has been a long-standing problem that’s seen a number of solutions, including MirrorMaker and Confluent Replicator. Although the utility of these projects has come a long way, they’re not without their respective issues.&rdquo;. The issues referred to in the previous sentence, is what the new cluster linking functionality is supposed to fix. It looks very promising, the one question I have right now is if this is a Confluent Platform Enterprise only functionality?</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/data-rocks/managing-kafka-connectors-at-scale-using-kafka-connect-manager-kcm-31d887de033c">Managing Kafka Connectors at scale using Kafka Connect Manager</a>. A while back we, (<a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>), looked at using CDC and Debezium to get data out from the database to Kafka. One of the problems we faced was how to manage the various Kafka Connectors, and ensure they were functioning correctly. The post I link to here would have been the perfect solution for us - a framework for managing Kafka Connectors. It would be interesting to know if it is open-sourced.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 40, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/10/04/interesting-stuff---week-40-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-10-04T15:40:24+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/10/04/interesting-stuff---week-40-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/09/29/diving-into-delta-lake-dml-internals-update-delete-merge.html">Diving Into Delta Lake: DML Internals (Update, Delete, Merge)</a>. Later releases of Delta Lake supports DML, (data manipulation language), statements. The post linked to here demonstrates how to use each of these DML commands, describes what Delta Lake is doing behind the scenes when you run one, and offers some performance tuning tips for each one. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/confluent-platform-6-0-delivers-the-most-powerful-event-streaming-platform-to-date/">Introducing Confluent Platform 6.0</a>. As the title of this post says; the post is about the new 6.0 release of Confluent Platform. Reading the post, this release looks huge. There are so many interesting things in there, but the ones that stand out for me are the ksqlDB improvements! For more information about the new ksqlDB functionality, look at the post <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-12-0-features-updates/">ksqlDB 0.12.0 Introduces Real-Time Query Upgrades and Automatic Query Restarts</a>. This is awesome!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-real-time-stream-processing-works-with-ksqldb/">How Real-Time Stream Processing Works with ksqlDB, Animated</a>. While we are on the subject of ksqlDB, this post is doing a great job how ksqlDB works. If you are interested in ksqlDB at all, you must read the post!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-java-client-iot-inspired-demo/">ksqlDB Meets Java: An IoT-Inspired Demo of the Java Client for ksqlDB</a>. Even more ksqlDB. The post linked to here looks at the new ksqlDB Java client. So, instead of using REST API&rsquo;s, you can now do ksqlDB &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; programmatically, using this new client, That is very, very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Yes, what AM I doing? Sometimes, quite often actually, I wonder that myself. Today, however, I do know what I am doing, or more specifically, what I just did! Yesterday, (October 3), I delivered a virtual conference talk at SQLBits about SQL Server and Kafka.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the talk was pre-recorded, and after I had uploaded the recording, the organizers did some editing. I messed up with what parts of the talk needed editing, so the result was that around a third of the talk was missing. Not good! Anyway, the organizers will do a re-edit and upload so that attendees can view it on demand. If you were one of the attendees, I do apologize again!</p>

<p>Anyway, today I uploaded the slide deck as well as all code for the talk, (including instructions). If you are interested, you can download it from <a href="https://nielsberglund.com/download/set-data-free-kafka.zip">here</a>. If you have questions comments etc., please <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping me</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 39, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/27/interesting-stuff---week-39-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-27T09:41:44+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/27/interesting-stuff---week-39-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/monzo-microservices/">Modern Banking in 1500 Microservices</a>. This is an <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation where the presenters explain how <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monzo_(bank)">Monzo</a> builds, operates, observes and maintains the banking infrastructure. They talk about how they compose microservices to add new functionality, deployment and incident tooling, monitoring practices and how they share knowledge effectively. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/podcasts/urban-planning-software-architecture/">Pat Helland on Software Architecture and Urban Planning</a>. The link here is to a podcast by the legendary <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pathelland/">Pat Helland</a> where he talks about the relationship between software architecture and urban planning. Pat explores planning for future growth, regulations/standards, and communication practices that cities - and software architecture - had to evolve to use. He uses these comparisons to distil lessons that architects can use in building distributed systems. If you are only going to listen to one podcast today, this week, month, etc., listen to this one!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-studio">Azure Data Studio</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/09/22/the-september-2020-release-of-azure-data-studio-is-now-available/">The September 2020 release of Azure Data Studio is now available</a>. As the title of the post says: a new version of Azure Data Studio is out. It has quite a few new features and enhancements, new notebook functionality, support for Kusto Query Language, (KQL), and other stuff. After I have published this post I will download this version and take it through its paces.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/09/24/open-sourcing-the-r-and-python-language-extensions-for-sql-server/">Open sourcing the R and Python language extensions for SQL Server</a>. Wow, this is big! Not only have the SQL Server language extensions for R and Python been open-sourced, but you can now use whatever version of R and Python you want, (well, more or less). Look out for some blog posts from me around this. Here are two links if you are interested in how it worked up until now: <a href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/sql-server-machine-learning-services/">Sql Server Machine Learning Services</a>, and <a href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/sql-server-extensibility-framework/">Sql Server Extensibility Framework</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-devops-with-confluent-kubernetes-and-gitops/">Apache Kafka DevOps with Kubernetes and GitOps</a>. The post linked to here looks at how we can do DevOps with Kafka and Kubernetes.</li>
<li><a href="https://blog.twitter.com/engineering/en_us/topics/infrastructure/2020/streaming-logging-pipeline-of-home-timeline-prediction-system.html">Streaming logging pipeline of Home timeline prediction system</a>. Twitter recently built a streaming data logging pipeline for its home timeline prediction system using Apache Kafka and Kafka Streams to replace the existing offline batch pipeline. This post looks at the architecture and how Twitter did it. In the post, it is mentioned that Twitter had to customise how KStreams left join semantic, and that is covered in the post: <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-twitter-built-a-machine-learning-pipeline-with-kafka/">Building a Machine Learning Logging Pipeline with Kafka Streams at Twitter</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 38, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/20/interesting-stuff---week-38-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-20T08:19:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/20/interesting-stuff---week-38-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-sql-server">Azure SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/09/17/azure-sql-digital-event-transform-your-applications-with-azure-sql/">Azure SQL digital event: Transform your applications with Azure SQL</a>. This post announces a webinar by <a href="https://twitter.com/bobwardms">Bob Ward</a> about Azure SQL, and how you can get the most out of Azure SQL. As the post says: &ldquo;<em>During this hour-long virtual event, I&rsquo;ll share my advice and guidance on getting the most out of Azure SQL, whether you’re looking to migrate from an on-premises SQL Server deployment or exploring ways to utilize the newest Azure SQL service options. You will also hear firsthand experiences and best practices from customers who have become expert Azure SQL users.</em>&rdquo;. Bob is a legend in the SQL Server world, so if you are interested, hurry up and register!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/superawesome-engineering/how-we-use-apache-druids-real-time-analytics-to-power-kidtech-at-superawesome-8da6a0fb28b1">How we use Apache Druid’s real-time analytics to power kidtech at SuperAwesome</a>. This post looks at real-time analytics of big data using Kafka and Apache Druid. I like the post a lot!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/09/15/easily-clone-your-delta-lake-for-testing-sharing-and-ml-reproducibility.html">Easily Clone your Delta Lake for Testing, Sharing, and ML Reproducibility</a>. The post linked to here introduces new functionality in Databricks Delta Lake; the ability to clone tables. This can come in handy for several scenarios: ML result reproducibility, data migration, significant changes to production tables, etc.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="event-driven-architecture">Event Driven Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/event-driven-finding-seams/">From Monolith to Event-Driven: Finding Seams in Your Future Architecture</a>. An excellent <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article looking at what we can do when we want to migrate from a monolithic architecture to a microservices/domain driven architecture.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/faun/event-driven-autoscaling-for-kubernetes-with-kafka-keda-d68490200812">Event-driven Autoscaling for Kubernetes with Kafka &amp; Keda</a>. A very cool post looking at how to scale Kafka consumers on Kubernetes. As I said, very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/stream-data-from-kafka-to-azure-data-explorer/">Streaming Data from Apache Kafka into Azure Data Explorer with Kafka Connect</a>. This blog post shows how to stream events from Apache Kafka on Confluent Cloud on Azure, into Azure Data Explorer, using the Kafka Connect Kusto Sink Connector.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>I am prepping for one of the largest data platform conferences taking place, (virtually), beginning of December this year: <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2020/"><strong>DATA PLATFORM VIRTUAL SUMMIT 2020</strong></a>. I hear you asking: &ldquo;why are you prepping?&rdquo;. Well, that&rsquo;s because:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Niels_Berglund.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>SQL Server &amp; Kafka</em></p>

<p>Yes, I am speaking at the conference! My topic is about, as you can see in <em>Figure 1</em>, the various ways we can stream data from SQL Server to Apache Kafka.</p>

<p>The conference has world class-speakers, (and me), so hurry up and <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2020/booking/">register</a>!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 37, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/13/interesting-stuff---week-37-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-13T09:38:45+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/13/interesting-stuff---week-37-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/distributed-video-sharing-demo/">Distributed Programming, Hash Tables, and Fun!</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenters demonstrate how they built a distributed hash-table video-sharing system, the technical hurdles encountered, and the pros/cons of using functional languages to do so. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://becominghuman.ai/cheat-sheets-for-ai-neural-networks-machine-learning-deep-learning-big-data-678c51b4b463">Cheat Sheets for AI, Neural Networks, Machine Learning, Deep Learning &amp; Big Data</a>. Cheat sheets are good, and I certainly need them. The post linked to gives, according to the post, <em>the most complete list of best AI cheat sheets</em>. I don&rsquo;t know about that, but there are some quite cool cheat sheets in there.</li>
<li><a href="https://dalelane.co.uk/blog/?p=4124">Using TensorFlow to make predictions from Kafka events</a>. This is a very interesting post, looking at how you can use Kafka and TensorFlow together to make machine learning predictions around sensor events.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/prioritize-messages-in-kafka/">Implementing Message Prioritization in Apache Kafka</a>. This post came at the exact right time, as I have been battling with how to implement priority messages in Kafka. In Rabbit, which we used previously, it was easy. In Kafka not so much. So reading about &ldquo;bucketing&rdquo; saved the day!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In <a href="/2020/09/06/interesting-stuff---week-36-2020/">last weeks roundup</a> I said how I was going to do a <strong>Derivco Webinar</strong> this week about <strong>SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>. Well, I did it September 10, it went off without a &ldquo;hitch&rdquo;, and - if I can say it myself - it was a lot of fun. If you are interested in seeing it, you find it on the Derivco YouTube channel <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EyCsQP5VJhU">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 36, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/06/interesting-stuff---week-36-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-09-06T08:40:13+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/09/06/interesting-stuff---week-36-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@madslundt/microservices-with-event-sourcing-using-net-core-33e3074171f5">Microservices with event sourcing using .NET Core</a>. This post looks at how to implement and structure an API using microservices and event sourcing. The article is very interesting, and it definitely gives &ldquo;food for thought&rdquo;!</li>
<li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/introducing-the-half-type/">Introducing the Half type!</a>. The title of the post says it all. Microsoft introduces a new type in .NET 5 - the <code>Half</code> type, which is <code>binary16</code>. The reason for this is that many computation workloads already take advantage of the <code>Half</code> type: machine learning, graphics cards, etc.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/oreillymedia/introducing-presto-839a26aac724">Introducing Presto</a>. Presto is a distributed SQL query engine, and it is designed to efficiently query data against disparate data sources of all sizes, ranging from gigabytes to petabytes. This post introduces Presto and looks at how Presto works. I find Presto very interesting in that we can use Presto to query Kafka!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/testing-kafka-applications/">Creating a Serverless Environment for Testing Your Apache Kafka Applications</a>. This post looks at how to use the <code>ccloud-stack</code> utility to create a serverless Kafka environment and how to use the Confluent Cloud CLI to provision a fully managed Datagen connector to pre-populate Kafka topics for your applications to use. Stay tuned for a blog-post from me where I test this out!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/confluent-cloud-enables-event-driven-architectures-everywhere-in-azure/">Enabling the Deployment of Event-Driven Architectures Everywhere Using Microsoft Azure and Confluent Cloud</a>. It becomes more and more common that we operate in a hybrid on-prem -&gt; cloud environment. Data migration can be a complex process. This post looks at how to build a persistent bridge from on-premises or other clouds to Microsoft Azure using Confluent Replicator.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Back in May I did together with <a href="https://charlla.com/">Charl</a> a <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> webinar around <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CSyNiEgEyvY">Kafka</a>. This coming week, (Thursday, Sep. 10), I am doing another webinar - this time about SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster. The webinar is open to everyone, and you can sign up <a href="https://derivco.co.za/derivco-webinar-a-lap-around-sql/">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 35, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/30/interesting-stuff---week-35-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-08-30T09:45:18+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/30/interesting-stuff---week-35-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-sql-database/what-is-azure-sql-edge-data-exposed/ba-p/1614877">What is Azure SQL Edge | Data Exposed</a>. This is part one of a three-part video series about Azure SQL Edge. In this part, we get an introduction to Azure SQL Edge and its features.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/08/27/enabling-spark-sql-ddl-and-dml-in-delta-lake-on-apache-spark-3-0.html">Enabling Spark SQL DDL and DML in Delta Lake on Apache Spark 3.0</a>. This post, and video, discuss some of the cool new features in Delta Lake 0.7.0. There are quite a lot of new exciting things in that release!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-summit-2020-session-highlights/">Best of Kafka Summit 2020 Roundup</a>. So, The Kafka Summit took place August 24 - 25, (virtually), and I managed to attend quite a few sessions. The post linked to here lists some of the &ldquo;must-see&rdquo; sessions. For me, the best session was the keynote the second day by Jay Kreps and Sam Newman. It was awesome!</li>
<li><a href="https://lenses.io/resources/streaming-sql-cheat-sheet-for-apache-kafka/">Streaming SQL Cheat Sheet for Apache Kafka</a>. As the title says, link to a cheat sheet for ksqlDB syntax. I have downloaded the cheat sheet and have it on my desktop so that I can access it easy!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kafka-streams-book.com/">Mastering Kafka Streams and ksqlDB</a>. The book in the post linked to here promises to be the &ldquo;go-to&rdquo; book for anything KStreams/ksqlDB related. I&rsquo;ll make sure my developers get some copies!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 34, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/23/interesting-stuff---week-34-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-08-23T11:47:46+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/23/interesting-stuff---week-34-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@danny.noam/http-based-contract-testing-gamesys-8c8d0d9aeee8">HTTP-Based Contract Testing @ Gamesys</a>. This is an interesting post discussing Contract Testing. Contract testing is testing between disparate, heterogenous components that interact via some binding interface. The interface is defined by a contract which defines the inputs and outputs between the components that are tested.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/08/21/top-5-reasons-to-convert-your-cloud-data-lake-to-a-delta-lake.html">Top 5 Reasons to Convert Your Cloud Data Lake to a Delta Lake</a>. Databricks Delta Lake is an open-source storage layer that brings reliability to data lakes. The post linked to here discusses the benefits of using a Delta Lake on top of your data lake.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@denniszielke/continuous-kubernetes-blue-green-deployments-on-azure-using-nginx-appgateway-or-trafficmanager-4490bce29cb">Continuous Kubernetes blue-green deployments on Azure using Nginx, AppGateway or TrafficManager — part 2</a>. This is the second part of a series of posts around advanced deployment processes. In this post, the author takes us through how to do blue-green deployments using Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS). Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://sbg.technology/2020/08/21/zero-downtime-kubernetes-deployments/">Zero-Downtime Kubernetes Deployments</a>. This post from one of <a href="/derivco">Derivco&rsquo;s</a> &ldquo;competitors&rdquo;, discusses how they do zero-downtime deployments. It is always interesting seeing how competitors are doing things!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-summit-2020-pro-tips-and-schedule/">How to Make the Most of Kafka Summit Virtually</a>. The, (virtual), Kafka Summit 2020, starts on Monday, (August 24). This post discusses how you - as an attendee - can get the most out of the conference. I will definitely be attending, and I hope I&rsquo;ll see you there!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/testing-kafka-streams/">Testing Kafka Streams – A Deep Dive</a>. This awesome post looks at how to do automated Kafka Streams testing; what tools to use and some of the problems you can run into. As I said, it is an awesome post - and I will make sure that the developers in my team dealing with Kafka Streams read the post. Yes, I am looking at you Stevo, and at you Reinhardt!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>One of the largest data platform conferences takes place, (virtually), beginning of December this year: <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2020/"><strong>DATA PLATFORM VIRTUAL SUMMIT 2020</strong></a>, and the cool things is:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/Niels_Berglund.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>SQL Server &amp; Kafka</em></p>

<p>Yes, I am speaking at the conference! My topic is about, as you can see in <em>Figure 1</em>, the various ways we can stream data from SQL Server to Apache Kafka.</p>

<p>The conference has world class-speakers, (and me), so hurry up and <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2020/booking/">register</a>!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 33, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/16/interesting-stuff---week-33-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-08-16T09:54:48+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/16/interesting-stuff---week-33-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-studio">Azure Data Studio</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/08/12/the-august-2020-release-of-azure-data-studio-is-now-available/">The August 2020 release of Azure Data Studio is now available</a>. As the title says, a new version of Azure Data Studio. There are quite a few Jupyter Notebooks enhancements in this release. Now I am waiting for the ability to execute individual lines of code in a Notebook cell.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/telltale-netflix-application-monitoring-simplified-5c08bfa780ba">Telltale: Netflix Application Monitoring Simplified</a>. This post about monitoring at Netflix came at a really good time for me, as at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> we are looking at improving our monitoring. So the post gives me food for thought.</li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/patterns-of-distributed-systems/">Patterns of Distributed Systems</a>. This article came to my attention thanks to a colleague of mine - thanks, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/scott-dukes-aaa49154/">Scott</a>! It discusses patterns for distributed systems, and how we can build up an understanding of how to better understand, communicate and teach distributed system design.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-state-stores-in-recovery/">The Curious Incident of the State Store in Recovery in ksqlDB</a>. This is a great article looking at the inner workings of ksqlDB. It is a must-read for anyone working with ksqlDB, (IMHO).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-consumer-multi-threaded-messaging/">Multi-Threaded Message Consumption with the Apache Kafka Consumer</a>. Kafka consumers are not thread-safe, so you need to be very careful if you want to implement a multi-threaded consumer. The article linked to here drills down into the internals of Kafka consumers, and looks at how to create a multi-threaded consumer.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>We are still in lockdown, but from tomorrow the restrictions are eased somewhat:</p>

<ul>
<li>Intra-province travel is allowed.</li>
<li>Bars and restaurants can sell alcohol.</li>
<li>Alcohol and cigarettes can be sold.</li>
</ul>

<p>Even though the restrictions are eased, I gather it will be a long time before we&rsquo;ll be back in the office. Oh, well - it is what it is.</p>

<p>On Tuesday, (Aug 18), I co-host the 4th installment of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/272339566/">Azure Sketches</a>. In this session, we share our expertise and experience if you want to deliver remote working solutions to help inside a global pandemic. Fast, Remote, Agile Application and desktop solutions delivered through Azure. NGOs and Non-Profits are welcome.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 32, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/09/interesting-stuff---week-32-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-08-09T07:36:58+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/09/interesting-stuff---week-32-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-sql">Azure SQL</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-sql-database/learning-how-to-transition-your-sql-server-skills-to-azure-sql/ba-p/1571163">Learning How to Transition Your SQL Server Skills to Azure SQL | Data Exposed</a>. This post introduces courses and workshops for you to learn Azure SQL. I have had a look at the material, and it is awesome!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/dataseries/netflixs-polynote-is-a-new-open-source-framework-to-build-better-data-science-notebooks-4bdab6b8d0ae">Netflix’s Polynote is a New Open Source Framework to Build Better Data Science Notebooks</a>. In this post, the author discusses Polynote. Polynote is a new notebook environment which provides substantial improvements to streamline experimentation in machine learning workflows.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/state-art-automl/">State of the Art in Automated Machine Learning</a>. This is an <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article summarising a panel discussion where the panel members discussed the state of the art in automated machine learning (AutoML). Some very interesting ideas and thoughts!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-2-6-updates/">What’s New in Apache Kafka 2.6</a>. The post linked to here discusses some of the new features in Kafka 2.6, which was released in early August. Some exciting things in the new release!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/tencent-kafka-process-10-trillion-messages-per-day/">How Tencent PCG Uses Apache Kafka to Handle 10 Trillion+ Messages Per Day</a>. Tencent is one of the largest Kafka users in the world, processing trillions of messages every day. This article, introduces Tencent&rsquo;s journey of building federated Kafka clusters for business use cases that require high scalability and fault tolerance. Some very fascinating concepts in the post. I will definitely look at some of the things mentioned.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-11-0-features-and-improvements/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.11.0</a>. Above I linked to a post related to a new Kafka release. The post here introduces a new ksqlDB release and looks at some of the new features.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/confluent-cloud-for-apache-kafka-everywhere/">Project Metamorphosis Month 4: Confluent Cloud for Apache Kafka Available Everywhere</a>. This post announces how Confluent Cloud is now available on all major cloud providers! Expect a blog post where I look at Confluent Cloud on Azure.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 31, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/02/interesting-stuff---week-31-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-08-02T14:17:05+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/08/02/interesting-stuff---week-31-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/infrastructure-monitoring-with-ksqldb-udtf/">Data Enrichment in ksqlDB Using UDTFs</a>. A very interesting post using ksqlDB and user defined functions for monitoring purposes. I will definitely try this!</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/an-introduction-to-stream-processing-with-apache-flink-b4acfa58f14d">An Introduction to Stream Processing with Apache Flink</a>. As the title says, the post introduces Apache Flink. It presents an overview of Apache Flink and its key features for streaming applications.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/realtime-event-driven-ecosystem/">The Challenges of Building a Reliable Real-Time Event-Driven Ecosystem</a>. There is an increasing appetite for data delivered in real-time, and this post looks at differences between the REST model and real-time APIs.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@jm4668/event-sourcing-from-static-data-using-kafka-d00069332802">Event sourcing from static data using Kafka</a>. This post looks at how we can generate events from changes to static data by using Kafka and ksqlDB. I found this post very useful!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/how-pushowl-uses-ksqldb-to-scale-analytics-and-reporting-use-cases/">How PushOwl Uses ksqlDB to Scale Their Analytics and Reporting Use Cases</a>. This is a very interesting post looking at how ksqlDB makes it easy to integrate event streaming applications into any tech stack.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-10-updates-key-columns/">I&rsquo;ve Got the Key, I&rsquo;ve Got the Secret. Here&rsquo;s How Keys Work in ksqlDB 0.10.</a>. The ksqlDB release 0.10 changes and improves how keys are handled. This post looks at some of the changes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Not so much what I am doing, but on Monday Derivco holds a webinar where the speaker is Lillian Barnard - the managing director of Microsoft SA. She&rsquo;ll be talking about building strong, high-performing teams as well as discussing creating diverse and inclusive workplaces.</p>

<p>Sign up <a href="https://derivco.co.za/webinar-with-lillian-barnard/">here</a>!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 30, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/26/interesting-stuff---week-30-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-07-26T13:01:43+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/26/interesting-stuff---week-30-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/07/22/a-comprehensive-look-at-dates-and-timestamps-in-apache-spark-3-0.html">A Comprehensive Look at Dates and Timestamps in Apache Spark 3.0</a>. Apache Spark 3.0 was released recently with quite a lot of new features and also changes to existing functionality and data types. This blog post deep dives into the <code>Date</code> and <code>Timestamp</code> types and tries to explain their behavior.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/kafka-data-privacy-security-and-compliance/">Data Privacy, Security, and Compliance for Apache Kafka</a>. There are increased regulatory demands for protecting personal/sensitive data. The blog post linked to here introduces Privitar Data Privacy Platform, and it looks at how it integrates to Confluent Platform through Privitar Kafka Connector.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/monitoring-confluent-cloud-ksqldb-stream-processing-service/">Measuring and Monitoring a Stream Processing Cloud Service: Inside Confluent Cloud ksqlDB</a>. This is the third is a series of posts on enhancements to ksqlDB to enable its offering in Confluent Cloud. Very interesting read!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/simplified-robust-exactly-one-semantics-in-kafka-2-5/">Improved Robustness and Usability of Exactly-Once Semantics in Apache Kafka</a>. Back in 2017, Confluent <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/exactly-once-semantics-are-possible-heres-how-apache-kafka-does-it/">introduced exactly-once semantics</a> in Kafka. Initially, it was met with a healthy dose of scepticism, but after a while, the doubt died away when people saw it working. This post discusses the recent improvements on exactly-once semantics (EOS) to make it simpler to use and more resilient. We are getting there, my friends!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 29, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/19/interesting-stuff---week-29-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-07-19T11:34:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/19/interesting-stuff---week-29-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/implementing-a-data-lake-architecture-for-business-intelligence-f2c99551db1a">Implementing a Data Lake or Data Warehouse Architecture for Business Intelligence?</a>. In this post, the author explains what business intelligence is, and compares Data warehouse and Data Lake architecture for doing Business intelligence. Interesting read, even though I may not agree with some of the sentiments in the post.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/07/15/spark-ai-summit-reflections.html">Spark + AI Summit Reflections</a>. The <a href="https://databricks.com/sparkaisummit/north-america-2020">Spark + AI Summit</a> was held June 22 - 26, and this post looks at some of the interesting keynotes and sessions from a developers perspective. Some cool &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; in there!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-science">Data Science</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@karthik.vaithyanathan/using-continuous-machine-learning-to-run-your-ml-pipeline-eeeeacad69a3">Using Continuous Machine Learning to Run Your ML Pipeline</a>. We live in a DevOps and CI/CD world! However, when doing Machine Learning, it is somewhat tricky. This post introduces <a href="https://cml.dev/">Continuous Machine Learning</a>, (CML), which is an open-source library for implementing continuous integration &amp; delivery (CI/CD) in machine learning projects. Looks very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/top-5-reasons-to-attend-kafka-summit/">Top 5 Reasons to Attend Kafka Summit Virtually</a>. So the virtual <a href="https://kafka-summit.org/">Kafka Summit 2020</a> is right around the corner. In the linked post <a href="https://twitter.com/tlberglund">Tim Berglund</a>, (no, we are not related), lists some reason why you should attend. I have registered, and I hope to see you there!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Still in lockdown, and still no end in sight for follow up post to <a href="/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/"><strong>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology</strong></a>. I am working on it, but can&rsquo;t seem to get the words onto paper, or rather the screen. The post is supposed to be about the architecture of the Big Data Cluster.</p>

<p>On Tuesday, (July 21), I am co-hosting the third <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271857436/"><strong>The Azure Sketches, Architect Series</strong></a> webinar together with Gordon Beeming and Lawrance Reddy. We use a combination of traditional drawing &amp; sketching with actual solution building to help reinforce the thought process in building Azure solutions and all of the dependencies in between. If you are interested, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271857436/">here</a> is the link for registration.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 28, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/12/interesting-stuff---week-28-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-07-12T07:13:58+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/12/interesting-stuff---week-28-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-sql-database/covid-19-data-analytics-and-reporting-with-azure-databricks-and/ba-p/1505849">COVID-19 data analytics and reporting with Azure Databricks and Azure SQL</a>. This post demonstrates the integration between Azure Databricks and Azure SQL to deliver insights and data visualizations using a publicly available COVID-19 dataset. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/deep-learning-with-apache-spark-part-1-6d397c16abd">Deep Learning With Apache Spark — Part 1</a>. If you are interested in Apache Spark, then this post is for you. It is the first post in a series on how to do Distributed Deep Learning with Apache Spark. This post looks at the basics of Spark and Deep Learning, plus a little bit more.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/swlh/what-is-and-why-delta-lake-how-change-data-capture-cdc-gets-benefits-from-delta-lake-fb177bdab8bc">Why Delta Lake ? How Change Data Capture (CDC) gets benefits from Delta Lake</a>. The post here looks at how the Delta Lake can overcome some of the inherent problems with today&rsquo;s data lakes.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.theseattledataguy.com/5-trends-in-big-data-and-sql-to-be-excited-about-in-2020/">5 TRENDS IN BIG DATA AND SQL TO BE EXCITED ABOUT IN 2020</a>. This post summarizes some of the major trends currently occurring in the SQL and data analytics world. It looks at how SQL is becoming more collaborative and open, and how the majority of databases we use are open source or switching to open source.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/multiple-event-types-in-the-same-kafka-topic/">Putting Several Event Types in the Same Topic – Revisited</a>. This post looks at how we can put different event types in the same topic using a new Schema Registry feature introduced in Confluent Platform 5.5: schema references. I wonder whether this changes how we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> deal with event types and topics?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 27, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/05/interesting-stuff---week-27-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-07-05T09:32:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/07/05/interesting-stuff---week-27-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/how-you-should-read-research-papers-according-to-andrew-ng-stanford-deep-learning-lectures-98ecbd3ccfb3">How You Should Read Research Papers According To Andrew Ng (Stanford Deep Learning Lectures)</a>. This post looks at how to approach knowledge acquisition through published research papers. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/cuda-on-wsl2-for-deep-learning-first-impressions-and-benchmarks-3c0178754035">Cuda on WSL2 for Deep Learning — First Impressions and Benchmarks</a>. A cool post about running CUDA on WSL2. This is something I need to check out!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="domain-driven-design">Domain Driven Design</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/walmartlabs/building-domain-driven-microservices-af688aa1b1b8">Building Domain Driven Microservices</a>. This blog post covers various concepts, strategies, and design heuristics to consider when you go into the world of microservices. More specifically when you to break a monolith into multiple domain-based microservices.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/kafka-for-your-data-pipeline-why-not-5a14b50efe7f">Kafka, for your data pipeline? Why not?</a>. The post here looks at how you can create a streaming data pipeline using Docker, Kafka, and Kafka Connect. Very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/infinite-kafka-data-storage-in-confluent-cloud/">Project Metamorphosis Month 3: Infinite Storage in Confluent Cloud for Apache Kafka</a>. This post discusses how Confluent is working towards limitless storage for Confluent Cloud. This looks very interesting, now if this could come for Kafka on-prem as well!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Wow! We are already in July - where has the first part of the year gone? Let&rsquo;s hope that the rest of the year will be better than the first half!</p>

<p>So, in last week&rsquo;s <a href="/2020/06/28/interesting-stuff---week-26-2020/">roundup</a>, I wrote these are nervous times right now, as it is MVP renewal time. The renewals should happen Wednesday, July 1st. I can say I was not that productive that day, as I mostly refreshed my email client to see whether there was an email saying if I were renewed or not.</p>

<p>The day dragged on, and I heard from some of my fellow MVP&rsquo;s how they had received their renewal emails - that did not make me feel any better, and then I received this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/mvp-2020.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>MVP Renewal</em></p>

<p>Phew, I am renewed for another year. Thank you, Microsoft!</p>

<p>Ok, enough about that. This week on Tuesday, (July 7th), the Azure User Group here in Durban have our monthly <em>News and Catchup</em> meeting. If you want to come and hang out, (virtually), the link is <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271041672/">here</a>. See you Tuesday!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 26, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/28/interesting-stuff---week-26-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-28T10:04:18+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/28/interesting-stuff---week-26-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/06/22/apache-spark-connector-for-sql-server-and-azure-sql-is-now-open-source/">Apache Spark Connector for SQL Server and Azure SQL is now open source</a>. As the title says, the post announces the open-sourcing of the Spark Connector for SQL Server. From the post: <em>The Apache Spark Connector for SQL Server and Azure SQL is a high-performance connector that enables you to use transactional data in big data analytics and persists results for ad-hoc queries or reporting. The connector allows you to use any SQL database, on-premises or in the cloud, as an input data source or output data sink for Spark jobs.</em> This is very, very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/06/23/expanding-sql-server-big-data-clusters-capabilities-now-on-red-hat-openshift/">Expanding SQL Server Big Data Clusters capabilities, now on Red Hat OpenShift</a>. As you probably know, I have an interest in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster. One of the questions that often come up is if one can run it on RedHat OpenShift, and the answer to that has been no, you cannot. That is until now, with the release of SQL Server cumulative update 5, (CU5). The post linked to here discusses it more in detail. Watch this space for a post about how to install the BDC on the RedHat OpenShift platform.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-systems">Distributed Systems</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.softwaremill.com/cure-your-fomo-apache-ignite-in-5-minutes-550d84b10ce3">Cure your FOMO — what is Apache Ignite in 5 minutes</a>. The post linked to here is about Apache Ignite which is essentially an in-memory data-grid/in-memory cache layer. It looks interesting, and let&rsquo;s see if we can do something with it at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-10-0-latest-features-updates/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.10.0</a>. This post discusses the new release of ksqlDB. There are quite a few new interesting features, that I am looking forward to testing! Let us hope they will have a .NET client soon in addition to the Java client.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/unifying-streams-and-state-seamless-path-to-real-time/">Unifying Streams and State: The Seamless Path to Real-Time</a>. This post and the accompanying video looks at how easy it is to do stream processing applications with Confluent Cloud and ksqlDB. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>These are nervous times! No, not because of COVID-19, but something much more serious: it is renewal time for MVP! July first all MVP&rsquo;s will know whether they have been renewed for another year. I have a funny feeling that I haven&rsquo;t done enough, but I guess we&rsquo;ll see on Wednesday!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/21/interesting-stuff---week-25-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-21T09:18:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/21/interesting-stuff---week-25-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/feature-toggles/">Feature Toggles: The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly</a>. An <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation where the presenter covers how to use feature toggles effectively, some of the horror stories and how to avoid them, and how to deal with them if they do occur.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ververica.com/blog/flink-for-online-machine-learning-and-real-time-processing-at-weibo">Flink for online Machine Learning and real-time processing at Weibo</a>. This post looks at the architecture of Weibo&rsquo;s Machine Learning platform and how they use Apache Flink to develop their real-time Machine Learning pipelines. I found this post very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-studio">Azure Data Studio</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/sql-server/released-sql-server-assessment-extension-for-azure-data-studio/ba-p/1470603">SQL Server Assessment Extension for Azure Data Studio</a>. This is very cool! An extension to Azure Data Studio which provides a user interface for evaluating SQL Server instances and databases for best practices.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/guide-to-kafka-pricing-and-diy-open-source-costs/">The Cost of Apache Kafka: An Engineer’s Guide to Pricing Out DIY Operations</a>. This is a very interesting post, looking at costings of running Kafka. It definitely provides food for thought.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In last weeks roundup, I mentioned about the second <strong>The Azure Sketches, Architect Series</strong> webinar, and how we should run it on Wednesday, June 17. Well, that didn&rsquo;t happen so we run it this coming Tuesday, (June 23), instead. Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271102120/">here</a> if you are interested.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 24, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/14/interesting-stuff---week-24-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-14T09:27:04+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/14/interesting-stuff---week-24-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/apache-hudi-graduation/">Building a Large-scale Transactional Data Lake at Uber Using Apache Hudi</a>. Hudi, developed by Uber, is similar to <a href="https://databricks.com/product/delta-lake-on-databricks">Delta Lake</a> in that it enables ACID semantics, (plus more), on data lakes. This post describes Uber&rsquo;s journey to building, releasing, and optimizing Apache Hudi.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://muratbuffalo.blogspot.com/2020/06/learning-about-distributed-systems.html">Learning about distributed systems: where to start?</a>. This post by <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> looks at resources to really learn and understand distributed computing. I urge you to look and read the resources <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> lists!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/streaming-databases/">Databases and Stream Processing: A Future of Consolidation</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenter digs into why both stream processors and databases are necessary from a technical standpoint but also by exploring industry trends that make consolidation in the future far more likely. He examines how these trends map onto common approaches from active databases like MongoDB to streaming solutions like Flink, Kafka Streams or ksqlDB.</li>
<li><a href="https://events.confluent.io/usecasesandarchitecturesforapa">Use Cases and Architectures for Apache Kafka and Event Streaming in the Gaming Industry</a>. Do.Not.Miss.This! The link here is for the registration page for a Confluent event where <a href="https://twitter.com/KaiWaehner">Kai Wähner</a> looks at how Kafka and Confluent Cloud provides a scalable, reliable and efficient infrastructure to make gamers happy and gaming companies successful.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Lockdown, lockdown, lockdown! What I would not give to be able to go out and have dinner with good friends at a restaurant right now!</p>

<p>Apart from that, things are not that bad. I am still working on the follow-up to the <a href="/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/"><strong>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology</strong></a> post. The upcoming post looks at the architecture. So when will it be published you may ask - I have no idea!</p>

<p>On Wednesday, (June 17), I am co-hosting the second <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271102120/"><strong>The Azure Sketches, Architect Series</strong></a> webinar together with Gordon Beeming and Lawrance Reddy. We use a combination of traditional drawing &amp; sketching with actual solution building to help reinforce the thought process in building Azure solutions and all of the dependencies in between. If you are interested, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271102120/">here</a> is the link for registration.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/07/interesting-stuff---week-23-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-07T09:57:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/07/interesting-stuff---week-23-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-sql-database/azure-sql-sessions-recap-at-microsoft-build-2020/ba-p/1432139">Azure SQL Sessions Recap at Microsoft Build 2020</a>. This post contains links to all the various sessions around Azure SQL Server at this year&rsquo;s MS Build conference. Quite a few very interesting sessions!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-ensures-consistent-internal-state-reliability-recovery-using-kafka-transactions/">Consistent Metastore Recovery for ksqlDB Using Apache Kafka Transactions</a>. The post linked to here is a continuation of the post I covered in my <a href="/2020/05/03/interesting-stuff---week-18-2020/">week 18</a> roundup; about <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/building-ksqldb-event-streaming-database/">ksqlDB Execution Plans</a>. This week&rsquo;s post discusses some of the work that’s gone into preserving the integrity of ksqlDB’s internal state in interactive mode.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/stream-processing-iot-data-best-practices-and-techniques/">Stream Processing with IoT Data: Challenges, Best Practices, and Techniques</a>. In this post, the author looks at Tesla&rsquo;s architecture and tech for handling IoT data. I found the post very interesting, and, even though at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> we do not deal with IoT data, we can definitely implement some of the principles outlined in the post.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/netflix-event-stream-flink/">Taming Large State: Lessons from Building Stream Processing</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenters talk about how Netflix solved a complex join of two high-volume event streams using Flink. They also discuss managing out of order events and processing late arriving data.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/fleet-management-gps-tracking-with-confluent-cloud-mongodb/">Real-Time Fleet Management Using Confluent Cloud and MongoDB</a>. The post linked to here looks at how to build a system incorporating ksqlDB, Kafka Connect, MongoDB, all in the cloud. The solution, in this case, is for fleet management, but it could be anything. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>As I wrote in the <a href="/2020/05/31/interesting-stuff---week-22-2020/">roundup from last week</a>, lockdown restrictions here in SA have been relaxed, a bit. That means that you can now exercise whenever you want, instead of between 06:00 - 10:00 am; yay!, (that was sarcasm). For me, nothing has really changed, and I do not think I&rsquo;ll be back in the office until July/August.</p>

<p>In our <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/">Durban Azure Transformation Labs</a> user group, we had the first monthly News &amp; Catchup meeting. This meeting is virtual, and we get together the first Tuesday every month chatting about what has happened in the industry during the month just gone by. If you are interested in what was said, the recording of the event 10 is up on YouTube: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YxLQOaEnCqY">News &amp; Catch up June 2020</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

