<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Niels Berglund</title>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com"/>
  <updated>2022-09-25T08:31:25+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://nielsberglund.com/</id>
  <generator uri="http://gohugo.io/">Hugo</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 38, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/25/interesting-stuff---week-38-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-09-25T08:31:25+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/25/interesting-stuff---week-38-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/churn.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Churn</em></p></strong>
<strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@sweetpagesco">Sarah Brown</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/churn">Unsplash</a></em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="ai-ml">AI/ML</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/this-is-how-you-can-build-a-churn-prediction-model-using-spark-e187b7eca339">This Is How You Can Build a Churn Prediction Model Using Apache Spark</a>. At <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, we&rsquo;re looking at creating ML models for churn, so lately, I&rsquo;ve been reading posts around this subject. I came across this post, a tutorial on building a churn prediction classifier using the ML stack from Spark. Very interesting and informative!</li>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/introduction-to-confusion-matrix-50676f2756ee">Introduction to Confusion Matrix</a>. When I first heard the term confusion matrix, I thought it was called so because you became confused trying to interpret it, 😄. Anyway, this post tries to explain what a confusion matrix is and how you can plot one using Python. When reading the post, remember that the algorithm used is to predict someone is sick.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://thesecretlivesofdata.com/raft/">Raft - Understandable Distributed Consensus</a>. Raft is a consensus algorithm that is designed to be easy to understand. Going forward, Kafka will use Raft instead of ZooKeeper. The page linked to is a visualization of how Raft works. My first thought was that &ldquo;this looks very much like a distributed transaction&rdquo;. Anyway, the visualization is very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/patterns-of-distributed-systems/">Patterns of Distributed Systems</a>. If you think: &ldquo;has Niels not linked to this before&rdquo;, you are absolutely correct. In 2020 I linked to this in one of my <a href="/2020/08/16/interesting-stuff---week-33-2020/">roundups</a>. At that stage, the compendium about the patterns for distributed systems was a work in progress. Now it is completed, and if you are interested in distributed systems, you must read it!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/check-it-out-azure-data-explorer-ms-learn-modules/ba-p/3633934">Check it out: Azure Data Explorer MS Learn modules</a>. The title says it all! <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> (ADX) has new MS Learn modules. If you want to learn ADX - check them out!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/sync-databases-and-remove-silos-with-kafka-cdc/">Keeping Multiple Databases in Sync Using Kafka Connect and CDC</a>. This blog post looks at how to keep databases in sync using Kafka technologies and CDC. It reviews the advantages and disadvantages of using JDBC and CDC for moving data. It then explores the real use case of how a legacy bank used Kafka Connect to bridge the silos and keep multiple applications/databases in sync.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/error-handling-with-apache-kafka-extension-for-azure-functions/ba-p/3628936">Error Handling with Apache Kafka extension for Azure Functions and more!!</a>. The Kafka extension for Azure functions was released recently with some cool features. As a side note, we (<a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>) are using it - awesome! Anyway, this post looks at some features in the Kafka extension. I particularly like the error handling (not that my code has any errors, but &hellip; 😄).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>This:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/adx-overview.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Azure Data Explorer</em></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/">Azure Durban User Group</a> are back to in-person meetings - yay! This Wednesday (Sep 28), I am doing an <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> presentation.</p>

<p>Come and join us if you are in the &lsquo;hood. The event is <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/288687700/">FREE</a>, and you register <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/288687700/">here</a>. See you on Wednesday!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 37, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/18/interesting-stuff---week-37-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-09-18T13:24:26+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/18/interesting-stuff---week-37-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/stream.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Stream</em></p></strong>
<strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo by: <a href="https://www.istockphoto.com/portfolio/kata716">kata716</a></em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/10-vscode-productivity-hacks-for-data-scientists-1836f87e0525">10 VSCode Productivity Hacks for Data Scientists</a>. Yes, I know; the title of this post says Data Scientists. With that in mind, I should have put it under the <strong>AI/ML</strong> section. However, the &ldquo;hacks&rdquo; in the post are not only useful for Data Scientists but for anyone using Python and VSCode. The post is not so much about hacks as it is about useful VSCode extensions, and I picked up a couple that I want to test.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://arcanecode.com/2022/09/12/fun-with-kql-format_datetime/">Fun With KQL – Format_DateTime</a>. I hate dealing with date-time! That&rsquo;s why I really like the Kusto Query Language (KQL) feature that this post discusses: the <code>format_datime</code> function. Read the post to see how it can be used. Very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://detective.kusto.io/">Kusto Detective Agency</a>. The Kusto Detective Agency is a way to promote <em>Azure Data Explorer</em> and the <strong>KQL</strong> (the Kusto Query Language). You join the &ldquo;agency&rdquo; by creating a free Azure Data Explorer cluster and providing an answer to a question. Looks really cool. I joined earlier in the week, and I&rsquo;ll keep you informed on how it goes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ai-ml">AI/ML</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/serving-ml-models-with-apache-spark-3adc278f7a78">Serving ML Models with Apache Spark</a>. This post covers more than what the title says. Yes, the post definitely looks at how to serve up <strong>MLLib</strong> models, but it also gives a comprehensive introduction to Spark. Very useful!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://rmoff.net/2022/09/14/stretching-my-legs-in-the-data-engineering-ecosystem-in-2022/">Stretching my Legs in the Data Engineering Ecosystem in 2022</a>. This is the first post in a series by Mr Kafka (<a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a>), where he looks at what is going on in the data engineering world nowadays. This is a must-read for anyone interested in data engineering!</li>
<li><a href="https://rmoff.net/2022/09/14/data-engineering-resources/">Data Engineering: Resources</a>. This is from the link above. This post lists useful links to resources around data engineering.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2022/real-time-analytics-on-network-flow-data-with-apache-pinot">Real-time analytics on network flow data with Apache Pinot</a>. Having observability of your infrastructure is of vital importance to be able to detect, diagnose, and remediate issues. This post looks at what LinkedIn has done to provide observability into network flows. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-gaming-infrastructure-kafka-ksqldb-websockets/">Real-Time Gaming Infrastructure for Millions of Users with Apache Kafka, ksqlDB, and WebSockets</a>. This post which shows a real-time gamification demo to integrate gamers via WebSockets to the data streaming backend infrastructure is interesting to me from a couple of points. It is interesting as we (<a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>) are in the iGaming industry. It is also interesting as we are doing something very similar right now!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Just reminding you of this (especially you, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lee-anne-james-96514023/">Lee-Anne</a> lol)</p>


<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/KZbMtYmM-2o" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>


<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to register for <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/booking/"><strong>Data Platform Summit 2022</strong></a>. Having registered, you can attend my session: <strong>ksqlDB - The Real Time Streaming Database</strong>, and obviously many other cool sessions as well.</p>

<p>Oh, and attending the conference is <strong>FREE</strong>, so what are you waiting for: <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/booking/"><strong>register</strong></a>!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 36, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/11/interesting-stuff---week-36-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-09-11T08:14:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/11/interesting-stuff---week-36-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/deepmind.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@deepmind?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">DeepMind</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/reinforcement-learning?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/blog/a-game-theoretic-approach-to-provably-correct-and-scalable-offline-rl/">A game-theoretic approach to provably correct and scalable offline RL</a>. This post looks at reinforcement learning (RL) and a way to design a systematic and provably correct way to create offline RL algorithms that can learn good policies with state-of-the-art empirical performance.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/generally-available-kusto-emulator/ba-p/3616093">Generally available: Kusto Emulator</a>. This is awesome! Microsoft has released a Docker image exposing the Kusto Query Engine endpoint in Azure Data Explorer. This means we can now create databases, and ingest and query data in a local environment!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/iot-real-time-analytics-wago-plc-with-databricks-auto-loader-4cd9d3c8de15">IoT Real-Time Analytics — WAGO PLC with Databricks Auto Loader</a>. Databricks Auto Loader allows you to stream or incrementally ingest and transform files from a data lake. This post looks at a solution whereby IoT messages are sent to an Azure IoT hub and ingested in Azure Data Lake Storage (ADLS). From ADLS, the data is streamed into Azure Databricks Delta Tables using Databricks Auto Loader. Very interesting, this may be something for us at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
<li><a href="https://lgouellec.github.io/kafka-streams-dotnet/">Welcome to Streamiz.Kafka.Net</a>. If you have used Kafka, you are probably aware of KStreams, the library to create stream processing applications. You are also most likely aware that KStreams is Java/Scala only. That is about to change now with Streamiz, a .NET stream processing library for Kafka, i.e. similar to KStreams. It is in active development, and if you are into Kafka, stream processing and .NET, I urge you to look at it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>I am prepping for this:</p>


<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="//www.youtube.com/embed/KZbMtYmM-2o" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>


<p>Yes, on September 22 at 12:30 UTC, I deliver the session <strong>ksqlDB - The Real Time Streaming Database</strong> at <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/"><strong>Data Platform Summit 2022</strong></a>.</p>

<p>The conference is free; you register <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/booking/">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 35, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/04/interesting-stuff---week-35-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-09-04T11:44:07+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/09/04/interesting-stuff---week-35-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/deep-learning-3.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Deep Learning</em></p></strong>
<strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/es/@pietrozj?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Pietro Jeng</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/deep-learning?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2022/08/microsoft-dev-box/">Microsoft Dev Box Now in Public Preview</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> post looks at the recent announcement of the public preview of Microsoft Dev Box, a workstation in the cloud targeted to developers. Integrated with Windows 365, the new service supports any developer IDE, SDK, or tool that runs on Windows and simplifies the onboarding of new developers.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/adx-web-explorer-updates-august-2022/ba-p/3613640">ADX Web Explorer updates – August 2022</a>. We all know that <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> is awesome! One of the cool things with ADX is its Web UI: <strong>ADX Web Explorer</strong>. The post linked to looks at what new (and enhanced features) there are in the August 2022 release of Web Explorer. The Funnel visual is one of the things I am excited about.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2022/challenges-and-practical-lessons-from-building-a-deep-learning-b">Challenges and practical lessons from building a deep-learning-based ads CTR prediction model</a>. In the ads business being able to predict click-through-rate is essential. This post describes how LinkedIn changed their previous CTR model for a deep-learning-based system, the challenges they experienced, and the lessons learned. Very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/using-ai-to-improve-your-literature-review-bb2d53348778">Using AI To Improve Your Literature Review</a>. When researching ML/AI topics, finding white papers/publications around the topics you are interested in is vital. However, the past twenty years have witnessed exponential growth in the number of published scientific papers, and it can be hard finding what you need with so many papers to &ldquo;trawl&rdquo; through. That&rsquo;s where what this post covers comes in. A research lab has released free software which allows you to write a query to search for papers you are interested in. The search functionality is backed by AI algorithms based on language models, such as GPT-3, and shows relevant papers to the query you wrote.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/what-is-kraft-and-how-do-you-use-it/">Getting Started with the KRaft Protocol</a>. The work to remove Apache Kafka&rsquo;s ZooKeeper dependency in favor of the KRaft (Apache Kafka Raft) protocol has been going on for a long time. It is not yet ready for use in production environments, but it is getting close. If you want to test it out, this post lists several key resources to help you learn everything you need about the ins and outs of KRaft.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 34, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/28/interesting-stuff---week-34-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-08-28T10:41:25+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/28/interesting-stuff---week-34-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/streaming-particles.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo Credit: <a href="https://www.istockphoto.com/portfolio/KBDS">KBDS</a> on <a href="https://www.istockphoto.com/">iStock</a></em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/azure-data-explorer-supports-native-ingestion-from-amazon-s3/ba-p/3606746">Azure Data Explorer supports native ingestion from Amazon S3</a>. The title of this post says it all. The post announces a new feature of <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>, the ability to ingest into ADX from Amazon S3.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/data-infrastructure/upsolver-simplifies-data-pipelines">Automating data pipelines: How Upsolver aims to reduce complexity</a>. Today, when you create a data pipeline, you most likely code the pipeline and its intricacies manually. The post linked to looks at, instead of coding data pipelines manually, how you can do it in a declarative way, handling transformations etc.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/streaming-first-real-time-ml">Streaming-First Infrastructure for Real-Time Machine Learning</a>. This article covers the benefits of streaming-first infrastructure for two scenarios of real-time ML. First is online prediction, where a model can receive a request and make predictions as soon as the request arrives. The second is continual learning when machine learning models can adapt to changes in production data distributions. Very, very cool! We have just now started looking at it at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/machine-learning-streaming-with-kafka-debezium-and-bentoml-c5f3996afe8f">Machine Learning Streaming with Kafka, Debezium, and BentoML</a>. This post looks at using modern data-related tools to integrate a Machine Learning model with a &ldquo;production&rdquo; database. This is so we can make real-time predictions as new records are added.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 33, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/21/interesting-stuff---week-33-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-08-21T12:37:51+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/21/interesting-stuff---week-33-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/benchmark.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Benchmark</p></strong>
<strong><p style="text-align: center;">Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/es/@manlyx?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Aliaksei Ramanouski</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/benchmark?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/blog/azure-data-explorer-log-and-telemetry-analytics-benchmark/">Azure Data Explorer: Log and telemetry analytics benchmark</a>. WOW - the numbers for <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> are pretty awesome! What I am talking about is this post that looks at benchmark numbers for <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>, Snowflake and Big Query. Since it is a Microsoft post, you&rsquo;d expect that ADX would come out looking quite good - but this good?!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/announcing-ga-launch-of-kafka-trigger-extension-on-azure/ba-p/3499015">Announcing GA launch of Kafka Trigger extension on Azure Functions</a>. The link here is from June; I am unsure if I have shared it before. Regardless, the post is worth sharing again, as it announces the release of Kafka triggers for Azure Serverless Functions. The Kafka trigger enables you to invoke functions in response to messages in Kafka topics and lets you write values/messages out to Kafka topics using an output binding. We have just started using it here at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> in a very cool project where we consume and publish to topics in Confluent Cloud.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/03/09/analytics-vs-transactions-api-data-streaming-with-apache-kafka/">Analytics vs. Transactions in Data Streaming with Apache Kafka</a>. When thinking of Kafka and data, one often sees Kafka used for analytical purposes of data. This post looks at using Kafka for transactional workloads in resilient, mission-critical architectures.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 32, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/14/interesting-stuff---week-32-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-08-14T09:09:45+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/14/interesting-stuff---week-32-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/streaming.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Streaming</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/ingesting-protobuf-data-from-kafka-to-azure-data-explorer/ba-p/3595793">Ingesting Protobuf data from Kafka to Azure Data Explorer</a>. As you know, I really like <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> and Kafka, and I have written a couple of posts about ADX and Kafka <a href="/2021/09/06/run-self-managed-kusto-kafka-connector-serverless-in-azure-container-instances/">here</a> and <a href="/2021/10/27/how-to-ingest-into-azure-data-explorer-from-apache-kafka-using-kafka-connect/">here</a>. In my posts, the data I ingested was JSON. This post looks at how to ingest Protobuf data from Kafka into ADX. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.databricks.com/blog/2022/08/09/low-latency-streaming-data-pipelines-with-delta-live-tables-and-apache-kafka.html">Low-latency Streaming Data Pipelines with Delta Live Tables and Apache Kafka</a>. Another Kafka-related post (you&rsquo;d almost think Kafka is popular). This post looks at building a fully managed low-latency data pipeline to ingest, cleanse, transform and improve the quality of streaming data from Apache Kafka with Delta Live Tables. We at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> are very interested in this!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-science-ai-ml">Data Science / AI / ML</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/microsoft/ai-for-beginners">Artificial Intelligence for Beginners - A Curriculum</a>. The link is to a GitHub repository containing an AI course for beginners, which was put together by Microsoft. It is free and consists of a 12-week, 24-lesson curriculum. This course introduces learners to a variety of AI concepts. It looks very, very interesting. At <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, we see AI/ML as the future, and our AI/ML champion <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nadia-fick-b533478/">Nadia</a> is looking at what we can do to incorporate this curriculum with what we are doing.</li>
<li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-synapseml-for-dotnet/">Announcing SynapseML for .NET – Large Scale ML with a Simple API</a>. SynapseML (the artist formerly known as MMLSpark) has been around for a while and is an open-source library to simplify the creation of scalable machine learning pipelines. Recently SynapseML v0.10 was released, and part of that release was a new set of .NET APIs. This post looks at those APIs and how you can build scalable and intelligent systems for solving challenges using these new APIs. Very, very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/stream-processing-ultimate-guide/">Getting Started with Stream Processing: The Ultimate Guide</a>. Regardless of your business, the ability to react in real-time has become increasingly important. We rely on streaming data to handle real-time data, and stream processing is critical to building real-time applications. This post looks at how ksqlDB can help your business create the types of applications that deliver rich, real-time customer experiences.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/serverless-stream-processing-with-apache-kafka-and-azure/">Serverless Stream Processing with Apache Kafka, Azure Functions, and ksqlDB</a>. We&rsquo;re continuing with the stream processing theme from above. This post looks at serverless stream processing. More specifically, serverless in Microsoft Azure. The post builds an application that integrates ksqlDB and Azure Functions, using the best functions of each to really lean into the strengths of both.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 31, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/07/interesting-stuff---week-31-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-08-07T09:39:14+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/08/07/interesting-stuff---week-31-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/deep-learning.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Deep Learning</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/use-fresh-and-unlimited-volume-of-adx-data-kusto-from-your/ba-p/3588894">Use fresh and unlimited volume of ADX data (Kusto) from your favorite analytic tool - Excel pivot</a>. For a while, Excel has had the ability to query data in <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> - yay! The slightly negative aspect of this was that typically data in ADX is counted in billions, and to query the data in Excel, you had to bring the data into Excel first - goodbye memory! The post linked to looks at a way to query ADX data in real-time without importing any data and without any volume limitations.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-science-machine-learning-ai">Data Science / Machine Learning / AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/6-papers-every-modern-data-scientist-must-read-1d0e708becd">6 Papers Every Modern Data Scientist Must Read</a>. This post brings up a point which is very dear to me - that to be on top of your chosen technologies, you need to understand the foundation and building blocks of said technologies. Anyway, the technology referred to in this post is deep learning, and the post lists white papers covering some of the most essential modern fundamentals of Deep Learning everyone in the field show be familiar with.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture-big-data">Data Architecture / Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://mrpaulandrew.com/2022/08/01/building-a-data-mesh-architecture-in-azure-part-13-how-to-organise-data-domains-in-practice/">Building a Data Mesh Architecture in Azure – Part 13 – How To Organise Data Domains In Practice</a>. This post is part of a series on how to build a Data Mesh on Azure. As the post&rsquo;s subtitle implies, this &ldquo;episode&rdquo; looks at data domains. Use <a href="https://mrpaulandrew.com/tag/data-mesh-vs-azure/">this link</a> if you are interested in reading more in this series. As a side note - there has been quite a debate (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:6919930275212726272/">link here</a>) around this implementation vs. the original data mesh &ldquo;principles&rdquo; as outlined by Zhamak Dehghani <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/data-mesh-principles.html">here</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.databricks.com/blog/2022/08/03/announcing-the-preview-of-serverless-compute-for-databricks-sql-on-azure-databricks.html">Announcing the Preview of Serverless Compute for Databricks SQL on Azure Databricks</a>. Databricks SQL is a serverless data warehouse on the Databricks Lakehouse Platform. It was initially previewed in late 2020, and this post announces the public preview on Azure. We at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> have been waiting for this!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/database-modernization-integrate-data-with-any-cloud/">Getting Started with Database Modernization</a>. Before you read the post linked to, I suggest you read <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/cloud-data-migrations-database-modernization-with-confluent/">Accelerate Cloud Database Modernizations and Migrations with Confluent</a>, which starts looking at the journey to easily migrate data to any cloud database for real-time data streaming, integration, and analytics. I suggest you read that post before this because this post builds on that one and looks at the steps you need to take to get started on your database modernization journey.</li>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/data-mesh-a-data-movement-and-processing-platform-netflix-1288bcab2873">Data Mesh — A Data Movement and Processing Platform @ Netflix</a>. Another post about Data Mesh, but in this case, the Data Mesh is not what we would think it is, i.e. what&rsquo;s mentioned above. Data Mesh is the Netflix Data Mesh, a fully managed streaming data pipeline product. The Data Mesh was introduced around a year ago. Since then, it has evolved, and this post is the first in a series covering different aspects of Data Mesh and lessons learned throughout the journey.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 30, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/31/interesting-stuff---week-30-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-31T08:02:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/31/interesting-stuff---week-30-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/chess-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Chess</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/2022/07/25/data-chess-game-databricks-vs-snowflake-part-1/">Data chess game: Databricks vs. Snowflake, part 1</a>. There is no doubt that Snowflake and Databricks compete in becoming the leading cloud data platform vendor. This post looks at these two vendors from different backgrounds (data lake and warehousing) and how they are now &ldquo;duking&rdquo; it out in the lakehouse.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/07/25/recap-of-databricks-lakehouse-platform-announcements-at-data-and-ai-summit-2022.htm">Recap of Databricks Lakehouse Platform Announcements at Data and AI Summit 2022</a>. The linked post summarises the major Databricks Lakehouse Platform innovations and contributions to open source and data and AI projects announced at the Data and AI Summit 2022.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Scalable-Data-Analytics-Azure-Explorer/dp/1801078548">Scalable Data Analytics with Azure Data Explorer: Modern ways to query, analyze, and perform real-time data analysis on large volumes of data</a>. A while ago, I was asked to do an editorial review of a book about <strong>Azure data Explorer</strong>. Well, the link here is to that book. If you are into ADX, then this book is a must-read.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-ci-cd-with-github/">4 Must-Have Tests for Your Apache Kafka CI/CD with GitHub Actions</a>. This post looks at applying GitOps principles to the development lifecycle of a Kafka client application using GitHub Actions: for testing locally and in Confluent Cloud, with and without Schema Registry, and for schema evolution.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/07/28/the-heart-of-the-data-mesh-beats-real-time-with-apache-kafka/">The Heart of the Data Mesh Beats Real-Time with Apache Kafka</a>. We all have heard about the &ldquo;data mesh&rdquo; by now. A requirement of the data mesh infrastructure is that it is real-time, reliable, and scalable. This post explores how Apache Kafka, as an open and scalable decentralized real-time platform, can be the basis of a data mesh infrastructure and – complemented by many other data platforms like a data warehouse, data lake, and lakehouse – solve real business problems.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 29, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/24/interesting-stuff---week-29-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-24T11:50:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/24/interesting-stuff---week-29-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/dps-2022.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Conference</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://rmoff.net/2022/07/20/how-to-write-a-good-tech-conference-abstract-learn-from-the-mistakes-of-others/">How to Write a Good Tech Conference Abstract - Learn from the Mistakes of Others</a>. I guess the title says it all. Things to think about when writing conference abstracts. This post by <a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a> is very valuable, but it should have come somewhat earlier. Why - you ask? Well, the conference &ldquo;season&rdquo; is upon us, and I have submitted quite a few abstracts. Unfortunately, the majority have been rejected. Maybe the result would have been better following the advice in this post. Anyway, rejections are part of the game - onwards and upwards!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/data-pre-processing-for-azure-data-explorer-with-apache-spark/ba-p/2727993">Data pre-processing for Azure Data Explorer with Apache Spark</a>. So, you want to load data into <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>. No problem, ADX has quite a few &ldquo;nifty&rdquo; ways to get the data into it. However, sometimes the data would need some complex data engineering upfront. Something that even ADXs powerful data-transformation capabilities cannot do. If that&rsquo;s the case, this post comes in handy. It looks at how to do it using PySpark and the notebook experience in Azure Synapse Analytics. Have Fun!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/2022/07/19/confluent-addresses-major-real-time-application-roadblocks-with-q3-update/">Confluent addresses major real-time application roadblocks with Q3 update</a>. This post looks at how Confluent partnered with Hashicorp to introduce a Terraform provider. The integration exposes Confluent cloud APIs for automated deployment and management of mission-critical data streaming resources. This is just the right time for us at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> as we are introducing Confluent Cloud right now!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/introducing-confluent-platform-7-2/">Introducing Confluent Platform 7.2: Enhanced Cloud-Native Security and Geo-Replication</a>. This post announces the release of Confluent Platform 7.2. The release covers three major areas: simplified cluster ops, improved data sharing, and improved stream processing capabilities via ksqlDB 0.26.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Above I was &ldquo;moaning&rdquo; about my abstracts being rejected. But, as you can see from the picture up top, &ldquo;all is not lost&rdquo;. I am presenting at <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/"><strong>Data Platform Summit 2022</strong></a>, and the session is <strong>ksqlDB - the Real-Time Streaming Database</strong>. So, right now I am prepping for the presentation!</p>

<p>Data Platform Summit is an awesome conference, it is this year as well virtual. So no traveling needed, hurry up and sign up <a href="https://dataplatformgeeks.com/dps2022/booking/">here</a>. Its is <strong>FREE</strong>!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 28, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/17/interesting-stuff---week-28-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-17T12:50:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/17/interesting-stuff---week-28-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/risk-management.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;"><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@cdc?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">CDC</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/%22risk-management%22?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a>
  </em></p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://whitepages.tygraph.com/2022/07/continuous-export-for-azure-application-insights-using-azure-data-explorer-kusto/">Continuous export for Azure Application Insights using Azure Data Explorer (Kusto)</a>. If you &ldquo;live in Azure-land&rdquo;, you probably use Application Insights to collect data for analysis. The analysis in App Insight is based on the Kusto engine but does not have all bells and whistles. To do more advanced analytics of your App Insights data, you should export your data to <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> (ADX). This post discusses a pattern for continuously streaming data from Application Insights data to ADX.</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-explorer/flow-usage">Usage examples for Azure Data Explorer connector to Power Automate</a>. I love <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> (heh- who would have thunk), but there is some &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; that frustrates me. Among them is that it is hard (neigh impossible) to do things based on scheduled tasks, triggers, etc. Well, neigh impossible until you read this Microsoft doc. This document looks at how to &ldquo;hook up&rdquo; <a href="https://powerautomate.microsoft.com/">Microsoft Power Automate</a> to ADX, and it also includes several typical Power Automate connector usage examples. Very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLwyttaal5U3r9jnHSaGT75sRqSfNDrX11">Azure Data Explorer L300 Workshop</a>. A couple of weeks ago, the Azure Data Explorer PM (Program Manager) team held a workshop spread over three days (around 2 - 3 hours per day). The workshop covered <strong>a lot</strong>, and the good thing was that it was recorded. The link here is to the YouTube playlist of the workshop. If you are interested in ADX, you <strong>must</strong> have a look!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/07/14/using-spark-structured-streaming-to-scale-your-analytics.html">Using Spark Structured Streaming to Scale Your Analytics</a>. This post looks at how a Databricks customer leverages Structured Streaming and the Databricks Lakehouse Platform to scale its analytics and keep its data products up to date.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/share-find-understand-data-streams-stream-catalog/">How to Find, Share, and Understand Your Data Streams with Stream Catalog</a>. If you want to get the most out of your data, it is vital to be able to discover, understand, organize and reuse your data. These requirements have led to the notion of a data catalogue. The post linked to looks at the Confluent Stream Catalog, what it is and what you can do with it.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/ml-prediction-on-streaming-data-using-kafka-streams-1e4ebd21008">ML Prediction on Streaming Data Using Kafka Streams</a>. This post looks at how you can boost the performance of your Python-trained ML models by serving them over a Kafka streaming platform in a Scala application.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/risk-management-with-confluent-databricks-data-streaming-analytics/">How streaming data and a lakehouse paradigm can help manage risk in volatile trading markets</a>. In financial markets, managing risk is a must. It is the key to success if you can do it well. The post linked to, looks at how you can ingest and process large amounts of raw data to compute real-time portfolio valuations, risk metrics, and more using integrated technology from Confluent and Databricks. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 27, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/10/interesting-stuff---week-27-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-10T09:58:43+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/10/interesting-stuff---week-27-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/mvp-renewal-2022-2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">MVP Renewal</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture-big-data">Data Architecture / Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/from-data-warehouse-to-data-lake-to-data-lakehouse-44ca03e0d624">From Data Warehouse to Data Lake to Data Lakehouse</a>. As the title implies, this post looks at Data Warehouses, Data Lakes and Data Lakehouses. It starts with an overview of the different Data Store technologies to see the whole picture and to understand what has changed and what has not. The post then looks at what&rsquo;s for what, what you need, and the advantages and limitations of Data Warehouses, Data Lakes, and Data Lakehouses. Oh, and as a part of the post, the author builds a Data Lakehouse. Very cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/30/open-sourcing-all-of-delta-lake.html">Open Sourcing All of Delta Lake</a>. So, as the title says, Databricks Delta Lake has now been fully open-sourced. This post looks at the reasoning behind it and what it means for the data community going forward.</li>
<li><a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/the-data-engineering-pipeline-6f7a306fcfdc">The Data Engineering Pipeline</a>. Data Engineers are at the heart of the engine room of any data-driven company. In this post, the author provides a high-level overview of the Data Engineering Pipeline, including best practices and tools to help drive data-driven organizations.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/aviation-flight-data-analytics-azure-synapse-platform-debananda-ghosh/">Aviation flight data analytics with Azure Synapse platform</a>. This post looks at flight data analytics use cases specific to the aviation industry. The interesting thing for me here is the usage of Synapse Data Explorer, the &ldquo;brother&rdquo; of <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>. It is fascinating to see how much &ldquo;cool stuff&rdquo; can be done with a powerful analytics engine - Synapse Data Explorer - and the query language Kusto!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/07/05/data-streaming-for-data-ingestion-into-data-warehouse-and-data-lake/">Data Streaming for Data Ingestion into the Data Warehouse and Data Lake</a>. This post is the second in a series exploring concepts, features, and trade-offs of a modern data stack using a data warehouse, data lake, and data streaming together. You find the first part <a href="https://www.kai-waehner.de/blog/2022/06/27/data-warehouse-vs-data-lake-vs-data-streaming-friends-enemies-frenemies/">here</a>. In this post, the author looks at how data streaming technologies are a perfect fit for data ingestion into data warehouses, data lakes, etc. This post came at the precisely right time as we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> are looking at this (ingestion into data lakes) now.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In the beginning of July MVP&rsquo;s around the world are on tenterhooks, as it is MVP renewal time: &ldquo;will I be an MVP for another year?&rdquo;. After the &ldquo;judgement&rdquo; you then see the LinkedIn feed be flooded by MVP&rsquo;s posts how happy they are that have been renewed. Last year was a bit silly seeing all the posts, since everyone was renewed automatically, and we knew about it beforehand.</p>

<p>With all that said, as you can see from the pictures at the top, I was renewed! Yay!!</p>

<p>At the same time of renewal, but entirely independent, I received this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/mvp-swag-2022-1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>MVP SWAG</em></p>

<p>Yup, MVP SWAG: hoodie, coffee cup and a Thank You card! Very cool, THANK YOU, Microsoft and the MVP Program!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 26, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/03/interesting-stuff---week-26-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-07-03T10:03:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/07/03/interesting-stuff---week-26-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/data-vault.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Data Vault</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2022/06/30/introducing-the-sql-server-2022-blog-series/">Microsoft SQL Server Blog</a>. If you follow what happens in the database world, you probably know that Microsoft SQL Server 2022 is now in Public Preview. This version of SQL Server promises to be a pretty impressive release, so I suggest two things: <a href="https://info.microsoft.com/ww-landing-sql-server-2022.html">download the preview</a> and test it out, and bookmark the SQL Server 2022 Blogging Series page in the linked post to follow along and see future blog posts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.playfab.com/blog/take-advantage-of-azure-data-explorer-with-playfab-data-connections">Take advantage of Azure Data Explorer with Playfab data connections</a>. PlayFab is a complete backend platform for live games with managed game services, real-time analytics, and LiveOps, and you can read more about it <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/gaming/playfab/what-is-playfab">here</a>. This post announces how there is now an <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> connector for PlayFab. Based on what we are doing in <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, PlayFab sounds like something we really should look into, and having <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> connectors makes it even more so.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://venturebeat.com/2022/06/28/databricks-strikes-back/">Databricks strikes back</a>. Databricks held its <a href="https://databricks.com/dataaisummit/">Data+AI Summit 2022</a> last week (June 27 - 30). The post linked to was published the same day as the Summit started, and it looks at the full range of announcements during the conference (yes, the author of the post was pre-briefed by Databricks). Some very cool &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; there!</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/24/prescriptive-guidance-for-implementing-a-data-vault-model-on-the-databricks-lakehouse-platform.html">Prescriptive Guidance for Implementing a Data Vault Model on the Databricks Lakehouse Platform</a>. Another Databricks-related post, this one by Databricks themselves. The post discusses Data Vault&rsquo;s and how to implement them within the Bronze/Silver/Gold layer. It also looks at how to get the best performance of Data Vault with Databricks Lakehouse Platform.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@robgolder/kafka-streams-state-store-30110bf4f24">Kafka Streams: State Store</a>. Kafka Streams stateful processing enables grouping related events that arrive at different times. Operations such as joins, reduce, counts, and aggregations can then be performed on them. That is all well and good, but the previously mentioned functionality would require state to be stored. This post dives into how state is stored in KStreams, and I found it very informative!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/26/interesting-stuff---week-25-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-26T09:33:06+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/26/interesting-stuff---week-25-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/microsoft-open-hack-2022-1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong><p style="text-align: center;">Microsoft Open Hack</p></strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-architecture">Data Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/24/data-warehousing-modeling-techniques-and-their-implementation-on-the-databricks-lakehouse-platform.html">Data Warehousing Modeling Techniques and Their Implementation on the Databricks Lakehouse Platform</a>. This post talks about the different data modelling techniques supported by the Databricks Lakehouse Platform and how each fits within each layer of the Bronze, Silver, and Gold architecture. For me, this post is very timely as we are right now implementing a Data Lakehouse here at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/wix-engineering/migrating-to-a-multi-cluster-managed-kafka-with-0-downtime-b936655f888e">Migrating to a Multi-Cluster Managed Kafka with 0 Downtime</a>. This post discusses how they at <a href="https://www.wix.com/">Wix</a> migrated 2000 microservices from on-prem Kafka clusters to Confluent Cloud. The post looks at critical design decisions and best practices for this type of migration.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/apps-on-azure-blog/announcing-ga-launch-of-kafka-trigger-extension-on-azure/ba-p/3499015">Announcing GA launch of Kafka Trigger extension on Azure Functions</a>. As the title implies, this post announces the GA release of Kafka triggers. Kafka triggers enable you to invoke functions in response to messages in Kafka topics and let you write values/messages out to Kafka topics using an output binding. Very, very cool, and this comes at the right time for a project we are starting at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/data-pipeline-principles-use-cases-examples/">Applying Data Pipeline Principles in Practice: Exploring the Kafka Summit Keynote Demo</a>. The Kafka Summit 2022 key-note demo showed how a fictional airline company merges with another airline company and wants a data pipeline built on Confluent to enable analytical and operational workstreams. This blog post deconstructs the demo through excerpts of real code used to create it. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>By now, you probably wonder what the picture at the top has to do with anything. So last week, Microsoft ran an <a href="https://openhack.microsoft.com/">OpenHack</a> here at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>. The topic of the OpenHack was <strong>Modern Data Warehousing</strong>, covering Azure Data Lake Storage, Azure Databricks, Azure Synapse Analytics and other cool stuff. Anyway, the OpenHack ran for three days, and on the last day, Microsoft had an event in our canteen where Derivco&rsquo;s employees had the chance to talk to various people from Microsoft.</p>

<p>Part of this event was the &ldquo;selfie booth&rdquo;, and in the picture, you see me sitting beside <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lee-anne-james-96514023/">Lee-Anne James</a>, who is our contact at Microsoft for all Data and AI. I cannot express enough how awesome she is. She really goes all out for us! Thanks, Lee-Anne!</p>

<p>So I mentioned the &ldquo;selfie booth&rdquo;, and part of the deal was that if you took a selfie and published it on your blog, Twitter, LinkedIn, etc., you got some swag:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/synapse-2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Azure Synapse Analytics Swag</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 1</em> you see the swag I managed to score - not bad!</p>

<p>Oh, I also managed to publish a blog post around some &ldquo;weird&rdquo; Git errors:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/06/25/solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-some-repo-is-owned-by-someone-else/">Solution to GIT: &ldquo;unsafe repository (&lsquo;some-repo&rsquo; is owned by someone else)&rdquo;</a>. I recently re-formatted my PC, and after everything was installed again, I got a &ldquo;weird&rdquo; error when I tried to do a <code>git pull</code>. The post looks at why I got the error and how to fix it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>

<p>2022-06-25-solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-somerepo-is-owned-by-someone-else.md</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solution to GIT: &#34;unsafe repository (&#39;some-repo&#39; is owned by someone else)&#34;
]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/25/solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-some-repo-is-owned-by-someone-else/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-25T19:16:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/25/solution-to-git-unsafe-repository-some-repo-is-owned-by-someone-else/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/git.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Git</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@synkevych?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Roman Synkevych 🇺🇦</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/git-repository?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Every 6 - 9 months (or so), I clean up my development PC just to keep it &ldquo;lean and mean&rdquo;. I do it by formatting the hard-drive partition the OS (in this case, Windows) is on, followed by a new install. Recently I had a four-day weekend here in SA. Four glorious days off, a perfect time to &ldquo;nuke&rdquo; my PC and re-install!</p>

<p></p>

<p>Off I go, everything goes to plan (<a href="https://community.chocolatey.org/">Chocolatey</a> is my friend), and after a while, I am done (or as done as one can be). At this stage, I needed to do my <a href="/2022/06/19/interesting-stuff---week-24-2022/">weekly roundup blog post</a> for the week gone by, and as I had done some changes to the GitHub repo from my <strong>MacBook Pro</strong>, I wanted to do a <code>git pull</code> in the repo directory for my blog. Part of the story is that on my dev PC, I have all my repos on a separate partition from the system partition, so the non-system partition was un-affected by the reformat (or so I thought). Imagine my surprise when doing the <code>git pull</code> I got:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/git-unsafe-repo-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Unsafe Repository</em></p>

<p>Hmm, the error we see in <em>Figure 1</em> does not make any sense at all. It is my repo, I created it, so what is the problem?</p>

<h2 id="the-problem">The Problem</h2>

<p>Trying to narrow down the issue, I did a <code>git clone</code> into a new directory of the same repo I couldn&rsquo;t <code>pull</code>, which worked perfectly! I went over to my MacBook and did a <code>pull</code> against the same repo that failed previously, and that worked as well. By now, I was utterly dumbfounded, so I started to do proper research (read Googled), and I came across <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/71901632/fatal-error-unsafe-repository-home-repon-is-owned-by-someone-else/71949648#71949648">this post</a>, which talked about security vulnerabilities in the Git client, and how they had been fixed in version <code>2.35.2</code>. When I checked my version, it was <code>2.36.1</code>, so I might be on to something here.</p>

<p>When reading about the security vulnerability in the link above, I came across this:</p>

<p><em>This version changes Git&rsquo;s behavior when looking for a top-level <code>.git</code> directory to stop when its directory traversal changes ownership from the current user.</em></p>

<p>Hmm, ownership and current user, let&rsquo;s look at the directory where the <code>pull</code> failed:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/git-unsafe-repo-owner-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2:</strong> <em>Directory Ownership</em></p>

<p>When looking at the advanced security settings for the directory, I saw something like in <em>Figure 2</em>, a &ldquo;weird&rdquo; looking owner of the directory. Actually, it is not that weird; it is a security identifier (<code>SID</code>). A <code>SID</code> in the Windows OS identifies a user, user group, or other security principal.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> To get to the advanced security settings, I right-clicked on the directory, chose <strong>Properties</strong>, clicked on the <strong>Security</strong> tab, and in the <strong>Security</strong> tab, I clicked the <strong>Advanced</strong> button.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From what we see in <em>Figure 2</em>, it is evident that the directory owner is not the same as the current user, i.e. me. Before we look at ways to fix the issue, let&rsquo;s understand why the owner is not myself. I created the directory at one point, so the owner should be me.</p>

<p>The answer is that the directory sits on a different partition/hard drive. When I reformatted the machine, the ownership was transferred to the particular <code>SID</code> since I was not &ldquo;around&rdquo;.</p>

<p>So now we know the reason and why it happened; let&rsquo;s fix it.</p>

<h2 id="fix-the-issue">Fix the Issue</h2>

<p>The obvious way to fix the problem is to change the directory owner to me. This can be done in the <strong>Advanced Security Settings</strong> we saw before:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/git-unsafe-repo-change-owner.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 3:</strong> <em>Change Owner</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 3</em>, we see how it is done. I clicked the <strong>Change</strong> button (outlined in blue), which brought up the <em>Select User or Group</em> dialog. I entered my user name in the textbox (outlined in red) and then clicked <strong>OK</strong>. I am now back to being the directory owner, and when doing a <code>git pull</code>, everything works!</p>

<p>This is one way to change the owner. The problem with this is that if you have quite a few repo directories under a &ldquo;root&rdquo; directory (as I do), then it can become a bit tedious to do it: right-click directory, <strong>Properties</strong>, <strong>Security</strong>, <strong>Advanced</strong>, <strong>Change</strong> - for each directory. It would be cool if one could do something more batch-like.</p>

<p>On Windows, we have a pretty neat tool that allows taking ownership of a file or folder using the command-line interface. The tool is <code>takeown.exe</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">$ takeown /f . /r /d Y
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Code Snippet 1:</strong> <em>Take Ownership</em></p>

<p>In <em>Code Snippet 1</em>, we see how I am in the root directory of my Git repos and how I call <code>takeown</code>. The parameters are:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>/f</code>: the directory or file to take ownership of. We see how I have defined <code>/f .</code>, (dot), which indicates the current directory.</li>
<li><code>/r</code>: performs a recursive operation on all files in the specified directory and subdirectories.</li>
<li><code>/d</code>: suppresses the confirmation prompt that is displayed when the current user does not have the <code>List Folder</code> permission on a specified directory and instead uses the specified default value. In my case, I used <code>Y</code>, which indicates to take ownership.</li>
</ul>

<p>Be aware that the above recurses through all directories and files, so it may take a while.</p>

<p>Another way to solve the issue, which does not involve changing ownership, is to tell Git that the directory is safe. To mark a directory safe, you use the <code>git config --global --add safe.directory &lt;option&gt;</code> command. The <code>option</code> can be a path to a directory or <code>*</code>, wherein Git treats any directory as safe.</p>

<p>When running <code>git config --global --add safe.directory</code>, the end result is that a <code>[safe]</code> section is being added to the <code>~/.gitconfig file</code>, and the section indicates what is safe:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">[user]
  email = niels.it.berglund@gmail.com
  name = Niels Berglund
[safe]
  directory = *
</code></pre>

<p>*<em>Code Snippet 2:</em> <em>Git Config File</em></p>

<p>In <em>Code Snippet 2</em> we see my <code>~/.config</code> file after I executed <code>git config --global --add safe.directory *</code>.</p>

<p>Remember that if you add a specific directory as <code>safe</code>, any changes to the directory name or path will cause the error to re-occur. However, if you add all directories as safe (or change ownership), you do not need to worry about name or path changes. It will just work.</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>This post looked at what causes the <em>unsafe repository (&lsquo;some-repo&rsquo; is owned by someone else)</em> Git error. We said that this error occurs when you run a Git client with a version of <code>2.35.2</code> or higher and execute a Git command in a directory owned by someone else than the user executing the command.</p>

<p>The way to solve this is to either change the ownership of the directory/directories or mark them as safe.</p>

<p>Having re-installed Windows, it is now time to do my <strong>MacBook Pro</strong> as well. Wish me luck!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>If you have comments, questions etc., please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 24, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/19/interesting-stuff---week-24-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-19T13:40:48+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/19/interesting-stuff---week-24-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/performance.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Performance</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@toddquackenbush?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Todd Quackenbush</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/performance?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/202x/2022/06/10/Quamina-Optimizing">Making Code Faster</a>. This post is a continuation of the post <a href="https://github.com/timbray/quamina">here</a>, which I covered in the roundup for <a href="/2022/05/15/interesting-stuff---week-19-2022/">week 19, 2022</a>. The post discusses various approaches to performance testing of your code. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning-ai">Machine Learning/AI</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://gradientflow.com/distributed-computing-for-ai-a-status-report/">Distributed Computing for AI: A Status Report</a>. The post linked to looks at what role distributed computing plays in AI. The consensus is that it becomes more and more essential to understand distributed computing in AI projects. Also, when hiring for AI, you often compete with &ldquo;pure&rdquo; distributed computing roles.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2022/06/15/recapping-recent-updates-to-client-tools-in-sql-server/">Recapping recent updates to client tools in SQL Server</a>. It has been a while since I have covered tools for SQL Server. Let me rectify that with this link. As the title implies, this post looks at SQL Server tools. What caught my eye was the notebook enhancements in <strong>Azure Data Studio</strong> and the containerization of Azure SQL Database! Cool stuff!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/5-ways-which-adx-can-provide-leading-edge-your-data-platform-dixit/">5 Ways in which ADX can provide a leading edge to your Data Platform</a>. I am pretty &ldquo;fond&rdquo; of <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong> as you know if you read my blog. I particularly like the super-fast ingestion and querying and the ability to do real-time analysis! However, there are other advantages of ADX, and the post I have linked to looks at 5 of those.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/cloud-incident-management-at-confluent/">How Confluent Treats Incidents in the Cloud</a>. Since we at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> looks at using Confluent Cloud, this post came in real handy. As the title says, the post looks at Confluent Cloud incidents and how they are handled. Very informative!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/12/interesting-stuff---week-23-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-12T15:27:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/12/interesting-stuff---week-23-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/snowflake.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Snowflake</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@mharrisonphotography?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Megs Harrison</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data">Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2022/06/new-intelligent-data-platform/">A New Microsoft Platform in Town: the Microsoft Intelligent Data Platform</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> post looks at the recently introduced Microsoft Intelligent Data Platform. This new platform fully integrates Microsoft&rsquo;s database, analytics, and governance offerings. It encompasses everything already available in the Azure Data space (Azure Data Factory, Azure Data Explorer, etc.) to the Synapse Analytics products, Power BI, and the newly rebranded Purview data governance service.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/06/08/announcing-the-availability-of-data-lineage-with-unity-catalog.html">Announcing the Availability of Data Lineage With Unity Catalog</a>. This post talks about the Databricks Data Lineage offering using the Unity Catalog. It looks at how the Unity Catalog provides automated and real-time data lineage at a granular level for all workloads (SQL, R, Python, Scala) and across all asset types (notebooks, workflows, dashboards). Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/shippeo-tech-blog/debezium-to-snowflake-lessons-learned-building-data-replication-in-production-a5430a9fe85b">Debezium to Snowflake: Lessons learned building data replication in production</a>. This blog looks at lessons learned when using Debezium to replicate data at scale in near real-time to Snowflake. There are some very useful tidbits in the post, even though we don&rsquo;t use Snowflake at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/elastically-scale-apache-kafka-clusters-in-confluent-cloud/">How to Elastically Scale Apache Kafka Clusters on Confluent Cloud</a>. In last week&rsquo;s <a href="/2022/06/05/interesting-stuff---week-22-2022/">roundup</a>, I mentioned Confluent Cloud&rsquo;s elasticity compared with on-prem Kafka, and we saw how much better it was in Confluent Cloud. The post here covers how we can easily resize a Confluent Cloud cluster and how it works internally. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 22, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/05/interesting-stuff---week-22-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-06-05T09:58:38+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/06/05/interesting-stuff---week-22-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/vector.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Vector</strong></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="databases">Databases</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/geekculture/vector-databases-taking-data-revolution-to-the-next-level-4a0faa437b2c">Vector Databases: Taking Data Revolution to The Next Level</a>. We know about SQL and no-SQL databases and how they are used, and that they are used for structured and semi-structured data. However, we now see more unstructured data, and the question is how we can deal with (search, etc.) this data. Dealing with unstructured data is where vector databases can help. This post looks at vector databases, how they can help us manage unstructured data, and the solutions they offer.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/azure-data-explorer-in-60-minutes-with-the-new-samples-gallery/ba-p/3447552">Azure Data Explorer in 60 minutes with the new samples gallery</a>. The post linked to announces the new Azure Data Explorer samples gallery feature. This feature provides an easy way to upskill and demo Azure Data Explorer with an end-to-end experience on a free, publicly available cluster. If you haven&rsquo;t looked at Azure Data Explorer yet, now it&rsquo;s time to do it.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/implementing-and-optimizing-bounding-box-queries-in-azure-data/ba-p/3416786">Implementing and Optimizing Bounding Box Queries in Azure Data Explorer</a>. This post looks at how we can in Azure Data Explorer create a function that would return objects - in this case vehicles - that are within a given bounding box in a given time period. This is quite a cool usage of bounding boxes!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/10x-apache-kafka-elasticity/">Making Confluent Cloud 10x More Elastic Than Apache Kafka</a>. Elasticity is the cornerstone of cloud-native computing. This post looks at how Confluent took Apache Kafka&rsquo;s horizontal scalability to the next level—in fact, they took it up multiple levels—and made Confluent Cloud 10x more elastic! Quite interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 21, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/29/interesting-stuff---week-21-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-29T13:13:28+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/29/interesting-stuff---week-21-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/snake.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>anaConda</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@sharonmccutcheon?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Sharon McCutcheon</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/how-to-manage-conda-environments-on-an-apple-silicon-m1-mac-1e29cb3bad12">How to Manage Conda Environments on an Apple Silicon M1 Mac</a>. As I mentioned in a <a href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/04/03/interesting-stuff---week-13-2022/">previous roundup</a>, I have switched over to the &ldquo;dark side&rdquo; for my travel laptop - I did get myself a MacBook Pro. Coming from a Windows background setting it up and configuring it is sometimes a chore, so I tend to save links to blog posts/articles covering setup/configuration of a Mac. This link is such a post, and it looks at how to manage different Python environments using Conda.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.jamesserra.com/archive/2022/05/microsoft-build-event-announcements-4/">Microsoft Build event announcements</a>. Last week (May 24 - 26), Microsoft held its annual Build conference. Many interesting things were announced, and the post linked to looks at some of the data platform announcements. One &ldquo;biggie&rdquo; is that SQL Server 2022 has been released into Public Preview.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-explorer">Azure Data Explorer</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.jamesserra.com/archive/2022/05/microsoft-build-event-announcements-4/">Deleting individual records in a table</a>. You who read my blog probably know that I like <strong>Azure Data Explorer</strong>. You also may know that my background is SQL Server. I mention my SQL Server background because sometimes doing things in ADX is somewhat different from what you&rsquo;d do in SQL Server. An example of this is deleting records. That is what this post looks at. It covers deleting individual records from a table and how it works behind the scenes.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-data-explorer-blog/optimized-autoscale-predictive-planning/ba-p/3413543">Optimized autoscale – predictive planning</a>. Azure Data Explorer has supported autoscaling (out and in) for quite some time. The autoscaling has been reactive, i.e. the scaling is delayed and requires time to alleviate the pressure off the cluster. This post looks at predictive autoscaling. It was recently added, and it tracks main metrics and builds a usage pattern. This allows ADX to plan cluster scale out and scale in ahead of time to further improve cluster performance while reducing cost.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/messaging-on-azure-blog/benchmarking-azure-event-hubs-premium-for-kafka-and-amqp/ba-p/3377483">Benchmarking Azure Event Hubs Premium for Kafka and AMQP workloads</a>. Microsoft recently announced the general availability of Azure Event Hubs Premium. It is a new product tier meant to support high-end event streaming scenarios. This post benchmarks this new product tier against Kafka, and the numbers are quite interesting. It is probably worth having a look at Azure Event Hubs Premium.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-3-2-0-new-features-and-updates/">What&rsquo;s New in Apache Kafka 3.2.0</a>. The title of this post kind if gives it away. Yes, the post looks at some of the new and improved features in the 3.2 release of Apache Kafka. What is of particular interest to me is the new features in KStreams. I hope they will make way for new functionality in ksqlDB as well.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2022]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/22/interesting-stuff---week-20-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2022-05-22T10:40:58+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2022/05/22/interesting-stuff---week-20-2022/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/posts/warehouse.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Warehouse</strong> <em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@jezar?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Jezael Melgoza</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>

<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>AI/data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>data architecture</li>
<li>streaming</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/05/20/five-simple-steps-for-implementing-a-star-schema-in-databricks-with-delta-lake.html">Five Simple Steps for Implementing a Star Schema in Databricks With Delta Lake</a>. At <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, we are starting to implement Databricks and Delta Live tables. This post, looking at simple tips and tricks for getting the best performance from Delta Lake star schema databases used in data warehouses and data marts, comes therefore at the right time.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/05/19/how-i-built-a-streaming-analytics-app-with-sql-and-delta-live-tables.html">How I Built A Streaming Analytics App With SQL and Delta Live Tables</a>. In this post, the author describes how easy it is to build a production-ready streaming analytics application with Delta Live Tables and Databricks SQL.</li>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/05/17/build-scalable-real-time-applications-on-the-lakehouse-using-confluent-databricks-part-2.html">Build Scalable Real-time Applications on the Lakehouse Using Confluent &amp; Databricks, Part 2</a>. In this post, which is a continuation of <a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2022/01/13/confluent-streaming-for-databricks-build-scalable-real-time-applications-on-the-lakehouse.html">the post here</a>, you learn more about the Confluent Connector for Databricks, streamlining the creation of real-time apps in AWS for data analytics use cases. Even though the examples use AWS, you can easily do this in Azure as well.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. Please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me if you have ideas for what to cover.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

