<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Niels Berglund</title>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://nielsberglund.com"/>
  <updated>2020-06-21T09:18:32+02:00</updated>
  <id>https://nielsberglund.com/</id>
  <generator uri="http://gohugo.io/">Hugo</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/21/interesting-stuff---week-25-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-21T09:18:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/21/interesting-stuff---week-25-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/feature-toggles/">Feature Toggles: The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly</a>. An <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation where the presenter covers how to use feature toggles effectively, some of the horror stories and how to avoid them, and how to deal with them if they do occur.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ververica.com/blog/flink-for-online-machine-learning-and-real-time-processing-at-weibo">Flink for online Machine Learning and real-time processing at Weibo</a>. This post looks at the architecture of Weibo&rsquo;s Machine Learning platform and how they use Apache Flink to develop their real-time Machine Learning pipelines. I found this post very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="azure-data-studio">Azure Data Studio</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/sql-server/released-sql-server-assessment-extension-for-azure-data-studio/ba-p/1470603">SQL Server Assessment Extension for Azure Data Studio</a>. This is very cool! An extension to Azure Data Studio which provides a user interface for evaluating SQL Server instances and databases for best practices.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/guide-to-kafka-pricing-and-diy-open-source-costs/">The Cost of Apache Kafka: An Engineer’s Guide to Pricing Out DIY Operations</a>. This is a very interesting post, looking at costings of running Kafka. It definitely provides food for thought.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In last weeks roundup, I mentioned about the second <strong>The Azure Sketches, Architect Series</strong> webinar, and how we should run it on Wednesday, June 17. Well, that didn&rsquo;t happen so we run it this coming Tuesday, (June 23), instead. Sign up <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271102120/">here</a> if you are interested.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 24, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/14/interesting-stuff---week-24-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-14T09:27:04+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/14/interesting-stuff---week-24-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/apache-hudi-graduation/">Building a Large-scale Transactional Data Lake at Uber Using Apache Hudi</a>. Hudi, developed by Uber, is similar to <a href="https://databricks.com/product/delta-lake-on-databricks">Delta Lake</a> in that it enables ACID semantics, (plus more), on data lakes. This post describes Uber&rsquo;s journey to building, releasing, and optimizing Apache Hudi.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://muratbuffalo.blogspot.com/2020/06/learning-about-distributed-systems.html">Learning about distributed systems: where to start?</a>. This post by <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> looks at resources to really learn and understand distributed computing. I urge you to look and read the resources <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> lists!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/streaming-databases/">Databases and Stream Processing: A Future of Consolidation</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenter digs into why both stream processors and databases are necessary from a technical standpoint but also by exploring industry trends that make consolidation in the future far more likely. He examines how these trends map onto common approaches from active databases like MongoDB to streaming solutions like Flink, Kafka Streams or ksqlDB.</li>
<li><a href="https://events.confluent.io/usecasesandarchitecturesforapa">Use Cases and Architectures for Apache Kafka and Event Streaming in the Gaming Industry</a>. Do.Not.Miss.This! The link here is for the registration page for a Confluent event where <a href="https://twitter.com/KaiWaehner">Kai Wähner</a> looks at how Kafka and Confluent Cloud provides a scalable, reliable and efficient infrastructure to make gamers happy and gaming companies successful.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Lockdown, lockdown, lockdown! What I would not give to be able to go out and have dinner with good friends at a restaurant right now!</p>

<p>Apart from that, things are not that bad. I am still working on the follow-up to the <a href="/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/"><strong>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology</strong></a> post. The upcoming post looks at the architecture. So when will it be published you may ask - I have no idea!</p>

<p>On Wednesday, (June 17), I am co-hosting the second <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271102120/"><strong>The Azure Sketches, Architect Series</strong></a> webinar together with Gordon Beeming and Lawrance Reddy. We use a combination of traditional drawing &amp; sketching with actual solution building to help reinforce the thought process in building Azure solutions and all of the dependencies in between. If you are interested, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/271102120/">here</a> is the link for registration.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/07/interesting-stuff---week-23-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-06-07T09:57:23+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/06/07/interesting-stuff---week-23-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-sql-database/azure-sql-sessions-recap-at-microsoft-build-2020/ba-p/1432139">Azure SQL Sessions Recap at Microsoft Build 2020</a>. This post contains links to all the various sessions around Azure SQL Server at this year&rsquo;s MS Build conference. Quite a few very interesting sessions!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-ensures-consistent-internal-state-reliability-recovery-using-kafka-transactions/">Consistent Metastore Recovery for ksqlDB Using Apache Kafka Transactions</a>. The post linked to here is a continuation of the post I covered in my <a href="/2020/05/03/interesting-stuff---week-18-2020/">week 18</a> roundup; about <a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/building-ksqldb-event-streaming-database/">ksqlDB Execution Plans</a>. This week&rsquo;s post discusses some of the work that’s gone into preserving the integrity of ksqlDB’s internal state in interactive mode.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/stream-processing-iot-data-best-practices-and-techniques/">Stream Processing with IoT Data: Challenges, Best Practices, and Techniques</a>. In this post, the author looks at Tesla&rsquo;s architecture and tech for handling IoT data. I found the post very interesting, and, even though at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> we do not deal with IoT data, we can definitely implement some of the principles outlined in the post.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/netflix-event-stream-flink/">Taming Large State: Lessons from Building Stream Processing</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenters talk about how Netflix solved a complex join of two high-volume event streams using Flink. They also discuss managing out of order events and processing late arriving data.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/fleet-management-gps-tracking-with-confluent-cloud-mongodb/">Real-Time Fleet Management Using Confluent Cloud and MongoDB</a>. The post linked to here looks at how to build a system incorporating ksqlDB, Kafka Connect, MongoDB, all in the cloud. The solution, in this case, is for fleet management, but it could be anything. Very cool!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>As I wrote in the <a href="/2020/05/31/interesting-stuff---week-22-2020/">roundup from last week</a>, lockdown restrictions here in SA have been relaxed, a bit. That means that you can now exercise whenever you want, instead of between 06:00 - 10:00 am; yay!, (that was sarcasm). For me, nothing has really changed, and I do not think I&rsquo;ll be back in the office until July/August.</p>

<p>In our <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/">Durban Azure Transformation Labs</a> user group, we had the first monthly News &amp; Catchup meeting. This meeting is virtual, and we get together the first Tuesday every month chatting about what has happened in the industry during the month just gone by. If you are interested in what was said, the recording of the event 10 is up on YouTube: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YxLQOaEnCqY">News &amp; Catch up June 2020</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 22, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/31/interesting-stuff---week-22-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-31T07:20:05+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/31/interesting-stuff---week-22-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2020/05/microsoft-build-2020-highlights/">Microsoft Build 2020: Highlights</a>. A couple of weeks ago Microsoft held its annual developer conference, Build. Due to the pandemic, it was a virtual 48 hour, around the clock conference, and it was free. The article linked to here is an <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article listing noteworthy &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; from the conference. As a side note: I wonder how much changes we will see in the conference landscape after when this pandemic is over. Will there be &ldquo;on-prem&rdquo; conferences any more, or will most conferences go virtual?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/apache-arrow-java">Apache Arrow and Java: Lightning Speed Big Data Transfer</a>. So Apache Arrow is a cross-language, cross-platform, columnar in-memory data format for data. The <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article linked to here introduces Apache Arrow and gets you acquainted with the basic concepts of the Apache Arrow Java library. If you&rsquo;re not a Java developer, don&rsquo;t worry - Apache Arrow offers libraries for many other languages as well: C, C++, C#, Go, to name a few.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://databricks.com/blog/2020/05/27/modernizing-risk-management-part-1-streaming-data-ingestion-rapid-model-development-and-monte-carlo-simulations-at-scale.html">Modernizing Risk Management Part 1: Streaming data-ingestion, rapid model development and Monte-Carlo Simulations at Scale</a>. This blog post demonstrates how to modernize traditional value-at-risk (VaR) calculation. It is demonstrated in the post, by using various components of the Databricks Unified Data Analytics Platform — Delta Lake, Apache SparkTM and MLflow. This enables a more agile and forward-looking approach to risk management.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/clickstream-data-and-analytics-with-confluent-ksqldb-kafka-connect/">Building a Clickstream Dashboard Application with ksqlDB and Elasticsearch</a>. This post shows an example of how you can build an event-driven application to help you unlock insights contained in the event streams of your business. As the title implies, Kafka, ksqlDB, and Elasticsearch are the components used. Very cool post!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/secure-kafka-deployment-best-practices/">Best Practices to Secure Your Apache Kafka Deployment</a>. So you are building your event streaming platform on Kafka - awesome! When you are ready to go live, your &ldquo;pesky&rdquo; security department asks you about security: &ldquo;how is the data that flows through Kafka secure, what have you done to prevent data breaches?&rdquo;. Trust me, they will ask you! Fear not, the post I link to here reviews five security categories and the essential features of Kafka and Confluent Platform that enable you to secure your event streaming platform. If you work with Kafka, <strong>READ</strong> the post!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CSyNiEgEyvY">Derivco Webinar - Kafka Masterclass</a>. As I mentioned in last weeks roundup, <a href="https://twitter.com/charllamprecht">Charl Lamprecht</a>, and I were going to do a <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> Webinar about Kafka: <strong>Conquer Your Data with Kafka and ksqlDB</strong>. Well, we did it, and the link here is to the uploaded YouTube video. Both <a href="https://twitter.com/charllamprecht">Charl</a> and I had a blast, and we believe the webinar was a success - peak attendance was at around 700 attendees</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Still lockdown! Apparently, some of the lockdown restrictions will be eased June 1, but I don&rsquo;t see me being back in the office for at least a month, most likely two.</p>

<p>As I mentioned above, I did the <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> Kafka <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CSyNiEgEyvY">webinar</a> last week together with <a href="https://twitter.com/charllamprecht">Charl</a>, and we had a great time.</p>

<p>I am still working on the follow-up to the <a href="/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/"><strong>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology</strong></a> post. The upcoming post looks at the architecture. So when will it be published you may ask? I have learnt from my mistakes, so at this stage, I have no idea.</p>

<p>Our local <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/">Azure Meetup group</a> has a virtual catchup on Tuesday, (June 1), where we discuss any news or anything interesting that came out in May 2020 in the industry. If you are interested, please register <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/270811782/?rv=ce1&amp;_xtd=gatlbWFpbF9jbGlja9oAJDA1NDZiYjMxLTUzZjAtNDQwOS05YmQ0LTIzMGEyYTg4NjEwZg&amp;_af=event&amp;_af_eid=270811782">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 21, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/24/interesting-stuff---week-21-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-24T06:51:36+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/24/interesting-stuff---week-21-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://muratbuffalo.blogspot.com/2020/05/slog-serializable-low-latency-geo.html">SLOG: serializable, low-latency, geo-replicated transactions</a>. In this blog post <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> dissects a white paper about how one can in a distributed system avoid the tradeoff of giving up one of serializability, low latency writes, or high transactional throughput. <a href="https://twitter.com/muratdemirbas">Murat</a> does a great job dissecting a complex topic and make it understandable.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/azure-data-studio/machine-learning-extension?view=sql-server-ver15">Machine Learning extension (preview) for Azure Data Studio</a>. The May 2020 release of Azure Data Studio was <a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/05/20/the-may-2020-release-of-azure-data-studio-is-now-available/">announced</a> a week or so ago, and in that release was an extension for Machine Learning. The link here is to the documentation of the extension. It looks interesting, and I&rsquo;ll try to take it for a &ldquo;spin&rdquo; as soon as I get time.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ververica.com/blog/how-godaddy-uses-flink-to-run-real-time-streaming-pipelines">How GoDaddy uses Flink to run real time streaming pipelines</a>. This post, as the title says, looks at data pipelines at GoDaddy, and how they use Apache Flink in conjunction with other tools to create and run those pipelines. What I found especially interesting in the post was the description of how they deployed a new pipeline into production. That is something I will copy and try to implement at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>On Tuesday, (May 26), I am co-hosting the first <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/270689806/"><strong>The Azure Sketches, Architect Series</strong></a> webinar together with Gordon Beeming and Lawrance Reddy. This series will use a combination of traditional drawing &amp; sketching with actual solution building to help reinforce the thought process in building Azure solutions and all of the dependencies in between. If you are interested, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Azure-Transformation-Labs/events/270689806/">here</a> is the link for registration.</p>

<p>Thursday, May 28, I do another first, the first-ever Derivco Webinar. <a href="https://twitter.com/charllamprecht">Charl Lamprecht</a>, who is Derivco&rsquo;s Kafka Guru, and I are delivering a webinar about Kafka and ksqlDB: <strong>Conquer Your Data with Kafka and ksqlDB</strong>. If you are interested, you can register <a href="https://derivco.co.za/derivco-webinar/">here</a>.</p>

<p>I hope to see you at either of these events!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/17/interesting-stuff---week-20-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-17T08:53:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/17/interesting-stuff---week-20-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://learn.particular.net/courses/adsd-online-free">Advanced Distributed Systems Design (Online Course)</a>. Udi Dahan is one of the world&rsquo;s foremost experts on Service-Oriented Architecture, Distributed Systems and Domain-Driven Design. Enrol for free and learn all about distributed systems design. Usually, this course costs $2,500, but now - due to the pandemic - it is free! Udi is an excellent instructor, and as one of my colleagues said: <em>as apposed to other so-called experts, there is none of this &ldquo;tear down, and build up&rdquo; bullsh%t.</em></li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2020/05/monolith-decomposition-newman">Decomposing a Monolith Does Not Require Microservices - Sam Newman at QCon London</a>. This is an <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article based on a presentation by Sam Newman at QCon in London, where he discussed breaking down monoliths.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/distributed-knowledge/paxos-consensus-for-beginners-1b8519d3360f">Paxos consensus for beginners</a>. The post here tries to explain Paxos. Paxos is a consensus algorithm, and most other consensus algorithms, such as Raft, ZAB, etc., are based on Paxos. So I said that the post tries to explain Paxos, and in my mind, the author succeeds!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/ebaytech/resiliency-and-disaster-recovery-with-kafka-dc8901c881c">Resiliency and Disaster Recovery with Kafka</a>. The post linked to here presents possible solutions for running a multi-region Kafka setup. I really liked the post as it gave some solutions to issues we have at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> right now.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/building-a-telegram-bot-powered-by-kafka-and-ksqldb/">Building a Telegram Bot Powered by Apache Kafka and ksqlDB</a>. This post does exactly what the title says: <a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a>, (Mr Kafka), shows us how to use Kafka and ksqlDB together to build an awesome app! Very cool usage of ksqlDB!</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/analytics-vidhya/learn-how-to-use-kafkacat-the-most-versatile-kafka-cli-client-d9cf398e5883">Learn how to use Kafkacat — the most versatile Kafka CLI client</a>. <code>kafkacat</code> is a command-line tool for producing and consuming Kafka messages, (and more), and in the post, the author talks us through how easy it is to use.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-9-0-feature-updates/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.9.0</a>. As the title says; the post announces ksqlDB 0.9, and looks at some new features. I am quite interested in the multi-join support! That will come in quite handy for <a href="/derivco">us</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/removing-zookeeper-dependency-in-kafka/">Apache Kafka Needs No Keeper: Removing the Apache ZooKeeper Dependency</a>. This post outlines the work done to remove the ZooKeeper dependency from Kafka.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Still in lock-down! It is now coming up to two months, and I do not see any end in sight. The only positive is that the restrictions on online commerce have been lifted, so I managed to get me a <a href="https://www.corsair.com/us/en/Categories/Products/Gaming-Keyboards/RGB-Mechanical-Gaming-Keyboards/K95-RGB-PLATINUM-XT-Mechanical-Gaming-Keyboard/p/CH-9127411-NA">Corsair K95 RGB PLATINUM XT</a> keyboard. I like it!</p>

<p>I wrote in one the <a href="/2020/04/26/interesting-stuff---week-17-2020/">Interesting Stuff - Week 17, 2020</a> post about how Microsoft has open-sourced the SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework, and I am working together with a couple of other MVPs and Microsoft developer on a .NET extension. Watch this space!</p>

<p>I am also working on the follow-up to the <a href="/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/">A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology</a> post. The upcoming post looks at the architecture. So when will it be published you may ask? I have learnt from my mistakes, so at this stage, I have no idea.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 19, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/10/interesting-stuff---week-19-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-10T10:16:08+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/10/interesting-stuff---week-19-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/05/07/announcing-mssql-cli-is-now-generally-available-on-macos-and-linux/">Announcing mssql-cli is now generally available on macOS and Linux</a>. <code>mssql-cli</code> is an open-source and cross-platform command-line tool to manage SQL Server on-prem and on the cloud. It has some cool features such as Intellisense and syntax highlighting. The blog post linked to here announces, among other things, the availability of <code>mssql-cli</code> on Linux and Mac. I have used it a bit, and it is quite awesome!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/maestral-solutions/high-five-with-net-5-cfea40e2c53a">High Five with .NET 5</a>. This post looks at the upcoming .NET 5 - the successor to .NET Core - and some of the features it brings.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="domain-driven-design">Domain Driven Design</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@chatuev/ddd-for-microservices-4778a363c071">DDD for microservices</a>. The post linked to here is the first post in a series where the author his experience adopting Domain-Driven Design and integrating it into the software development process. This particular post gives an introduction to DDD. I, for one, am looking forward to the upcoming posts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/swlh/data-lake-design-for-better-architecture-storage-security-data-governance-16d2a36721ba">Data Lake — Design For Better Architecture, Storage, Security &amp; Data Governance</a>. This post discusses architecture patterns to follow when designing and building data lakes. Keep your eyes open for follow-up posts looking at practical approaches.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/hadoop-distributed-file-system-b09946738555">Hadoop Distributed File System</a>. I found this post to be an excellent guide helping me understand a bit more about the Hadoop File System, (HDFS). Highly recommended!</li>
<li><a href="https://eng.uber.com/monitoring-data-quality-at-scale/">Monitoring Data Quality at Scale with Statistical Modeling</a>. If you base business decisions on data, you cannot have bad data. This post looks at how Uber monitors data quality by using statistical modelling. I found the post very interesting!</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/apache-yarn-zookeeper-61e17a958215">Apache YARN &amp; Zookeeper</a>. This post dives down into the components that help with resource allocation and high availability in Hadoop: YARN and Zookeeper.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-pull-queries-high-availability/">Highly Available, Fault-Tolerant Pull Queries in ksqlDB</a>. This, very informative, blog post looks at how ksqlDB pull queries can be highly available even during server failures.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@abhishek1987/using-docker-to-test-your-kafka-applications-3057770d736d">Using Docker to test your Kafka applications</a>. A very cool post looking at how one can use a Java library, <code>testcontainers-java</code>, to run integration tests for Kafka based applications.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@megachucky/is-apache-kafka-a-database-ddc310898f5c">Is Apache Kafka a Database?</a>. This is a thought-provoking article looking at if Kafka can be considered a database. My thoughts around that are - it depends. It depends on what functionality you expect a database to have. So, to me, I&rsquo;d say Kafka is close, really close, but I would like to see the ability to do range queries against some other field(s) than the <code>ROWKEY</code> field before I consider Kafka a database.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 18, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/03/interesting-stuff---week-18-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-05-03T11:50:01+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/05/03/interesting-stuff---week-18-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://mybuild.microsoft.com/">Microsoft Build</a>. The COVID-19 virus impacts everything, not least conferences, with many conferences canceled. Fortunately, some conferences go virtual, and Microsoft Build 2020 is one of them. The link here is to the registration for MS Build 2020, and it is free! Yes, you read that right - MS Build is free! I, for one, have already signed up. Hope to see you there!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-science">Data Science</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/2020/04/r-400-is-released.html">R 4.0.0 now available, and a look back at R&rsquo;s history</a>. From the title of the post, you get what it covers. <a href="https://twitter.com/revodavid">David</a> from [Revolution Analytics] looks at what is new in the recently released R 4.0, and he also takes a look back at the history of R.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/broadcom-uses-ksqldb-to-modernize-machine-learning-anomaly-detection/">Broadcom Modernizes Machine Learning and Anomaly Detection with ksqlDB</a>. The post linked to here is a very cool example of how we can use Kafka and ksqlDB together with Machine Learning for a lot of interesting topics (pun intended). In this particular case for anomaly detection.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ververica.com/blog/flink-forward-virtual-2020-recap">Flink Forward Virtual 2020 Recap</a>. Above I wrote about the upcoming MS Build virtual conference. The post here is a look at a virtual conference that already has taken place: the Flink Forward 2020 conference. The post has links to the session recordings as well as the slide decks. I have had a look, and there are a lot of interesting sessions.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/building-ksqldb-event-streaming-database/">ksqlDB Execution Plans: Move Fast But Don’t Break Things</a>. This post drills into how execution plans work in ksqlDB, and what challenges there are to maintain compatibility when releasing new ksqlDB features. Very interesting!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In previous roundups, I have written about the lock-down here in SA. Well, the lock-down was initially supposed to end mid-April, but it was extended to end of April. However, the lock-down is not over, as it has now moved from stage 5, to stage 4. That changes almost nothing, i.e. you are still supposed to stay at home. What has changed is that restaurants are allowed to deliver, so this Friday, (May 1), I had pizza for the first time in a month, yum!</p>

<p>The other thing that has changed being in stage 4 is that online businesses can sell, (and deliver), computer &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;. So right now I am waiting on a delivery of a new keyboard and mouse, so I am happy! The little things in life - eh?!</p>

<p>Finally, the first-ever SQL Server 2019 Virtual Symposium happens May 7 - 8. Don&rsquo;t miss the chance to hear the likes of <a href="https://twitter.com/bobwardms">Bob Ward</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/BuckWoodyMSFT">Buck Woody</a> present awesome stuff! I had hoped to present as well, but this time it was not to be. I will, however, attend, and I suggest you do likewise. The symposium is arranged by <a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/"><strong>DataPlatformGeeks</strong></a>, and you can register <a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/virtual-symposium-sql-server-2019-may-2020/">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 17, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/26/interesting-stuff---week-17-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-26T09:53:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/26/interesting-stuff---week-17-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="event-driven-architecture">Event Driven Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/why-your-microservices-architecture-needs-aggregates-342b16dd9b6d">Why Your Microservices Architecture Needs Aggregates</a>. In this post, the author looks at what aggregates are and how they can help in the long run. In essence, the author discusses the Aggregate Pattern, where an aggregate is a cluster of domain objects that can be treated as a single unit.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/bbc-distributed-monolith-microservices/">Beyond the Distributed Monolith: Rearchitecting the Big Data Platform</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenter talks about how BBC re-architected a distributed monolith, and how they designed their new microservices architecture. A very interesting presentation!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server-2019-extensibility-framework">SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/sqlserver/2020/04/22/open-sourcing-the-java-language-extension-for-sql-server/">Open sourcing the Java language extension for SQL Server</a>. If you follow my blog, you may be aware that I have been writing about the <a href="/s2k19_ext_framework_java">SQL Server Extensibility Framework, and the Java Language Extension</a>. The Java language extension has now been open-sourced, and the post linked to here discusses that. What this means is that anyone interested can now create a language extension for their favorite language! That.Is.So.Awesome!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster">SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/">A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology</a>. Finally! I finally managed to get this post out of me. The post is a blog version of a conference talk I do: <strong>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>. Initially, I thought I would get away with one post covering the talk, but I realised while writing the post that it requires a couple of more posts. So, this, the first, post looks at the background of the <strong>SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>, and the technology behind it.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.xeotek.com/kadeck/">KaDeck – Master your Apache Kafka blackbox</a>. This link here is to a Kafka tool which enables you to manage and connect securely to your Apache Kafka clusters, as well as monitor and manage your topics and create reports etc. It looks quite useful, I must say!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/webify-event-streams-using-kafka-connect-http-sink/">Webify Event Streams Using the Kafka Connect HTTP Sink Connector</a>. This post looks at how easy it is to push events from Kafka to web pages using the Kafka connector for HTTP.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/introducing-confluent-platform-5-5/">Introducing Confluent Platform 5.5</a>. Hot on the heels of the release of Apache Kafka 2.5 comes the release of Confluent Platform 5.5, The post linked to here looks at some of the new features in the 5.5 release.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me. Most importantly, stay safe out there!</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: Background &amp; Technology]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-26T06:49:39+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/26/a-lap-around-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-background--technology/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You who read my blog have probably noticed some posts around <strong>SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>, (BDC). You have also most likely seen me posting about giving conference talks and webinars around BDC.</p>

<p>One of the presentations I do around BDC is named &ldquo;A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster&rdquo;, and I thought it would be a good idea to make a blog post around the presentation. Well, as per usual for me, &ldquo;a blog post&rdquo; becomes multiple posts.</p>

<p>So, in this post, we look at the background to <strong>SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>, the technology behind it, and a little bit around monitoring the cluster. In future posts, we look at architecture, data virtualization and other interesting bits and pieces.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data">Data</h2>

<p>Before we &ldquo;drill into&rdquo; what a Big Data Cluster is, let us discuss why Microsoft felt the need for BDC. It all comes down to data:</p>

<p>We are getting more and more data, and to stay competitive, we need to be able to use that data; to integrate it, manage it and analyze it.</p>

<p>The problem is that the data comes in all shapes and types; relational data, NoSQL, files, etc., etc. So how do we integrate and analyze this data?</p>

<h4 id="sql-server">SQL Server</h4>

<p>I come back to the question about how to handle all this data shortly, but before that let us think about the evolution of SQL Server throughout the years.</p>

<p>From its &ldquo;humble beginnings&rdquo; as another flavor of Ashton Tate/Sybase, Microsoft evolved SQL Server throughout the years:</p>

<ul>
<li>SQL Server 7.0 - re-write of the codebase in C++, introducing: User Mode Scheduling, (UMS), and a multi-dimensional database called SQL OLAP Services.</li>
<li>SQL Server 2000 - OLAP Services became Analysis Services.</li>
<li>SQL Server 2005 - this was a massive release! Microsoft introduced, among other things, SQL Server Integration Services, the XML data type, SQL Server Service Broker, and my favorite: SQLCLR.</li>
<li>SQL Server 2016 - in this release Microsoft introduced SQL Server Machine Learning Services, (the ability to call R code from T-SQL). Microsoft also added PolyBase, which in this release allowed the creation of External Table(s) against Hadoop data.</li>
<li>SQL Server 2017 - Microsoft added Python in addition to R in SQL Server Machine Learning Services. Also - another biggie - for the first time: SQL Server on Linux, as well as containers!</li>
<li>SQL Server 2019 - Java is added in addition to R and Python, and it is introduced as SQL Server Extensibility Framework. Polybase is greatly enhanced, and we can now create external tables against relational databases, as well as MongoDB and CosmosDB, plus generic ODBC data sources.</li>
</ul>

<p>From the above, which is by no means complete, we see how Microsoft has evolved SQL Server to be not only an exceptional relational database but also an engine which can do many things related to data.</p>

<p>Coming back to what I asked above about how to integrate, manage and analyze all types of data, Microsoft sees SQL Server as the hub in all this, and the solution is <strong>SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</strong>.</p>

<p>The idea is that with SQL Server 2019 Big Data cluster we should be able to handle, (manage, integrate, analyze), not only relational data, but also other types of data, (Big Data), and extend SQL Server to store data in the petabyte range.</p>

<h2 id="sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster">SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</h2>

<p>So, from the above, we see that a BDC is not your usual SQL Server instance; it is an entirely different &ldquo;beast&rdquo;.</p>

<p>As the name implies, a BDC is a cluster of &ldquo;things&rdquo;. When you deploy the BDC, you deploy a scalable cluster of SQL Server, (multiple instances in fact), Hadoop File System, (HDFS), and Apache Spark. By having these components in the cluster, you can process and analyse massive amounts of data, not only relational data but big data as well.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> Oh how things have changed. From once at a time shying away from Open Source, Microsoft now embraces Open Source: Linux, Apache Spark, Hadoop File System!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A difference from a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; SQL Server installation is that the SQL Server instances in a BDC are SQL Server on Linux in containers. All components in a BDC run in containers, and since we now have multiple containers we need something that manages and orchestrates the containers and their workload. For this we use Kubernetes. So, when we deploy a BDC, we deploy into a Kubernetes cluster.</p>

<p>The type of Kubernetes cluster does not matter that much, it can be in the cloud, or on-prem. I always deploy to Azure, and the Azure Kubernetes Service, but as I said - it can essentially be any cluster.</p>

<h2 id="kubernetes">Kubernetes</h2>

<p>Kubernetes, (k8s), is an open-source container orchestration system for automating application deployment, scaling, and management. Kubernetes helps you with:</p>

<ul>
<li>Service discovery, load balancing.</li>
<li>Storage orchestration.</li>
<li>Automated rollouts and rollbacks.</li>
<li>Automated sharding.</li>
<li>more &hellip;</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> When I first started hearing about Kubernetes I wondered where the abbreviation &ldquo;k8s&rdquo; came from and what it means. I had various theories, each one &ldquo;weirder&rdquo; than the other. Well, the answer is that k is the first letter in the name, s is the last letter, and the 8 in between stands for the number of letters between k and s.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="kubernetes-basics">Kubernetes Basics</h4>

<p>A k8s cluster consists of:</p>

<ul>
<li>Node(s) - the actual servers the cluster runs on. They can be either bare metal or VM&rsquo;s.</li>
<li>Pod(s) - a Pod is a collection of containers, and a Pod exists on a Node.</li>
<li>Service - a Service defines a logical set of pods and a policy by which to access them. You access the cluster from the outside via exposed endpoints by the services.</li>
<li>Namespace - a virtual cluster of nodes.</li>
<li>Volume -  a directory that contains data accessible to containers in a given Pod. Since Pods and therefore containers come and go a Volume provides a mechanism to connect Pods/containers to persistent data stores elsewhere.</li>
<li>other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>

<p>Each k8s cluster has a master node, (sometimes also called the control plane). The master node runs a collection of processes which manages the cluster and its state. The master node also exposes the API layer which we interact with when managing the cluster.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> If you create a k8s cluster in Azure, (AKS), the master is abstracted away from you.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As mentioned above, the nodes contain your application&rsquo;s pods. The nodes contain, in addition to your pods, two k8s components:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>kubelet</code> - this is the k8s agent which processes the orchestration requests from the master node.</li>
<li><code>kube-proxy</code> - the proxy routes network traffic and manages IP addressing.</li>
</ul>

<p>Each node also contains a container runtime, which is the component that allows containerized applications to run:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kubernetes-1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 1:</strong> <em>Kubernetes</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 1</em> we see some of the parts of a two-node Kubernetes cluster, with a Master node. We see how the Master node communicates with the <code>kubelet</code> agent in the individual nodes, and how a developer/operational &ldquo;dude&rdquo; manages the cluster using a tool named <code>kubectl</code>, which we talk about more below. Each node has, in this example, two pods with two containers each, and the pods sit in the container runtime. The <code>kube-proxy</code> communicates with the pods, and a &ldquo;user&rdquo; connects to a pod via <code>kube-proxy</code>.</p>

<p>In k8s, we also have the notion of <code>StatefulSet</code>, which is a workload API used to manage stateful applications. It manages the deployment and scaling of a set of Pods and provides guarantees about the ordering and uniqueness of these Pods. This is important in the context of the BDC since we really want the BDC to have stateful services - think databases.</p>

<h4 id="managing-a-k8s-cluster">Managing a k8s Cluster</h4>

<p>Above I mentioned how the master node exposes an API layer which we interact with when managing the cluster.</p>

<p>**<code>kubectl</code></p>

<p>The way to manage a cluster is via a command-line tool - <code>kubectl</code> - which allows you to inspect cluster resources; create, delete, and update components; etc.</p>

<p>To illustrate the use of <code>kubectl</code> I have created a small k8s cluster in Azure. The cluster is named <code>kubernetes-test</code>, (imaginative - I know), and the first thing we need to do is to configure <code>kubectl</code> to connect to the cluster.</p>

<p>To configure <code>kubectl I use an Azure CLI command:</code>az aks get-credentials`, like so:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">az aks get-credentials --name kubernetes-test \
                       --resource-group rg-k8s-test \
                       --admin \
                       --overwrite-existing \
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Code Snippet 1:</strong> <em>Configure <code>kubectl</code></em></p>

<p>We see in <em>Code Snippet 1</em> how I pass in the name of the cluster and the resource group as parameters together with two optional parameters:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>admin</code> - gets cluster administrator credentials.</li>
<li><code>overwrite-existing</code> - overwrites any existing cluster entry with the same name.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> In the code snippet above I use <code>\</code> to denote line-break. If you run this in Powershell on Windows, you use backtick, (&rdquo;`&ldquo;), as a line-break symbol.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When I execute the code in <em>Code Snippet 1</em> I get:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-kubectl-cfg.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 2:</strong> <em>Configure <code>kubectl</code></em></p>

<p>The <code>config</code> file we see outlined in red in <em>Figure 2</em> holds, among other things, the keys for the Kubernetes cluster. To ensure that I can connect to the cluster, I call <code>kubectl get nodes</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-kubectl-nodes.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 3:</strong> <em>View Nodes</em></p>

<p>We see in <em>Figure 3</em> the result after executing <code>kubectl get nodes</code>, and how my k8s cluster has three nodes. If I were to execute something like <code>kubectl get pods</code> I would not get a result back as I have not deployed anything to the cluster yet.</p>

<p><strong>Kubernetes Dashboard</strong></p>

<p>You do not have to rely on <code>kubectl</code> solely for monitoring and managing a Kubernetes cluster, as you can also use the <a href="https://kubernetes.io/docs/tasks/access-application-cluster/web-ui-dashboard/">Kubernetes Dashboard</a>. In Azure you access the dashboard by the <code>az aks browse</code> command, and - as with <code>get-credentials</code> - you pass in the names of the resource group and cluster: <code>az aks browse --resource-group rg-k8s-test --name kubernetes-test</code>, and a new tab opens in your browser:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-k8s-dash-error.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 4:</strong> <em>Kubernetes Dashboard Errors</em></p>

<p>Hmm, what is this - the tab that opens up shows the dashboard as we see in <em>Figure 4</em>, but it is full of warnings!</p>

<p>The problem here is that on AKS Role Based Access Control, (RBAC), is enabled by default and the service account used by the dashboard does not have enough permissions to access all resources.</p>

<p>We fix that by running the following command:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">kubectl create clusterrolebinding kubernetes-dashboard -n kube-system \
              --clusterrole=cluster-admin \
              --serviceaccount=kube-system:kubernetes-dashboard
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Code Snippet 2:</strong> <em>Assign Permissions to Kubernetes Dashboard</em></p>

<p>After we execute the code in <em>Code Snippet 2</em> we can run the <code>az aks browse</code> command as per above, and now the dashboard comes up with no errors.</p>

<p>Further down in this post, I revisit the dashboard in the context of a SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster.</p>

<p>So that was a bit about Kubernetes. Admittedly this barely scratches the surface of k8s. If you are interested in knowing more about k8s I can recommend <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLLasX02E8BPCrIhFrc_ZiINhbRkYMKdPT">this YouTube playlist</a>, where <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brendan-burns-487aa590/">Brendan Burns</a>, co-creator of Kubernetes, drills down into k8s.</p>

<h2 id="deploying-bdc-to-kubernetes">Deploying BDC to Kubernetes</h2>

<p>So, we now know why we need the BDC, and we also know a bit about the platform the BDC runs on. Let us go on and look at how we install/deploy a BDC.</p>

<p>If you, like me, are a SQL Server guy, you are probably quite familiar with installing SQL Server instances by mounting an ISO file, and running setup. Well, you can forget all that when you deploy a BDC. The setup is all done via Python scripts, or a wizard in <strong>Azure Data Studio</strong>, (ADS)!</p>

<h4 id="install-tools">Install Tools</h4>

<p>There are some tools needed when deploying a BDC:</p>

<ul>
<li>Python - well, Python is not a tool as such, but you need Python installed on the machine you install from.</li>
<li><code>azdata</code> - command-line tool for installing and managing a big data cluster.</li>
<li><code>kubectl</code> - I mentioned the command-line tool for monitoring the underlying Kubernetes cluster above.</li>
<li>Azure Data Studio - a cross-platform graphical tool for querying SQL Server and other data sources.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> ADS is not required per se unless you use it for deployment, but it is an excellent tool when working with the BDC after deployment.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="deployment">Deployment</h4>

<p>The actual deployment of a BDC would require a couple of posts in itself, so here I point you to a couple of resources about BDC deployment:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/big-data-cluster/deployment-guidance?view=sql-server-ver15#deploy">How to deploy SQL Server Big Data Clusters on Kubernetes</a>. This is the official Microsoft documentation for deploying a BDC.</li>
<li><a href="https://mohammaddarab.com/how-to-deploy-a-big-data-cluster-to-a-single-node-kubeadm-cluster/">How to Deploy a Big Data Cluster to a Single Node Kubeadm Cluster</a>. A post by my friend and BDC guru <a href="https://mohammaddarab.com/">Mohammad Darab</a> about deploying to an on-prem single node cluster.</li>
<li><a href="https://mohammaddarab.com/how-to-deploy-a-big-data-cluster-to-a-multi-node-kubeadm-cluster/">How to Deploy a Big Data Cluster to a Multi Node Kubeadm Cluster</a>. A second post by <a href="https://mohammaddarab.com/">Mohammad</a>, this time he deploys to an on-prem multi node cluster.</li>
<li><a href="/2019/12/23/how-to-deploy-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-using-azure-data-studio/">How to Deploy SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster Using Azure Data Studio</a>. The link here is to a blog post by &ldquo;yours truly&rdquo; about how to deploy to Azure using ADS.</li>
</ul>

<p>Following the <a href="/2019/12/23/how-to-deploy-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-using-azure-data-studio/">Azure Data Studio post</a> I now have a BDC deployed to the k8s <code>kubesqlbdc-cluster</code> in the Azure resource group <code>rg-ignite-sqlbdc</code>.</p>

<h2 id="managing-a-bdc">Managing a BDC</h2>

<p>So now we have installed and deployed our BDC, let us look at how we can manage it.</p>

<h4 id="kubernets-dashboard">Kubernets Dashboard</h4>

<p>Above I mentioned the k8s dashboard, but we did not see it &ldquo;in action&rdquo;. Let us spin it up against our BDC cluster and see what it looks like.</p>

<p>So let us use the code we saw right above <em>Figure 4</em>, but change the <code>--resource-group</code> and <code>--name</code> options to what I deployed my BDC as:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">az aks browse --resource-group rg-ignite-sqlbdc \
              --name kubesqlbdc-cluster
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Code Snippet 3:</strong> <em>Kubernetes Dashboard</em></p>

<p>When I execute the code in <em>Code Snippet 3</em>, I see something like so:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-dash1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 5:</strong> <em>Kubernetes Start Dashboard</em></p>

<p>What we see in <em>Figure 5</em> is how the <code>az aks browse</code> command creates a secure channel from the dashboard in the k8s cluster to <code>localhost</code>, and at the same time a page opens in your browser:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-dash2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 6:</strong> <em>Kubernetes Dashboard</em></p>

<p>So, in <em>Figure 6</em> we see the overview page of the k8s dashboard. In the left, outlined in blue, we see a list of components making up the k8s cluster:</p>

<ul>
<li>Nodes.</li>
<li>Pods.</li>
<li>Services.</li>
<li>Replica and Stateful Sets.</li>
<li>and more.</li>
</ul>

<p>By clicking on any of the entries you drill further down into that specific component. However, when I look at the dashboard I do not see anything that refers to a SQL Server Big Data Cluster at all. I mean, I am certain that there should be able to see something under Stateful Sets for example:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-dash-default-ns.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 7:</strong> <em>Empty Stateful Sets</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 7</em> we see the result when I click on Stateful Sets, (outlined in red), in the dashboards Web UI: nothing. What is up with that?</p>

<p>Well, cast your mind back to when you created and deployed your cluster - at that time you gave the BDC cluster a name. When you deploy your BDC cluster, a k8s namespace gets created with that name.  The BDC is then created and deployed into that namespace. Look again at <em>Figure 6</em> and you see, outlined in red, a drop-down containing the various k8s namespaces in this k8s cluster:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-dash3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 8:</strong> <em>Kubernetes Namespaces</em></p>

<p>When I expand the drop-down, I see some more namespaces in addition to the <code>default</code> namespace, and among them, outlined in red, the namespace for the BDC cluster: <code>sqlbdc-cluster</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-dash4.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 9:</strong> <em>Overview BDC Cluster</em></p>

<p>When I click on &ldquo;my&rdquo; namespace, (once again outlined in red), I see an overview as in <em>Figure 9</em>. When we now are in the BDC namespace let us revisit the Stateful Sets as in <em>Figure 7</em>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-dash5.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 10:</strong> <em>BDC Stateful Sets</em></p>

<p>What we see in <em>Figure 10</em> is definitely more like it, as we can see quite a few stateful sets, and amongst them; <code>master</code>, (outlined in red). Master is the stateful set for the SQL Server master instance in a BDC, and we will look at <code>master</code> in a bit.</p>

<h4 id="kubectl">kubectl</h4>

<p>So the k8s dashboard is one way to manage and get information about a BDC, and the dashboard is a quick and easy way to get information about your cluster. I find however that when you want to do more than just get an overview of your cluster you use <code>kubectl</code>, (which I mentioned above).</p>

<p><strong>Pods</strong></p>

<p>Let us revisit the <code>get pods</code> command which I mentioned wouldn&rsquo;t return any result if I ran it against the test cluster above. If I do it now against the <code>kubesqlbdc-cluster</code> however:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kubectl1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 11:</strong> <em>Get Pods</em></p>

<p>Cool, we see in <em>Figure 11</em> that we actually have pods in the cluster. Notice in <em>Figure 11</em> how I called <code>get pods</code> with the namespace I wanted the pods from. You can also call <code>get pods</code> with <code>--all-namespaces</code> to see all pods in your k8s cluster.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> Yes, when we look at <em>Figure 11</em> we see how some pods are in an evicted state. How to solve that is a topic for a future post.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In <em>Figure 11</em> we see a pod outlined in red, the <code>master-0</code> pod. It belongs to the <code>master</code> stateful set we saw above, and we can further drill into the pod:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kubectl2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 12:</strong> <em>Describe Pod</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 12</em> we see how we execute <code>kubctl describe pods/master-0 ...</code> to get detailed information about the pod. We see, outlined in yellow, how the pod has a containers section, where the various containers in the pod are listed, and we see one of the containers, the <code>mssql-server</code> container. There are more, and we see that later.</p>

<p>The <code>Labels</code> section, (outlined in red), is interesting as it gives us some insight into what this pod is doing, and what role it plays in the BDC. We&rsquo;ll come back to this in next post.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> Instead of <code>kubectl describe ...</code> we can run <code>kubectl get pods/master-0 ... -o json</code> to get the same output as in <code>describe</code>, but in JSON format.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Services</strong></p>

<p>I mentioned above about <code>Services</code>, and how they among many things expose endpoints by which we can access the BDC from the &ldquo;outside world&rdquo;.</p>

<p>To find out what services we have in the BDC, we use a <code>kubectl</code> command:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kubectl3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 13:</strong> <em>Services</em></p>

<p>The command we use, as we see in <em>Figure 13</em>, is <code>kubectl get svc -n sqlbc-cluster</code>. That gives us back the various services with their name, what type they are, their internal IP address, their external IP address, (if any), and the ports the expose.</p>

<p>The services outlined in red in <em>Figure 13</em>, are the external endpoint services, i.e. the services we can reach from the outside world. The service highlighted in yellow, <code>master-svc-external</code> is the service that exposes the master instance of SQL Server. We see in <em>Figure 13</em> that the port for the SQL Server instance is not the usual 1433 but 31433. So to connect to the master instance, you connect to the IP shown in <code>EXTERNAL-IP</code> using port <code>31433</code>.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> The port numbers shown for the externally exposed services can all be changed during deployment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We have seen how we can use <code>kubectl</code> to get a list of services, and we see that some of the services expose external endpoints. But what are those endpoints, what do they do? Well, we know that <code>master-svc-external</code> is the SQL Server master instance, as I just said that, but the others?</p>

<p>So, here&rsquo;s the thing: <code>kubectl</code> is awesome for managing the k8s cluster, but it doesn&rsquo;t know anything about the specifics about the BDC. Fortunately there &ldquo;is an app for that&rdquo;: <code>azdata</code>.</p>

<h4 id="azdata">azdata</h4>

<p>I mentioned in the deployment section above that <code>azdata</code> is a pre-requisite for deployment, and after installation of a BDC, <code>azdata</code> gives you complete control of the BDC.</p>

<p>Using <code>azdata</code>, you can upgrade your cluster, deploy applications into your cluster, see statuses, and much more. To get more detail of what <code>azdata</code> can do, <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/big-data-cluster/reference-azdata?view=sql-server-ver15">here</a> is the reference documentation for <code>azdata</code>.</p>

<p>Now, knowing a bit about <code>azdata</code> let us use it to view a list of endpoints, something similar to what we saw in <em>Figure 13</em>.</p>

<p>Before you use <code>azdata</code> ensure you have configured <code>kubectl</code> as we did in <em>Code Snippet 1</em> above. Then you can log in to the cluster:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-azdata1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 14:</strong> <em><code>azdata</code> Log-in</em></p>

<p>To log in, we use the <code>azdata login</code> command, (surprise, surprise), which is outlined in red in <em>Figure 14</em>. When you log in you supply the BDC namespace, the username you set provided when you deployed, and the password. You are then good to go!</p>

<p>So, let us get the endpoints:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-azdata2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 15:</strong> <em>Get Endpoints</em></p>

<p>We retrieve the endpoints by calling <code>azdata bdc endpoint list</code>, which you see outlined in red in <em>Figure 15</em>. In <em>Figure 15</em> we also see part of the result coming back as JSON. If we want the result back in a more readable format, we can use the <code>--output</code>, or <code>-o</code> option with either of the following values:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>json</code></li>
<li><code>jsonc</code></li>
<li><code>table</code></li>
<li><code>tsv</code></li>
</ul>

<p>Let us see what it looks like in <code>table</code> format:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-azdata3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 16:</strong> <em>Endpoints in Tabular Format</em></p>

<p>Well, what we see in <em>Figure 16</em> is more readable than what we saw in <em>Figure 15</em>, don&rsquo;t you agree. Outlined in red, we see the command with the <code>table</code> output value, and then the various endpoints. As I said before, we see the SQL Server master instance endpoint accessible via port <code>31433</code>.</p>

<p>What is outlined in yellow are two endpoints we&rsquo;ll discuss now.</p>

<h2 id="monitoring-the-bdc">Monitoring the BDC</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve seen above how the k8s dashboard allows us to monitor the k8s cluster, at least to some degree. What about monitoring the BDC cluster? We know from what we have covered so far that the k8s cluster does not know anything about BDC, so how do we monitor a BDC cluster?</p>

<p>Let us go back to <em>Figure 15</em> and look at what is highlighted in yellow:</p>

<ul>
<li>Log Search Dashboard</li>
<li>Metrics Dashboard</li>
</ul>

<p>When you look at the URL&rsquo;s for those two endpoints, you see how they end in <code>kibana</code> and <code>grafana</code> respectively. Remember what I said up above about how Microsoft embraces Open Source; this is another example of it. They include Kibana and Grafana in the BDC together with Elasticsearch and InfluxDB!</p>

<h4 id="kibana">Kibana</h4>

<p>We start with Kibana. Kibana is an open-source log analysis platform, where the logs are stored in Elasticsearch clusters. To use Kibana, we browse to the URL for the endpoint:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kibana1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 17:</strong> <em>Kibana Login</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 17</em> we see the login screen for Kibana. To log in, you use the username and password you defined during the BDC deployment. You then log in:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kibana2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 18:</strong> <em>Kibana Home Screen</em></p>

<p>After you have logged in, you are presented with the Kibana home screen as we see in <em>Figure 18</em>. To get to the logs, you click on the symbol on the left looking like a compass:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kibana3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 19:</strong> <em>Kibana Logs</em></p>

<p>What you see in <em>Figure 19</em> is the Kibana Discover screen, where you now can drill into the logs, query them using KQL, (Kibana Query Language), and lots more.</p>

<h4 id="grafana">Grafana</h4>

<p>Having had a brief look at Kibana, let us go to Grafana.</p>

<p>Grafana is an open-source visualization tool that can be used on top of a variety of different data stores but is most commonly used together with Graphite, InfluxDB, Prometheus, Elasticsearch and Logz.io. In the BDC, the underlying data store is InfluxDB.</p>

<p>You browse to the Grafana URL, and you log-in using the same credentials as you did with Kibana:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-grafana1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 20:</strong> <em>Grafana Home Screen</em></p>

<p>In the Grafana home screen as you see in <em>Figure 20</em> you click on the &ldquo;Home&rdquo; button outlined in red:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-grafana2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 21:</strong> <em>Grafana Dashboards</em></p>

<p>The Grafana installation comes with some already created dashboards, and we see a list of them in <em>Figure 21</em>. I click on the &ldquo;SQL Server Metrics&rdquo;:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-grafana3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 22:</strong> <em>SQL Server Metrics</em></p>

<p>The Host drop-down list, (outlined in red), gives you a list of all the SQL Server instances in the BDC. I choose <code>master-0</code> which is the SQL Server master instance, and we see in the figure some of the metrics collected for SQL Server.</p>

<p>We have here seen how Microsoft has included compelling monitoring tools in the BDC:</p>

<ul>
<li>Kibana for log monitoring.</li>
<li>Grafana for metrics monitoring.</li>
</ul>

<p>That is very cool that the BDC contains these tools, but what is doing the data collection?</p>

<h2 id="log-and-monitor-data-collection">Log and Monitor Data Collection</h2>

<p>To answer the question above, we can look closer at one of the pods to see what containers are in the pod:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bdc-lap-around-bdc-kubectl4.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Figure 23:</strong> <em>SQL Server Metrics</em></p>

<p>In <em>Figure 23</em> we see how I have called <code>kubectl get pods master-0</code> with some output &ldquo;magic&rdquo; to get information about the SQL Server master instance pod. We see that the pod contains three containers, and the two outlined in red are the interesting ones:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>collectd</code> - Unix daemon that collects, transfers and stores performance data of computers and network equipment. It feeds InfluxDB.</li>
<li><code>fluentbit</code> - a lightweight log collector, it feeds Elasticsearch.</li>
</ul>

<p>These two containers, (or sometimes one of them), are part of almost all pods in a BDC. That is how the BDC collects data from the various services and feeds it into Elasticsearch and InfluxDB.</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>In this first post, of a couple, based on my conference talk &ldquo;A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster&rdquo; we looked at a couple of things:</p>

<ul>
<li>The background, i.e. why do we have the BDC.</li>
<li>The technology behind it - what makes it tick.</li>
<li>Managing and monitoring a BDC.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Background:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>We are getting more and more data.</li>
<li>The data comes in all shapes and sizes.</li>
<li>We want SQL Server to be the hub for all our data, regardless of type.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Technology</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Kubernetes.</li>
<li>SQL Server on Linux.</li>
<li>Apache Spark.</li>
<li>Hadoop File System (HDFS).</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Managing &amp; Monitoring</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Kubernetes Dashboard.</li>
<li><code>kubectl</code>.</li>
<li><code>azdata</code>.</li>
<li>Grafana and Kibana.</li>
</ul>

<p>In next post, we take a look at the architecture of the BDC.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>If you have comments, questions etc., please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 16, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/19/interesting-stuff---week-16-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-19T09:59:40+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/19/interesting-stuff---week-16-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data-science">Data Science</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/2020/04/forecasting-best-practices-from-microsoft.html">Forecasting Best Practices, from Microsoft</a>. It is a long time since I have linked to something from <a href="http://blog.revolutionanalytics.com">Revolution Analytics</a>. That is now rectified by this post where <a href="https://twitter.com/revodavid">David</a> points to resources from Microsoft around best practices around time series forecasting. Have a look, quite a lot of cool stuff there!</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/rendezvous-architecture-for-data-science-in-production-79c4d48f12b">Rendezvous Architecture for Data Science in Production</a>. In this post the author discusses one of the biggest problems in Data Science today how to productionise your models. The answer to that problem is something called the Rendezvous Architecture.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://note.microsoft.com/MSR-Webinar-Coyote-Registration-Live.html">Better design, implementation, and testing of async systems with Coyote</a>. In the <a href="/2020/03/29/interesting-stuff---week-13-2020/">Interesting Stuff - Week 13, 2020</a> I wrote about Coyote, the framework for building reliable asynchronous software. The link here is a registration page for a webinar April 30 about Coyote. If you are interested in things like async and distributed systems, then I suggest you register. See you there!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="event-driven-architecture">Event Driven Architecture</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/phi-skills/event-driven-data-collection-d662a7db52a5">Event-Driven Data Collection</a>. I linked to some posts about Event Driven Architecture in the <a href="/2020/04/05/interesting-stuff---week-14-2020/">Interesting Stuff - Week 14, 2020</a> post, and the post linked to here is by the same author as the posts in the <a href="/2020/04/05/interesting-stuff---week-14-2020/">week 14</a> roundup. In this post, the author discusses how to populate databases from event-driven data collection.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/apache-kafka-2-5-latest-version-updates/">What’s New in Apache Kafka 2.5</a>. Apache Kafka version 2.5 was released earlier this week, and the post here discusses new &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; in the release.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-business-intelligence-using-ksqldb/">Real-Time Small Business Intelligence with ksqlDB</a>. In this post, the author makes the point that the Kafka ecosystem is not only for the Netflix:es in this world, but that by using ksqlDB even smaller companies can gain insights into their data.</li>
<li><a href="https://rmoff.net/2020/04/16/a-quick-and-dirty-way-to-monitor-data-arriving-on-kafka/">A quick and dirty way to monitor data arriving on Kafka</a>. The title of this post describes the post perfectly. <a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a> shows a way to quickly and easily monitor Kafka data, and be alerted if something happens. Actually be alerted if something does not happen (data arriving).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me. Most importantly, stay safe out there!</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 15, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/12/interesting-stuff---week-15-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-12T09:27:47+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/12/interesting-stuff---week-15-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/kafka-acks-explained-c0515b3b707e">Kafka Acks Explained</a>. The post here covers in detail how acks in Kafka works, and what the two config options <code>acks</code> and <code>min.insync.replicas</code> does. Very informative!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/confluent-cloud-ksql-as-a-service/">Confluent Cloud KSQL is Now Available</a>. Finally! The post title says it all. KSQL and ksqlDB are now generally available in Confluent Cloud. That is so cool!</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/fraud-prevention-and-threat-detection-with-kafka-streams/">Preventing Fraud and Fighting Account Takeovers with Kafka Streams</a>. This is an awesome post, looking at how Kafka streams can be used in a fraud preventing scenario. Quite a lot of useful ideas in the post!</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@NetflixTechBlog/inca-message-tracing-and-loss-detection-for-streaming-data-netflix-de4836fc38c9">Inca — Message Tracing and Loss Detection For Streaming Data @Netflix</a>. I don&rsquo;t know how I have not seen this post earlier. Well, anyway, the post gives a good overview of how Netflix does message loss detection and tracing of their streaming events.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Had a nice Easter dinner yesterday - Happy Easter, everyone!</p>

<p>Still in lock-down. The lock-down period here in SA was a couple of days ago extended to the end of April! Let&rsquo;s hope the lock-down has an\ positive impact!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me. Most importantly, stay safe out there!</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 14, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/05/interesting-stuff---week-14-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-04-05T08:25:49+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/04/05/interesting-stuff---week-14-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data">Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/a-guide-to-modern-batch-data-warehousing-extraction-f63bfa6ef878">A Guide To The Data Lake — Modern Batch Data Warehousing</a>. Lately I have come across blog posts about data, data lakes, data warehousing, etc. Maybe that&rsquo;s because we are now looking at this at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, and how an ideal data architecture would look like for us. Anyway, the post here discusses how one can redefine batch data extraction and the data lake.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/an-introduction-to-dataframe/">An Introduction to DataFrame</a>. I don&rsquo;t know how I missed this before, but this post announces a data frame data type for .NET. The DataFrame type can come in very handy in a project I&rsquo;m working on right now. We&rsquo;ll see!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="events">Events</h2>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://medium.com/phi-skills/events-are-the-key-to-master-data-11984332e435">Events are the Key to Master Data</a>. The blog post linked to here discusses events as a type of data, and why events are essential.</p></li>

<li><p><a href="https://medium.com/phi-skills/the-path-to-event-driven-mastery-8baff91826f1">The Path to Event-Driven Mastery</a>. This post is a follow-up to the one above. In this post, the author gives a quick overview of different concepts related to events and how they are similar or different from each other.</p></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/real-time-data-replication-with-ksqldb/">Real-Time Data Replication with ksqlDB</a>. This post looks at how functionality in Kafka&rsquo;s ksqlDB is used to replicate data from multiple sources to data warehouses.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Last week <a href="/2020/03/29/interesting-stuff---week-13-2020/">I mentioned</a> how South Africa is now in lock-down due to the Coronavirus, and how the muse has left me, and I cannot get a SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster blog post out.</p>

<p>Well, we are still in lock-down, we are going into the second week now. Fortunately, I live in a house with a garden and pool, so I can at least get outside. To get some exercise, I yesterday walked around the pool: 50 laps, which is around two kilometres! Before the lock-down, the thought of walking around the pool for exercise would never, ever have entered my mind!</p>

<p>And for the muse, no I did not find her on my walk. I hope she&rsquo;ll be back soon!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me. Most importantly, stay safe out there!</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 13, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/29/interesting-stuff---week-13-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-03-29T09:58:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/29/interesting-stuff---week-13-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="data">Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/building-a-data-warehouse-basic-architectural-principles-66bd7059ffd0">Building a Data Warehouse: Basic Architectural principles</a>. The post linked to here looks at an approach towards simplifying data warehousing. The post comes in &ldquo;handy&rdquo; as we are looking at this in <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> at the moment.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/blog/coyote-making-it-easier-for-developers-to-build-reliable-asynchronous-software/">Coyote: Making it easier for developers to build reliable asynchronous software</a>. This post is about Coyote, which is a programming framework for building reliable asynchronous software. It ensures the design and code remain in sync, which simplifies the addition of new features. Looks very interesting - I&rsquo;ll talk to some of my developers and see what they say.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-real-time-data-and-big-data-streaming/">ksqlDB: The Missing Link Between Real-Time Data and Big Data Streaming</a>. When processing data, the question is, what is more efficient: event streaming or batch processing. The question comes from two ideas around data analytics architecture: state orientation and event orientation The post I link to here looks at both concepts and, as this is from Confluent, it highlights the event streaming capabilities in ksqlDB.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>In last weeks <a href="/2020/03/22/interesting-stuff---week-12-2020/">roundup</a> I mentioned how South Africa had declared a national disaster and more or less put the country in lock-down. This due to the Coronavirus. Well, the &ldquo;more or less&rdquo; lock-down became a true lock-down last Friday (March 27), and we are no longer allowed to leave our homes, except in case of emergencies, and to purchase groceries!</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll see how long the lock-down lasts. Initially, it is said to be for 3 weeks, but most people expect it to be longer. From a work perspective, I am lucky to be working for <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, as the company has made a tremendous effort in enabling all employees to work from home!</p>

<p>The blog-post I have been working on based on my conference talk <em>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</em> is still not done. I have a bad case of &ldquo;writers&rsquo; block&rdquo; at the moment. Hopefully, I will get over it sooner rather than later, but do not expect this post anytime soon. Sorry about that!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me. Most importantly stay safe out there!</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 12, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/22/interesting-stuff---week-12-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-03-22T09:38:19+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/22/interesting-stuff---week-12-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/six-rules-for-good-git-hygiene-5006cf9e9e2">Six Rules for Good Git Hygiene</a>. My Git knowledge is minimal, so this post about how to be a team player with commits, pushes, and pulls was really useful for me.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/how-to-use-stateful-operations-in-kafka-streams-1cff4da41329">How to Use Stateful Operations in Kafka Streams</a>. The post linked to here explores stateful operations in the Kafka Streams DSL API. It focuses on aggregation operations such as <code>aggregate</code>, <code>count</code>, and <code>reduce</code> along with a discussion of related concepts. The post is the second in a series about Kafka Streams API, and the first post is <a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/learn-stream-processing-with-kafka-streams-stateless-operations-2111080e6c53">here</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/better-programming/testing-kafka-streams-applications-1c5cb14c5376">How to Test Kafka Streams Applications</a>. This post is the third in the series mentioned above, and the post explores a few examples of how to use the testing utilities provided by Kafka streams to validate topologies based on the Kafka Streams DSL API.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-8-0-feature-updates/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.8.0</a>. As the title of the post says, the post covers the new version of ksqlDB. There are quite a few new features that I cannot wait to test!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/confluentinc/ksql/blob/7bf5c120c7128d4825f74fc7e691ef2c68c6911b/design-proposals/klip-15-new-api-and-client.md">KLIP 15 - ksqlDB Client and New Server API</a>. From reading the announcement above about ksqlDB 0.8.0, I came across the page linked to here. Getting new ksqlDB client and server APIs to make stream developing easier is a game changer! I, for one, am eager to hear more about this. Oh, and <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/ksql-dev/yxcRlsOsNmo">here</a> is a lengthy Google Group discussion around this.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> KLIP stands for &ldquo;Kafka Language Improval Proposal&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>What a weird week this has been all thanks to the Coronavirus! On Sunday, (Mar 15), the president of South Africa - Cyril Ramaphosa - declared the Coronavirus a national disaster and more or less put the country in lock-down.</p>

<p>This resulted in that on Monday morning at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>, everyone that had remote working capabilities was sent home. For the remainder of staff, plans were made how to get them up-and-running remotely. At the end of the week most of the company, (~1800 people), worked from home. Way to go <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a>!</p>

<p>So since Monday afternoon, I have been working from home, and even though it is a bit strange initially, the whole experience has been overall positive.</p>

<p>You may remember how I in <a href="/2020/03/15/interesting-stuff---week-11-2020/">last weeks roundup</a> wrote that I am &ldquo;blogifying&rdquo; one of the conference talks I do about SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster: <em>A Lap Around SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</em>. Working from home has not given me any more time with the post, but I am nearly there, and it should be out in the next week.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me. Most importantly stay safe out there!</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 11, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/15/interesting-stuff---week-11-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-03-15T09:37:09+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/15/interesting-stuff---week-11-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://itnext.io/scalable-microservice-demo-k8s-istio-kafka-344a2610eba3">Scalable Microservice Demo K8s Istio Kafka</a>. In this post, the author shows a very &ldquo;cool&rdquo; example of how one can auto-scale applications in Kubernetes, using a Horizontal Pod Autoscaler, (HPA), and Istio.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/deploying-ml-models-in-distributed-real-time-data-streaming-applications-217954a0b423">Deploying ML Models in Distributed Real-time Data Streaming Applications</a>. This post explores the various strategies to deploy ML models in Apache Flink/Spark or other realtime data streaming applications.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/learn-stream-processing-with-kafka-tutorials/">Sharpening your Stream Processing Skills with Kafka Tutorials</a>. In the post linked to, the author discusses the various ways we can process streams in the Kafka eco-system and points us to the <a href="https://kafka-tutorials.confluent.io/">Kafka Tutorials</a> site, where we can learn about various aspects of building applications with Kafka.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>The last few weeks, I have been somewhat lazy, (OK then, very lazy), and I have not posted much about SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster or SQL Server Extensibility framework.</p>

<p>That is changing now. I am working on a post about SQL Server 2019 BDC, which is based on the conference talks I have given about the BDC.</p>

<p>I am also doing some cool &ldquo;stuff&rdquo; regarding the Extensibility Framework, but at this point, I am not allowed to say what it is. But if you are interested, watch this space!</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 10, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/08/interesting-stuff---week-10-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-03-08T12:44:22+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/08/interesting-stuff---week-10-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="net">.NET</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/okteto/how-to-develop-and-debug-asp-net-core-applications-in-kubernetes-e2d1fe62068f">How to Develop and Debug ASP.NET Core Applications in Kubernetes</a>. This is an interesting post looking at developing ASP.NET Core applications for Kubernetes using a tool/framework called <a href="https://github.com/okteto/okteto">Okteto</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/choosing-between-mock-api-and-real-backend/">Mock APIs vs. Real Backends – Getting the Best of Both Worlds</a>. The post linked to here from the Confluent discusses whether to mock or not and if you can do both.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/how-netflix-uses-druid-for-real-time-insights-to-ensure-a-high-quality-experience-19e1e8568d06">How Netflix uses Druid for Real-time Insights to Ensure a High-Quality Experience</a>. A few years ago we looked at Druid in <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> and evaluated if we could use it. Nothing came out of it, but from reading this post, maybe we should look again.</li>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/scalable-efficient-big-data-analytics-machine-learning-pipeline-architecture-on-cloud-4d59efc092b5">Architecture for High-Throughput Low-Latency Big Data Pipeline on Cloud</a>. Don&rsquo;t let the title of this post fool you; this is not cloud specific. The post discusses tools and techniques for building data pipelines for Big Data.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/kafka-zookeeper/">Kafka Needs No Keeper</a>. In this <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation, the presenter talks about the ongoing effort to replace the use of Zookeeper in Kafka: the reasons for why it should be done and how it will work.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 9, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/01/interesting-stuff---week-9-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-03-01T07:53:45+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/03/01/interesting-stuff---week-9-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="azure">Azure</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.paraesthesia.com/archive/2020/02/25/tips-for-custom-azure-devops-build-tasks/">Tips for Creating Custom Azure DevOps Build Tasks</a>. At <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> we have started using Azure DevOps in earnest, so this post by Travis comes in real handy.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="big-data">Big Data</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/presentations/data-mesh-paradigm/">Data Mesh Paradigm Shift in Data Platform Architecture</a>. In my weekly roundup for <a href="/2020/02/02/interesting-stuff---week-5-2020/">week 5</a>, I mentioned a post about the state of today&rsquo;s <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/data-monolith-to-mesh.html">data architecture</a>. The <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> presentation I link to here, is done by the same person that wrote the post, and the presentation is essentially the content of the blog post, (or the other way around :)).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="machine-learning-data-science">Machine Learning / Data Science</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/how-to-embed-a-spark-ml-model-as-a-kafka-real-time-streaming-application-for-production-deployment-933aecb79f3f">How to embed a Spark ML Model as a Kafka Real-Time Streaming Application for Production Deployment</a>. This is a very interesting post. As the title says, it covers the use of Spark ML together with Kafka, and how a streaming application can make ML predictions in real-time.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/trendyol-tech/how-to-implement-retry-logic-with-spring-kafka-710b51501ce2">How to implement retry logic with Spring Kafka</a>. An informative post with ideas on how to implement retry logic, (exactly as the title says).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/configure-kafka-to-minimize-latency/">99th Percentile Latency at Scale with Apache Kafka</a>. The post linked to here is a must-read for you who want to get the best performance out of your Kafka clusters. The post discusses how to configure Kafka to minimize latency.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/confluent-developer-offers-kafka-tutorials-resources-guides/">Introducing Confluent Developer</a>. In this post, Confluent&rsquo;s director of developer relations, <a href="https://twitter.com/tlberglund">Tim Berglund</a>, introduces the goto place for everything Kafka - <a href="https://developer.confluent.io/">Confluent Developer</a>. I&rsquo;ve had a look over the weekend, and it is a treasure trove of material to go through if you are into Kafka.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>The title in this section is not entirely correct as this is not so much about what I am doing right now as it is what I did the week just passed.</p>

<p>Anyway, the week just passed, I did two webinars for <a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/"><strong>DataPlatformGeeks</strong></a>, (DPG):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/videos/data-virtualization-in-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-by-niels-berglund-recorded-webinar/">Data Virtualization in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</a>. Where we look at how we do data virtualization in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/videos/deep-dives-into-the-storage-and-data-pools-in-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster-by-niels-berglund-recorded-webinar/">Deep Dives into the Storage and Data Pools in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</a>. A closer look at the storage and data pools in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster.</li>
</ul>

<p>I recommend all of you to <a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/registration">register</a> with DPG, as they have a plethora of free learning resources! Oh, and they also run a yearly conference; <a href="https://www.dps10.com/">Data Platform Summit</a>. I hope to be able to deliver a couple of sessions at the conference this year.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 8, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/02/23/interesting-stuff---week-8-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-02-23T06:46:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/02/23/interesting-stuff---week-8-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="distributed-computing">Distributed Computing</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/anatomy-cascading-failure">Anatomy of Cascading Failure</a>. In the <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article linked to here, the author discusses what a cascading failure is, and some anti-patterns around cascading failures. If you work with distributed systems, then you should really read this article.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="streaming">Streaming</h1>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@dev.anowak/monolith-to-event-driven-microservices-with-apache-kafka-6e4abe171cbb">Monolith to Event-Driven Microservices with Apache Kafka</a>. The post in the link talks about the advantages of event-driven systems, and how one can gradually evolve to an event-driven system from a monolith.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/articles/building-scalable-iot-application-with-apache-kafka/">The Kongo Problem: Building a Scalable IoT Application with Apache Kafka</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article discusses scalability and Kafka. The article is based on a series of blog posts, where the first post is <a href="https://www.instaclustr.com/instaclustr-kongo-iot-logistics-streaming-demo-application/">here</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="wind-what-is-niels-doing">WIND (What Is Niels Doing)</h2>

<p>Back in December, I did two webinars for <a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/">DataPlatformGeeks</a>, and you can read more about it <a href="/2019/12/08/interesting-stuff---week-49-2019/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Next week I am doing two more:</p>

<p><strong>February 25</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/events/dpg-webinar-25th-february-2020-0300-pm-0400-pm-ist-niels-berglund-data-virtualization-in-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster/">Data Virtualization in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</a>. Where we look at how we do data virtualization in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>February 27</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.dataplatformgeeks.com/events/dpg-webinar-27th-february-2020-0300-pm-0400-pm-ist-niels-berglund-deep-dives-into-the-storage-and-data-pools-in-sql-server-2019-big-data-cluster/">Deep Dives into the Storage and Data Pools in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster</a>. A closer look at the storage and data pools in SQL Server 2019 Big Data Cluster.</li>
</ul>

<p>The webinars are free, so if you have time, register and join the fun! Notice that the times in the links above are Indian Standard Time, so 3 pm IST is 09:30 am, UTC.</p>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interesting Stuff - Week 7, 2020]]></title>
    <link href="https://nielsberglund.com/2020/02/16/interesting-stuff---week-7-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <updated>2020-02-16T07:30:30+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://nielsberglund.com/2020/02/16/interesting-stuff---week-7-2020/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:</p>

<ul>
<li>data science</li>
<li>data in general</li>
<li>distributed computing</li>
<li>SQL Server</li>
<li>transactions (both db as well as non db)</li>
<li>and other &ldquo;stuff&rdquo;</li>
</ul>

<p>This blog-post is the &ldquo;roundup&rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.</p>

<p></p>

<h2 id="misc">Misc.</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2020/02/Microsoft-Application-Inspector">Microsoft Releases Application Inspector, a Tool for Examining Code Security</a>. This <a href="https://www.infoq.com/">InfoQ</a> article discusses <strong>Microsoft Application Inspector</strong> a source code analyzer with some interesting features. The application not only detects &ldquo;poor&rdquo; programming practices, but it also surfaces and reports interesting characteristics the code that would be difficult/time-consuming to identify.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="data-science-machine-learning">Data Science / Machine Learning</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/blog/zero-deepspeed-new-system-optimizations-enable-training-models-with-over-100-billion-parameters/">ZeRO &amp; DeepSpeed: New system optimizations enable training models with over 100 billion parameters</a>. The blog post linked to here looks at ZeRO, ( Zero Redundancy Optimizer), which is a memory optimization technology for large-scale distributed deep learning. From the post: <em>ZeRO can train deep learning models with 100 billion parameters on the current generation of GPU clusters at three to five times the throughput of the current best system.</em> Wowza! Those are large numbers!</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="streaming">Streaming</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/swlh/domain-events-versus-change-data-capture-e426772f76e5">Domain Events versus Change Data Capture</a>. The topics of change data capture and event-based systems come more and more up in various discussions. In the linked post, the author looks at these topics and explains the differences as well as when to use what.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/ksqldb-0-7-0-feature-updates/">Announcing ksqlDB 0.7.0</a>. In <a href="/2020/02/09/interesting-stuff---week-6-2020/">last weeks roundup</a> I covered a <a href="https://rmoff.net/2020/02/07/primitive-keys-in-ksqldb/">post</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/rmoff">Robin Moffat</a> where he looked at a new feature in the upcoming ksqlDB 0.7 release. The post linked to here is the official announcement of ksqlDB 0.7. There are quite a few new interesting features in the release, and us at <a href="/derivco">Derivco</a> will definitely look at the release.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confluent.io/blog/elasticsearch-ksqldb-integration-for-data-enrichment-and-analytics/">Integrating Elasticsearch and ksqlDB for Powerful Data Enrichment and Analytics</a>. In the post linked to here, the author looks at how we can use both Elasticsearch and ksqlDB to get more intelligence from your streaming data.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finally">~ Finally</h2>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week. I hope you enjoy what I did put together. If you have ideas for what to cover, please comment on this post or <a href="mailto:niels.it.berglund@gmail.com">ping</a> me.</p>]]></content>
    <author>
      <name>Niels Berglund</name>

    </author>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

