<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vector Db on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/vector-db/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vector Db on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 05:53:02 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/vector-db/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 51, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-12-21-interesting-stuff---week-51-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 05:53:02 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-12-21-interesting-stuff---week-51-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the final roundup of 2025! This week brings us an exceptional collection of paradigm-shifting insights as we close out the year: a battle-tested SQL Server log shipping script that&amp;rsquo;s been running uninterrupted in production for years, a comprehensive deep-dive into router-based agent architectures that are transforming monolithic AI systems, a mathematically rigorous takedown of vector database over-adoption in RAG systems, Armin Ronacher&amp;rsquo;s investigation into what Claude Code&amp;rsquo;s plan mode actually does under the hood, and Andrej Karpathy&amp;rsquo;s characteristically brilliant year-in-review covering everything from RLVR to &amp;ldquo;ghosts vs. animals&amp;rdquo; and the rise of vibe coding.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After we explore these articles, I&amp;rsquo;ll be signing off for the festive season to recharge with family and friends, returning in the new year with fresh insights and probably way too much excitement about whatever paradigm-shifting tech drops in January. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into Week 51&amp;rsquo;s highlights!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 19, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-05-14-interesting-stuff---week-19-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 11:34:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-05-14-interesting-stuff---week-19-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some very cool stuff this week. Polars for Rust! Azure Data Explorer as a Vector DB. ChatGPT and Pandas = PandasAI.;  and real-time streaming ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LangChain, Streamlit, and Pinecone for LLM. Real-time sentiment analysis with Docker, Kafka, and Spark Streaming. And more!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
