<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Saturday on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/data-saturday/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Saturday on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 09:35:25 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/data-saturday/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-05-21-interesting-stuff---week-20-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 09:35:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-05-21-interesting-stuff---week-20-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s post, I will share with you some of the most interesting and relevant articles I have read this week on various topics related to data and streaming. You will find links to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The latest research developments in reinforcement learning and how they can be applied to different domains and challenges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The real-time streaming ecosystem and how to design and implement a streaming solution using various tools and technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The performance and latency improvements of Apache Spark Structured Streaming and how they enable more use cases for real-time data processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The highlights of Kafka Summit 2023, the largest conference for Apache Kafka users and enthusiasts, and the new features and announcements from Confluent, the leading provider of Kafka solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Saturday&lt;/strong&gt; in Johannesburg in August and planning for the upcoming &lt;strong&gt;Data Saturday - Durban&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about these topics and want to stay updated on the latest trends and innovations in the data and streaming world, read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
