<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NotebookLM on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/notebooklm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in NotebookLM on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 08:22:09 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/notebooklm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 31, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-08-03-interesting-stuff---week-31-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 08:22:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-08-03-interesting-stuff---week-31-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup reveals AI evolving from simple automation tools into sophisticated collaborative partners that understand how humans actually learn, write, and work. From OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s Study Mode transforming ChatGPT into a patient Socratic tutor to Google&amp;rsquo;s NotebookLM becoming a PowerPoint wizard, we&amp;rsquo;re witnessing the emergence of AI systems designed for genuine partnership rather than replacement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, GitHub Copilot&amp;rsquo;s coding agent receives the proper onboarding treatment, and Claude&amp;rsquo;s new agent architecture reveals the beautiful chaos of managing digital workforces where brilliant AI specialists can only communicate through you. These developments suggest we&amp;rsquo;re finally cracking the code on making AI collaboration feel natural and productive rather than frustratingly robotic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 40, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-10-06-interesting-stuff---week-40-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2024 10:15:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-10-06-interesting-stuff---week-40-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup highlights Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Drasi, an open-source tool simplifying real-time event detection in complex systems, and Data Formulator, which enhances data visualization with AI-driven precision.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also explore the revolutionary MotleyCrew AI framework for multi-agent systems and OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s Realtime API, streamlining voice assistant creation. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss insights into AutoGen 0.4 and Promptriever, both pushing the boundaries of scalable AI and information retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
