<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Saturday Durban on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/data-saturday-durban/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Saturday Durban on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 09:32:16 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/data-saturday-durban/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 32, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-13-interesting-stuff---week-32-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 09:32:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-13-interesting-stuff---week-32-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🔍 In this week&amp;rsquo;s roundup: Discover the power of Big Data&amp;rsquo;s serving layers in James Serra&amp;rsquo;s post, unveiling the benefits of relational and physical layers for data accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🚀 Speculate on the groundbreaking potential of OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s trademarked GPT-5, reshaping the AI landscape. 🌊 Stay ahead in the streaming world with Hubert&amp;rsquo;s newsletter, spotlighting rising stars like Redpanda and must-read Flink insights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join Niels at Data Saturday Durban for an Azure OpenAI deep-dive and seize the opportunity to learn from top speakers. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss out!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 31, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-07-interesting-stuff---week-31-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 06:49:53 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-07-interesting-stuff---week-31-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🔥 In this weeks roundup. Unleash the Power of AI: Master the art of prompt engineering, crafting effective cues for NLP models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore RAG-based chatbots and OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s evolution from GPT-1 to GPT-4, with a teaser of GPT-5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dive into event-driven serverless apps and harmonize streaming with standardized hashing. Join Niels on data adventures and secure your spot at Data Saturday Durban.🔗🚀&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 30, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-30-interesting-stuff---week-30-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 08:51:07 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-30-interesting-stuff---week-30-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🌟 Discover the latest tech innovations in this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post! From managing and analyzing game data at scale using Azure PlayFab and Databricks, to exploring the powerful Ambassador Pattern for distributed systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get ready for the exciting news about OpenAI Whisper&amp;rsquo;s arrival on Azure OpenAI Service and Azure AI Speech, along with the introduction of function calling. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss the insights on using Azure &amp;ldquo;Prompt Flow&amp;rdquo; and the fascinating potential of Apache Kafka as a mission-critical data fabric for GenAI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join us on this tech journey and mark your calendar for the upcoming Data Saturday events! 🚀🌐&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 29, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-23-interesting-stuff---week-29-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 14:20:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-23-interesting-stuff---week-29-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;📚 Explore the latest tech wonders and data-driven innovations in this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From empowering analysts with Azure Data Explorer to estimating customer lifetime value through Lakehouse architecture, and the exciting Databricks-MosaicML collaboration democratizing generative AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delve into the best sessions of Kafka Summit London 2023 and discover how Confluent revolutionizes real-time order notifications for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, don&amp;rsquo;t miss the impressive lineup of industry experts and sessions at Data Saturday Durban! Join us as we journey through the fascinating world of technology and data insights! 🌟&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 28, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-16-interesting-stuff---week-28-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 07:24:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-16-interesting-stuff---week-28-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post, we dive into some exciting developments in the tech world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we explore the Kusto Detective Academy, a valuable resource for mastering the Kusto Query Language (KQL) in Azure Data Explorer. Then, we discover GPT4Readability, a new tool powered by advanced language models like GPT-3.5 and GPT-4, designed to simplify the process of writing documentation and README files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we delve into the integration of Kafka, Debezium, and BentoML to build a machine-learning streaming pipeline and a preview of a stream processing performance report comparing Apache Flink with RisingWave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we get a glimpse into the upcoming Data Saturday Durban event and the intriguing topics under consideration. If you want to expand your knowledge and meet industry experts, don&amp;rsquo;t miss out on this exciting opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 27, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-09-interesting-stuff---week-27-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 13:05:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-09-interesting-stuff---week-27-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Unveil captivating discoveries: Explore vector databases, Azure OpenAI updates, generative AI insights, streaming trends, and more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me on this knowledge-packed journey, filled with innovation and community contributions. Fuel your curiosity and read the full post now!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 26, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-02-interesting-stuff---week-26-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 11:48:53 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-02-interesting-stuff---week-26-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve got everything from data pipelines to streaming platforms in this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post: Hoptimator, the tool designed to streamline and optimize data pipelines. Mobile Premier League (MPL) and how they reduced player churn using Confluent Cloud. Materialized views and streaming tables for Databricks SQL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Data Saturday Durban&lt;/strong&gt; on August 19. It is still time to submit a talk.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-06-10-interesting-stuff---week-23-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 14:45:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-06-10-interesting-stuff---week-23-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s post, I share some of the exciting things I have come across during the week related to data and AI:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll learn about the new features and capabilities of Azure Data Explorer, Azure AI, and Microsoft Fabric. You&amp;rsquo;ll also see how to combine ChatGPT and streaming data for real-time generative AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is a CfS for Data Saturday Durban 2023. If you are passionate about data and are interested in presenting any data-related topic, this is your chance to shine!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re curious about these topics, check out this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
