<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apache Kafka on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/categories/apache-kafka/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Apache Kafka on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 06:11:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/apache-kafka/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Run Self-Managed Kusto Kafka Connector Serverless in Azure Container Instances</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-09-06-run-self-managed-kafka-connector-in-serverless-azure-container-instance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 06:11:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-09-06-run-self-managed-kafka-connector-in-serverless-azure-container-instance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-08-14-run-confluent-cloud--serverless-apache-kafka-on-azure/&#34;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; how I set up Kafka to run serverless in Azure by deploying Confluent Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have followed my blog lately, you have probably seen that I am interested in &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; and that I have a couple of conference talks coming. One being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to do Real-Time Analytics Using Apache Kafka and Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;: We are looking at how to stream events from Apache Kafka to Azure Data Explorer (ADX) and perform user-facing analytics in near real-time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is how to connect Kafka with ADX? You normally connect Kafka with another system using a Kafka Connect connector, and fortunately a connector exists for connecting Kafka with ADX: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Azure/kafka-sink-azure-kusto&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kafka Connect Kusto Sink Connector&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, since I am running managed Kafka (Confluent Cloud, remember), I need a managed connector to run it in Confluent Cloud&amp;rsquo;s Kafka Connect. In the previous paragraph, I mentioned I was fortunate as we had a Kafka connector for ADX. Unfortunately, it is not a managed connector, so I cannot run it in Confluent Cloud - bummer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this post looks at the various options we have if we want to use the Kafka Connect Kusto Sink Connector connecting Confluent Cloud in Azure with Azure Data Explorer. However, if you are not interested in neither Kafka nor ADX, the post may still be of use for you. The reason being it also covers running Docker images in Azure Container Instances (ACI).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Confluent Cloud &amp; Serverless Apache Kafka on Azure</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-08-14-run-confluent-cloud--serverless-apache-kafka-on-azure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 12:58:24 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-08-14-run-confluent-cloud--serverless-apache-kafka-on-azure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For readers of my blog, it should not come as a surprise that I think Apache Kafka is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/the%20best%2Fgreatest%20thing%20since%20sliced%20bread&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;the greatest thing since sliced bread&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and I have written &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/categories/kafka/&#34;&gt;some posts&lt;/a&gt; about it. The posts I have written has been geared towards the setup/deployment of Kafka, with a Windows/.NET slant to it. This post is in the same vein; how to set up Kafka but in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;conference season&amp;rdquo; is upon us, and I have some conference talks coming up. This year quite a lot of what I am talking about is in the cloud, specifically Azure. As some of the talks involve Apache Kafka, I thought it would be good if Kafka also ran in the cloud. Sure, I could always run Kafka on Docker on a VM in the cloud, but &amp;ldquo;they&amp;rdquo; say serverless is the new &amp;ldquo;in&amp;rdquo; thing, as well as managed services, so why not try that out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this post is about how to deploy Confluent Cloud on Azure!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
