<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>O3 on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/o3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in O3 on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 08:30:15 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/o3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-06-22-interesting-stuff---week-25-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 08:30:15 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-06-22-interesting-stuff---week-25-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech landscape reveals a fascinating convergence: while HTAP databases officially die and give way to modular data stacks, OpenAI proves that PostgreSQL mastery can handle ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s massive scale with just one primary instance and dozens of replicas. Meanwhile, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Code Researcher demonstrates AI agents evolving from simple code completion to autonomous system-level debugging. At the same time, OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s O3 family introduces true reasoning models that think through problems rather than relying on pattern matching.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The meta-narrative emerging is clear: traditional engineering excellence is converging with AI-native approaches, while organisational dynamics continue to trump pure technical merit in enterprise adoption. From self-evolving agents that develop strategic planning autonomously to comprehensive frameworks democratising AI development, we&amp;rsquo;re witnessing the early stages of Software 3.0&amp;rsquo;s promised transformation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Xmas, New Year 2024, Week 1 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-01-05-interesting-stuff---xmas-new-year-2024-week-1-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 08:40:02 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-01-05-interesting-stuff---xmas-new-year-2024-week-1-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The tech landscape continues to evolve at lightning speed, and this roundup captures some of the most compelling developments in AI and data. From groundbreaking advancements in Proximal Policy Optimization to the rise of agentic workflows and transformative frameworks like aiXplain&amp;rsquo;s Multi-Agent Autonomous Framework, AI&amp;rsquo;s potential seems boundless.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Add to that the shrinking models, plummeting costs, and bold predictions for 2025, and it&amp;rsquo;s clear we&amp;rsquo;re witnessing a pivotal moment in tech innovation. Dive in to explore the trends shaping our future!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 51, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-12-22-interesting-stuff---week-51-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 07:49:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-12-22-interesting-stuff---week-51-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup dives into the latest AI, streaming, and cloud innovation breakthroughs. From OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s new o3 models and ChatGPT Projects feature to Kafka&amp;rsquo;s queue support and Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s AIOpsLab, these developments transform workflows, enhance scalability, and push the boundaries of AI reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whether it&amp;rsquo;s managing complex systems or tackling real-world challenges, the future of tech is brighter than ever. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore these exciting advancements together!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
