<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>F# on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/f#/</link>
    <description>Recent content in F# on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 14:23:33 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/f#/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 30</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-30-interesting-stuff---week-30/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 14:23:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-30-interesting-stuff---week-30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, etc., that has to do with things that interest me&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the posts that has been most interesting to me, for the week just gone by.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Impressions Microsoft BUILD - Win 8</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2011-09-13-first-impressions-microsoft-build-win-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2011-09-13-first-impressions-microsoft-build-win-8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a while ago just finished watching the live stream of the first keynote (yes there will be one tomorrow as well), at Microsoft BUILD. Having attended / presented, at quite a few of these kind of events - and being somewhat jaded (well OK then, a lot jaded), I must still say that I am impressed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F#, Mono and Mac - Take II</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-20-fsharp-mono-and-mac-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-20-fsharp-mono-and-mac-2/</guid>
      <description>So yesterday I wrote about how I have started using F# and Mono on my MacBook.&#xA;I wrote about how I downloaded the F# bits, unzipped and put them in a specific directory I had created. Today after having browsed around a bit more I realized I had done it the hard way. To install the required bits for F# for Mac, you only have to download a zip file with an install package for Mac from the F# Cross Platform site on CodePlex.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F#, Mono and Mac</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-19-fsharp-mono-and-mac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-19-fsharp-mono-and-mac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a first post about my experiences with running F# and Mono on a Mac.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-15-using-fsharp-in-sqlclr/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote about how I have started to play with F#. As that post also covered SQLCLR it was obvious I was on Windows. Even though I make my living from development in a Windows environment, my main machine is a MacBook, and I run OSX as my main OS. I have previously also been running Linux (ArchLinux) on this machine as my main OS. Naturally I have heard about Mono (and also installed it a couple of times - and quickly un-installed again, but I have not really done anything with it. I have always run Windows in a VM on my MacBook for development etc. However after the announcement that F# was going &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/dsyme/archive/2010/11/04/announcing-the-f-compiler-library-source-code-drop.aspx&#34;&gt;Open Source&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomasp.net/blog&#34;&gt;Tomas P&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomasp.net/blog/fsharp-in-monodevelop.aspx&#34;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about his F# MonoDevelop plug-in&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, I decided that I should have a look at what it would be like to do F# &amp;ldquo;stuff in OSX.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TPL Dataflow, Axum v.NEXT?</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-18-tpl-dataflow-axum-v-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-18-tpl-dataflow-axum-v-next/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At PDC 2010 Microsoft showed the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/async.aspx&#34;&gt;Async&lt;/a&gt; features of coming C# (and VB.NET) versions, and quite a lot has been written about it already. Part of the Async CTP is &lt;strong&gt;TPL Dataflow&lt;/strong&gt;, and this has gone somewhat un-noticed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using F# in SQLCLR</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-15-using-fsharp-in-sqlclr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-15-using-fsharp-in-sqlclr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I have become very interested in F# and I am at the moment trying to get to grips with it. It is definitely a different beast than C#, but so far I like it - a lot!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I am a SQL nerd, and many moons ago I was very heavily involved in SQLCLR (for you who don&amp;rsquo;t know what that is; it is the ability to run .NET code inside the SQL Server engine. It was first introduced with SQL Server 2005). So I thought it would be a &amp;ldquo;giggle&amp;rdquo; to see if I could get some F# code running inside SQL Server.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beginners F# Resources</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-13-beginners-fsharp-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-13-beginners-fsharp-resources/</guid>
      <description>This post is more as a reminder to myself where to find online resources when learning F#. If anyone else can find it useful, so much better. And, if anyone out there has other online, resources, please leave a comment and I will include it. So, in no particular order:&#xA;Introductory article by Luke Hoban in MSDN Magazine. An online book about F#. Tutorial, by Dejan Jelovic, about getting started with F# from a C# developers perspective.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
