<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>OLTP on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/oltp/</link>
    <description>Recent content in OLTP on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 09:43:48 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/oltp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 15, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-04-14-interesting-stuff---week-15-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 09:43:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-04-14-interesting-stuff---week-15-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup! Dive into the evolving world of databases with insights on scalable OLTP systems in the cloud and the debut of Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Garnet, a cutting-edge alternative to Redis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In AI advancements, explore how Databricks transforms data engineering with Large Language Models and how autonomous AI agents like those described by Andrew NG are reshaping our technology expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, get the latest on practical applications in finance and streaming technologies, and join us for the upcoming Data and AI Community Days for a firsthand experience of innovation in action.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 12, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-24-interesting-stuff---week-12-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 08:47:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-24-interesting-stuff---week-12-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s exploration dives into the transformative realms of tech, from the evolution of OLTP databases to meet growing transactional demands to the innovative &amp;ldquo;Self-Learning GPTs&amp;rdquo; that adapt and grow through user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also delve into Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s AutoDev, an AI-driven leap towards autonomous software development. We wrap up with highlights from Kafka Summit London 2024, where the fusion of data streaming platforms and Gen AI took the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
