<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Azure Data Studio on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/categories/azure-data-studio/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Azure Data Studio on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 12:06:09 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/azure-data-studio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019 for Linux in Docker on Windows</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/sql-server-2019-for-linux-in-docker-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 12:06:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/sql-server-2019-for-linux-in-docker-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By the time I publish this blog post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/ignite&#34;&gt;MS Ignite&lt;/a&gt; is over. During Ignite, Microsoft announced quite a few new things, amongst them &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2019&lt;/strong&gt; with a whole lot of new features and functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I touched briefly on some of them in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-09-24-sql-server-2019-public-preview/&#34;&gt;What is New in SQL Server 2019 Public Preview&lt;/a&gt; post. A couple of things that caught my eye were that &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2019 for Linux&lt;/strong&gt; now supports In-Database analytics, what we know as &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt; (R and Python), as well as the Java language extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; You may ask yourself what the Java language extension is; well, that is the ability to access Java code from T-SQL. It is a little bit like SQLCLR, but it executes outside of the SQL Server memory and process space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing that I never really have played around with &lt;em&gt;SQL Server for Linux&lt;/em&gt;, mostly due to that in previous versions (2017) it did not have support for In-Database analytics, I thought that now would be a good time to have a look.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
