<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Extended Events on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>/tags/extended-events/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Extended Events on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 08:06:46 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/extended-events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server Machine Learning Services and Extended Events</title>
      <link>/2018/04/08/sql-server-machine-learning-services-and-extended-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 08:06:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/08/sql-server-machine-learning-services-and-extended-events/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in the day when I started with the &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server R Services - Internals&lt;/strong&gt; posts, I thought I would use &lt;a href=&#34;https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/bb630354(v=sql.105).aspx&#34;&gt;SQL Server Extended Events&lt;/a&gt; (XEvents) to figure things out. I knew SQL Server and the extensibility architecture supported XEvents because I had come across &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/sql/advanced-analytics/r/extended-events-for-sql-server-r-services&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; documentation, where it (amongst other things) said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;SQL Server provides a set of extended events to use in troubleshooting operations related to the SQL Server Trusted Launchpad, as well as Python or R jobs sent to SQL Server.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the above, it is pretty clear that XEvents is the way to go when drilling down into how things &amp;ldquo;hang together&amp;rdquo;. However, how hard I tried, I could not make &amp;ldquo;head or tails&amp;rdquo; of how to get things to work (I should probably have tried harder), so in the end, I went the &lt;strong&gt;WinDbg&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;WireShark&lt;/strong&gt; route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward a year (and a bit) and someone asked a question on an internal forum about XEvents and &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt;, and I decided to look into it and to try to understand it a bit better. So this post is the result of me &lt;del&gt;playing around with&lt;/del&gt; researching XEvents and SQL Server Machine Learning Services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>