<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Azure Data Explorer on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/categories/azure-data-explorer/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Azure Data Explorer on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 17:08:46 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/azure-data-explorer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>One Billion Row Challenge &amp; Azure Data Explorer</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-28-one-billion-row-challenge--azure-data-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 17:08:46 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-28-one-billion-row-challenge--azure-data-explorer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 1st (that&amp;rsquo;s dedication - New Year&amp;rsquo;s Day), 2024 &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/gunnar-morling-2b44b7229/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gunnar Morling&lt;/a&gt; published on his blog the &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.morling.dev/blog/one-billion-row-challenge/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Billion Row Challenge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The challenge is to load and aggregate one billion rows using Java. The challenge took on a life of its own, and there are now several implementations of the challenge in different languages, including databases (&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rmoff.net/2024/01/03/1%EF%B8%8F%E2%83%A3%EF%B8%8F-1brc-in-sql-with-duckdb/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Robin&lt;/a&gt;, &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hubertdulay.substack.com/p/1-billion-row-challenge-in-apache&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hubert&lt;/a&gt;, &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ftisiot.net/posts/1brows/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Francesco&lt;/a&gt;, among others). The data to aggregate is a list of temperature readings from weather stations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I thought It would be fun to do the challenge using &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/data-explorer/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/a&gt; (ADX) since I like ADX and have written blog posts about it. ADX is a fast, scalable, and highly available data analytics service. It is optimized for data exploration over large data volumes. ADX is a columnar store that uses a query language called &lt;strong&gt;Kusto Query Language&lt;/strong&gt; (KQL). It is a fully managed service, and it is part of the Azure platform.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, in this blog post, you&amp;rsquo;ll see what I did to load and aggregate one billion rows. Spoiler alert: certain things didn&amp;rsquo;t work out as I had hoped, but that could be due to me being more rusty with ADX than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cross-Platform Compatibility Made Easy with Multi-Platform Docker Images: Azure Data Explorer Sink Connector &amp; Kafka Connect</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-04-17-cross-platform-compatibility-made-easy-with-multi-platform-docker-images-azure-data-explorer-sink-connector--kafka-connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 06:02:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-04-17-cross-platform-compatibility-made-easy-with-multi-platform-docker-images-azure-data-explorer-sink-connector--kafka-connect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you may know, I am working on a blog-post series, &lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;. As the title implies, Kafka ingests data into &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (ADX). This is done using the Azure Data Explorer Kusto Sink connector, where the connector runs in a JVM process in Kafka Connect. All this run in Docker containers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While writing (still writing) the fourth post in the series, I realised I had to create my own image for Kafka Connect and the Kusto Sink connector. You will find an explanation as to why below. Since I have partly gone over to the &amp;ldquo;dark side&amp;rdquo; (using Apple Silicon, ARM64), I thought it&amp;rsquo;d be nice if the image I created targeted both AMD64 and ARM64. I.e. I wanted to create a multi-platform image. In my usual style, I thought: &amp;ldquo;How hard can it be? What could possibly go wrong&amp;rdquo; &amp;#x1f604;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Well, it was a tad more difficult than I imagined, and in this post, I cover the steps I took to create my Kafka Connect and Kusto Sink connector image as a multi-platform Docker image. Oh, and if you are not interested in the Kusto Sink connector and Kafka Connect at all (you should be &amp;#x1f604;), don&amp;rsquo;t worry. The steps covered here work for any Docker Image you want to create as a multi-platform image.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - II</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-04-03-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 07:26:29 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-04-03-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled by the &amp;quot; - II&amp;quot; in the title, as this is the third post in the series about using Kafka and &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (ADX) to develop a real-time leaderboard for online gaming. This (&amp;quot; - II&amp;quot;) is because the &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/&#34;&gt;initial post&lt;/a&gt; was more of an intro, where I introduced a framework for generating and publishing events to Kafka. Posts in the series are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - Prelude&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - II&lt;/strong&gt; (this post)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; was all about ingesting data into ADX from Kafka. In this post, you will see more about ingesting data into ADX and some &amp;ldquo;cool stuff&amp;rdquo; related to that. Specifically, what to do if you need to update/transform the data you ingest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - I</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 07:49:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second post in a series about using Kafka and &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (ADX) to develop a real-time leaderboard for online gaming. Hmm, the second post you say - why is it that the post title says &amp;quot; - I&amp;quot;? Good question; that is because the &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/&#34;&gt;initial post&lt;/a&gt; was more of an intro, where I introduced a framework for generating and publishing events to Kafka. Posts in the series are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - Prelude&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - I&lt;/strong&gt; (this post)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-04-03-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---ii/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - II&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in this post, you will learn more about ADX and why it is an excellent choice for near real-time applications, how to &amp;ldquo;hook up&amp;rdquo; Kafka to ADX and how to ingest data into an ADX database.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - Prelude</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 09:40:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog post series is inspired by my conference talk &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/rA3iZlZ8YOw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyze Billions of Rows of Data in Real-Time Using Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Posts in the series are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - Prelude&lt;/strong&gt; (this post)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-04-03-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---ii/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - II&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the presentation, I talk about &amp;ldquo;user-facing&amp;rdquo; analytics. Historically analytics has been limited to a small set of users in an organization (think the C-suite, power users, etc.). User-facing analytics changes that and makes analytics available to the end-users. An example of &amp;ldquo;user-facing analytics&amp;rdquo; is LinkedIn&amp;rsquo;s: &amp;ldquo;Who&amp;rsquo;s viewed your profile&amp;rdquo;. Another example is leaderboards, which are popular in online gaming.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since I work for a company (&#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/derivco&#34;&gt;Derivco&lt;/a&gt;) that develops systems for the iGaming industry, this series looks at the basics of a real-time leaderboard for online gaming using Kafka and &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (ADX).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought one post would cover this, but I quickly realized one post covering everything would be way too long. Therefore, I am splitting this topic into multiple posts, and in this post, I look at Kafka and event generation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Arguably, this first post has little to do with ADX, which is why the title says &lt;strong&gt;Prelude&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#x1f604;. Still, it is important because it sets up the publishing mechanism, which can be reused for anything else you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Ingest Into Azure Data Explorer From Apache Kafka using Kafka Connect</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-10-27-how-to-ingest-into-azure-data-explorer-from-apache-kafka-using-kafka-connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 14:13:37 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-10-27-how-to-ingest-into-azure-data-explorer-from-apache-kafka-using-kafka-connect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you follow my blog, you probably know that I am a huge fan of &lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/strong&gt; and event streaming/stream processing. Recently &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;ADX&lt;/strong&gt;) has caught my eye. In fact, in the last few weeks, I did two conference sessions about ADX. A month ago, I published a blog post related to Kafka and ADX: &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-09-06-run-self-managed-kafka-connector-in-serverless-azure-container-instance/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run Self-Managed Kusto Kafka Connector Serverless in Azure Container Instances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the title of that post implies, it looked at the ADX Kafka sink connector and how to run it in Azure. What the post did not look at was how to configure the connector and connect it to ADX. That is what we will do in this post (and maybe in a couple of more posts).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Run Self-Managed Kusto Kafka Connector Serverless in Azure Container Instances</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-09-06-run-self-managed-kafka-connector-in-serverless-azure-container-instance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 06:11:51 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-09-06-run-self-managed-kafka-connector-in-serverless-azure-container-instance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-08-14-run-confluent-cloud--serverless-apache-kafka-on-azure/&#34;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; how I set up Kafka to run serverless in Azure by deploying Confluent Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you have followed my blog lately, you have probably seen that I am interested in &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; and that I have a couple of conference talks coming. One being:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to do Real-Time Analytics Using Apache Kafka and Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;: We are looking at how to stream events from Apache Kafka to Azure Data Explorer (ADX) and perform user-facing analytics in near real-time.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The question is how to connect Kafka with ADX? You normally connect Kafka with another system using a Kafka Connect connector, and fortunately a connector exists for connecting Kafka with ADX: the &#xA;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Azure/kafka-sink-azure-kusto&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kafka Connect Kusto Sink Connector&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, since I am running managed Kafka (Confluent Cloud, remember), I need a managed connector to run it in Confluent Cloud&amp;rsquo;s Kafka Connect. In the previous paragraph, I mentioned I was fortunate as we had a Kafka connector for ADX. Unfortunately, it is not a managed connector, so I cannot run it in Confluent Cloud - bummer!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, this post looks at the various options we have if we want to use the Kafka Connect Kusto Sink Connector connecting Confluent Cloud in Azure with Azure Data Explorer. However, if you are not interested in neither Kafka nor ADX, the post may still be of use for you. The reason being it also covers running Docker images in Azure Container Instances (ACI).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
