<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kusto on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/kusto/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kusto on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 07:49:50 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/kusto/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - I</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 07:49:50 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-19-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second post in a series about using Kafka and &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (ADX) to develop a real-time leaderboard for online gaming. Hmm, the second post you say - why is it that the post title says &amp;quot; - I&amp;quot;? Good question; that is because the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/&#34;&gt;initial post&lt;/a&gt; was more of an intro, where I introduced a framework for generating and publishing events to Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, in this post, you will learn more about ADX and why it is an excellent choice for near real-time applications, how to &amp;ldquo;hook up&amp;rdquo; Kafka to ADX and how to ingest data into an ADX database.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Develop a Real-Time Leaderboard Using Kafka and Azure Data Explorer - Prelude</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 09:40:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-02-26-develop-a-real-time-leaderboard-using-kafka-and-azure-data-explorer---prelude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog post series is inspired by my conference talk &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/rA3iZlZ8YOw&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyze Billions of Rows of Data in Real-Time Using Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the presentation, I talk about &amp;ldquo;user-facing&amp;rdquo; analytics. Historically analytics has been limited to a small set of users in an organization (think the C-suite, power users, etc.). User-facing analytics changes that and makes analytics available to the end-users. An example of &amp;ldquo;user-facing analytics&amp;rdquo; is LinkedIn&amp;rsquo;s: &amp;ldquo;Who&amp;rsquo;s viewed your profile&amp;rdquo;. Another example is leaderboards, which are popular in online gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I work for a company (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/derivco&#34;&gt;Derivco&lt;/a&gt;) that develops systems for the iGaming industry, this series looks at the basics of a real-time leaderboard for online gaming using Kafka and &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (ADX).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought one post would cover this, but I quickly realized one post covering everything would be way too long. Therefore, I am splitting this topic into multiple posts, and in this post, I look at Kafka and event generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguably, this first post has little to do with ADX, which is why the title says &lt;strong&gt;Prelude&lt;/strong&gt; 😄. Still, it is important because it sets up the publishing mechanism, which can be reused for anything else you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Ingest Into Azure Data Explorer From Apache Kafka using Kafka Connect</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-10-27-how-to-ingest-into-azure-data-explorer-from-apache-kafka-using-kafka-connect/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 14:13:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-10-27-how-to-ingest-into-azure-data-explorer-from-apache-kafka-using-kafka-connect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you follow my blog, you probably know that I am a huge fan of &lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/strong&gt; and event streaming/stream processing. Recently &lt;strong&gt;Azure Data Explorer&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;ADX&lt;/strong&gt;) has caught my eye. In fact, in the last few weeks, I did two conference sessions about ADX. A month ago, I published a blog post related to Kafka and ADX: &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2021-09-06-run-self-managed-kafka-connector-in-serverless-azure-container-instance/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run Self-Managed Kusto Kafka Connector Serverless in Azure Container Instances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the title of that post implies, it looked at the ADX Kafka sink connector and how to run it in Azure. What the post did not look at was how to configure the connector and connect it to ADX. That is what we will do in this post (and maybe in a couple of more posts).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
