<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Netflix on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/netflix/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Netflix on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 05:29:55 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/netflix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 40, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-05-interesting-stuff---week-40-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 05:29:55 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-05-interesting-stuff---week-40-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week brings a convergent narrative around AI-assisted development that&amp;rsquo;s impossible to ignore: from Netflix&amp;rsquo;s Write-Ahead Log solving data reliability at massive scale, to Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s Claude Sonnet 4.5 claiming the coding benchmark crown, to Armin Ronacher shipping production infrastructure that&amp;rsquo;s 90% AI-generated, and GitHub&amp;rsquo;s Tomas Vesely treating Markdown specs as source code with AI as the compiler. The throughline is clear: we&amp;rsquo;re witnessing a fundamental shift where experienced engineers are radically expanding what&amp;rsquo;s possible by delegating implementation to AI while jealously guarding architectural decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tooling from Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s MSSQL extension for VS Code provides the visual verification layers that make this workflow sustainable. The question is no longer whether AI will write most of our code, but whether we&amp;rsquo;re building the right guardrails and developing the right instincts to know which decisions must remain human. Meanwhile, with less than a week until &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aimldatadurban.org/events/2025/ready-player-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on October 11, we&amp;rsquo;re still urgently seeking a lunch sponsor to support our attendees, speakers, and community. If you know anyone interested in backing Durban&amp;rsquo;s tech community, please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
