<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Netflix on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/netflix/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Netflix on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 08:22:43 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/netflix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 43, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-26-interesting-stuff---week-43-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 08:22:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-26-interesting-stuff---week-43-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Week 43, 2025! This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup explores the cutting edge of AI-assisted development and streaming infrastructure, from Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s Claude Code for web revolutionising autonomous coding with smart sandboxing, to GitHub&amp;rsquo;s new MCP Registry bringing order to the AI tooling chaos.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also dive into Netflix&amp;rsquo;s engineering marvel that delivers real-time recommendations to over 100 million devices without melting their infrastructure. Plus, I&amp;rsquo;m excited to share my personal news: I&amp;rsquo;ve submitted talks to all three .NET Conf 2025 South Africa events, including the historic first-ever .NET Conf in Durban. The Call for Speakers is still open if you want to be part of this milestone moment for our developer community!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 42, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-19-interesting-stuff---week-42-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 09:09:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-19-interesting-stuff---week-42-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 42 delivers a masterclass in engineering honesty and AI accessibility that cuts through the usual tech hype. Netflix&amp;rsquo;s Adrian Taruc and James Dalton reveal how they built a Real-Time Distributed Graph processing system capable of handling 5 million records per second, candidly admitting their initial monolithic Flink job was an &amp;ldquo;operational headache&amp;rdquo; before pivoting to a more complex but maintainable architecture. Andrej Karpathy proves AI training doesn&amp;rsquo;t require enterprise budgets with nanochat. Training a GPT-2-calibre model in under four hours for approximately $92. GitHub&amp;rsquo;s Andrea Griffiths tackles the COBOL crisis, showing how AI agents can modernise 65-year-old mainframe systems without developers learning COBOL. Anthropic dominates with Claude Haiku 4.5 (frontier performance at one-third the cost) and Agent Skills, an elegantly simple filesystem-based approach to agent specialisation that treats domain expertise like employee onboarding through progressive disclosure and structured folders.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I found myself in Johannesburg delivering &lt;strong&gt;Generative AI for Beginners: Build Your First Agent with Azure AI Foundry&lt;/strong&gt; at the Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day event to an almost-full house. There&amp;rsquo;s no rest ahead, though, for the first time ever, &lt;strong&gt;.NET Conf South Africa Community Edition&lt;/strong&gt; is coming to Durban on November 15 at &lt;strong&gt;Richfield College&lt;/strong&gt;, and we&amp;rsquo;re actively seeking speakers with .NET, C#, Blazor, MAUI, ASP.NET Core, or Azure expertise to share with the KwaZulu-Natal developer community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 40, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-05-interesting-stuff---week-40-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 08:25:55 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-05-interesting-stuff---week-40-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week brings a convergent narrative around AI-assisted development that&amp;rsquo;s impossible to ignore: from Netflix&amp;rsquo;s Write-Ahead Log solving data reliability at massive scale, to Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s Claude Sonnet 4.5 claiming the coding benchmark crown, to Armin Ronacher shipping production infrastructure that&amp;rsquo;s 90% AI-generated, and GitHub&amp;rsquo;s Tomas Vesely treating Markdown specs as source code with AI as the compiler. The throughline is clear: we&amp;rsquo;re witnessing a fundamental shift where experienced engineers are radically expanding what&amp;rsquo;s possible by delegating implementation to AI while jealously guarding architectural decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tooling from Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s MSSQL extension for VS Code provides the visual verification layers that make this workflow sustainable. The question is no longer whether AI will write most of our code, but whether we&amp;rsquo;re building the right guardrails and developing the right instincts to know which decisions must remain human. Meanwhile, with less than a week until &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aimldatadurban.org/events/2025/ready-player-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on October 11, we&amp;rsquo;re still urgently seeking a lunch sponsor to support our attendees, speakers, and community. If you know anyone interested in backing Durban&amp;rsquo;s tech community, please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
