<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aimldatadurban on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/aimldatadurban/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Aimldatadurban on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 12:24:39 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/aimldatadurban/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 50, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-12-14-interesting-stuff---week-50-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 12:24:39 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-12-14-interesting-stuff---week-50-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week explores how AI agents are fundamentally transforming software development, from Hugging Face enabling Claude to orchestrate complete LLM fine-tuning workflows through natural language, to Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Agent Lightning adding reinforcement learning capabilities without code rewrites, and Every&amp;rsquo;s pioneering Compound Engineering methodology, where single developers now accomplish what once required entire teams.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also examine GitHub&amp;rsquo;s research, revealing how developers are evolving from &amp;ldquo;code producers&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;creative directors of code,&amp;rdquo; the Model Context Protocol&amp;rsquo;s transition to the Linux Foundation, and practical tutorials on building procedural memory agents. Plus, a special celebration of our triumphant Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban Year-End-Finale, where nearly 200 attendees gave exceptional ratings despite the festive season, now it&amp;rsquo;s time for well-deserved rest before 2026! 🎄&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 49, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-12-07-interesting-stuff---week-49-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 09:34:21 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-12-07-interesting-stuff---week-49-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout this week, I&amp;rsquo;ve been diving deep into the philosophical underpinnings of modern programming languages, discovering that Go, Rust, and Zig aren&amp;rsquo;t just different feature sets, but entirely different worldviews about how we should write software. The AI coding revolution continued its wild ride with Claude Opus 4.5 proving it&amp;rsquo;s the world&amp;rsquo;s smartest coding AI while simultaneously prompting developers to warn each other it &amp;ldquo;needs to calm down,&amp;rdquo; alongside practical insights into what actually stops beginners from adopting Claude Code (spoiler: it&amp;rsquo;s psychological, not technical).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I also got hands-on with Claude Code Desktop, which streamlines the AI coding experience beautifully when it&amp;rsquo;s not freezing your entire system. Plus, I discovered that building governable AI agents requires control-plane architectures that separate the exciting autonomy from the essential safety guardrails, because nobody wants their AI tutor going rogue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 48, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-30-interesting-stuff---week-48-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:19:04 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-30-interesting-stuff---week-48-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup showcases the infrastructure layer that&amp;rsquo;s transforming AI coding from impressive demos to genuinely trustworthy production tools. Tiger Data open-sourced &lt;code&gt;pg-aiguide&lt;/code&gt; to teach LLMs production-ready PostgreSQL, Anthropic released Claude Opus 4.5 with dramatic efficiency gains and frontier-level capabilities, researchers mapped the architectural gulf between shallow and deep AI agents, and Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s engineering team revealed how they solved long-running agent consistency by borrowing practices from effective software engineering teams.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I delivered my &lt;strong&gt;C# MCP Servers and Azure AI&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;** talk at the &lt;strong&gt;.NET Conf 2025 Johannesburg&lt;/strong&gt; yesterday (literally blowing attendees away in the windy outdoor venue!). We&amp;rsquo;re putting final touches on &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aimldatadurban.org/events/2025/season-of-ai-mcp/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban: Season of AI - Merry Christmas People (MCP)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on December 13, CfS closes today. We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few tickets left for what promises to be an epic Year-End Finale!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 47, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-23-interesting-stuff---week-47-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 05:29:19 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-23-interesting-stuff---week-47-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup explores the critical shift from vague AI assistants to specialised, instruction-driven agents that actually deliver value, covering everything from GitHub Copilot&amp;rsquo;s instruction file architecture to sophisticated memory systems that transform digital amnesia into persistent Intelligence. We dive deep into Apache Iceberg&amp;rsquo;s emergence as the open table format of choice for unified real-time and batch analytics, examining why the appealing &amp;ldquo;Zero Copy&amp;rdquo; dream of streaming Kafka topics directly into lakehouse tables often backfires in production.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Generative AI section examines Google&amp;rsquo;s competitive panic mode as Gemini 3.0 Pro accelerates toward release, reveals how proper memory architectures enable AI agents to learn and adapt across sessions, and dissects why effective agents need operating manuals rather than mission statements. Plus, I share updates from .NET Conf Cape Town and details about our final &lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban&lt;/strong&gt; event of 2025, complete with a holiday-themed MCP deep-dive that&amp;rsquo;s opening registrations today (grab your tickets before they disappear faster than free pizza at a developer meetup!).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 46, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-16-interesting-stuff---week-46-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 12:53:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-16-interesting-stuff---week-46-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup explores the foundational research papers that transformed AI from an academic curiosity into production-ready technology, covering everything from the revolutionary Transformer architecture to the Model Context Protocol, which enables standardised tool integration. We examine critical performance optimisation techniques for Azure OpenAI deployments, where asynchronous programming delivers 11x speed improvements by parallelising tasks instead of processing them sequentially.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The spotlight then shifts to a paradigm-challenging analysis of why small language models with fewer than 10 billion parameters are proving architecturally superior for agentic AI systems, potentially delivering 30 times the cost savings while matching the performance of their trillion-parameter cousins on specialised tasks. Finally, I share updates from the successful .NET Conf 2025 Durban event and preview the upcoming roadshow, which will visit Cape Town and Johannesburg, where I&amp;rsquo;ll explore Model Context Protocol integration with C# and Azure AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 45, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-09-interesting-stuff---week-45-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 06:02:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-09-interesting-stuff---week-45-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup tackles the critical infrastructure challenges emerging as AI agents reshape software development, from Claude Code&amp;rsquo;s advanced orchestration strategies and the hidden costs of 10x coding velocity to Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s breakthrough 98% token reduction through code execution with MCP. Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Magentic Marketplace simulation exposes troubling vulnerabilities in agentic markets, revealing that even state-of-the-art models struggle with the &amp;ldquo;Paradox of Choice&amp;rdquo; and manipulation resistance when operating at scale.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;m deep in prep mode for &lt;strong&gt;Durban&amp;rsquo;s first-ever .NET Conf on November 15&lt;/strong&gt; at Richfield College Umhlanga Campus, a milestone event proving our city can host world-class developer conferences, while simultaneously planning &lt;strong&gt;December 13&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban: Season of AI - Merry Christmas People (MCP)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ll unwrap the latest in Model Context Protocol and agentic AI development with festive flair. The convergence of production-ready AI coding tools and the need for radically rethought development infrastructure has never been more apparent, and this week&amp;rsquo;s posts chart the path forward with unusual clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
