<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aimldatadurban on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/aimldatadurban/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Aimldatadurban on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 06:02:18 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/aimldatadurban/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 45, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-09-interesting-stuff---week-45-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 06:02:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-09-interesting-stuff---week-45-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup tackles the critical infrastructure challenges emerging as AI agents reshape software development, from Claude Code&amp;rsquo;s advanced orchestration strategies and the hidden costs of 10x coding velocity to Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s breakthrough 98% token reduction through code execution with MCP. Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Magentic Marketplace simulation exposes troubling vulnerabilities in agentic markets, revealing that even state-of-the-art models struggle with the &amp;ldquo;Paradox of Choice&amp;rdquo; and manipulation resistance when operating at scale.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;m deep in prep mode for &lt;strong&gt;Durban&amp;rsquo;s first-ever .NET Conf on November 15&lt;/strong&gt; at Richfield College Umhlanga Campus, a milestone event proving our city can host world-class developer conferences, while simultaneously planning &lt;strong&gt;December 13&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban: Season of AI - Merry Christmas People (MCP)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ll unwrap the latest in Model Context Protocol and agentic AI development with festive flair. The convergence of production-ready AI coding tools and the need for radically rethought development infrastructure has never been more apparent, and this week&amp;rsquo;s posts chart the path forward with unusual clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
