<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Create External Library on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>/tags/create-external-library/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Create External Library on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2019 11:15:19 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/create-external-library/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing R Packages in SQL Server Machine Learning Services - IV: Permissions</title>
      <link>/2019/04/21/installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---iv-permissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2019 11:15:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/21/installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---iv-permissions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the fourth in a series about installing R packages in &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt; (SQL Server ML Services). To see all posts in the series go to &lt;a href=&#34;/sql_server_ml_services_install_packages&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install R Packages in SQL Server ML Services Series&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why this series came about is a colleague of mine &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dane-bax/&#34;&gt;Dane&lt;/a&gt; pinged me and asked if I had any advice as he had issues installing an R package into one of their SQL Server instances. I tried to help him and then thought it would make a good topic for a blog post. Of course, at that time I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it would be more posts than one, but here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we look at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What permissions &lt;code&gt;CREATE EXTERNAL LIBRARY&lt;/code&gt; requires.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to create external libraries with different owners and what impact it has.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing R Packages in SQL Server Machine Learning Services - III</title>
      <link>/2019/04/10/installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 06:36:16 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/04/10/installing-r-packages-in-sql-server-machine-learning-services---iii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the third in a series about installing R packages in &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server Machine Learning Services&lt;/strong&gt; (SQL Server ML Services). To see all posts in the series go to &lt;a href=&#34;/sql_server_ml_services_install_packages&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Install R Packages in SQL Server ML Services Series&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why this series came about is a colleague of mine &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/dane-bax/&#34;&gt;Dane&lt;/a&gt; pinged me and asked if I had any advice as he had issues installing an R package into one of their SQL Server instances. I tried to help him and then thought it would make a good topic for a blog post. Of course, at that time I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it would be more posts than one, but here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we look at how we can use T-SQL and DDL commands to install packages in a remote SQL Server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019, Java &amp; External Libraries - II</title>
      <link>/2019/03/17/sql-server-2019-java--external-libraries---ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 17:13:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/17/sql-server-2019-java--external-libraries---ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is part of the &lt;a href=&#34;/s2k19_ext_framework_java&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp;amp; Java&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; series of posts, and it is the second post discussing SQL Server 2019, Java and the creation and use of external libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post about external libraries, we said that they were beneficial as they reduced complexities when deploying code, but there were still some caveats. So, in this post, we look at how to overcome those caveats&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2019, Java &amp; External Libraries - I</title>
      <link>/2019/03/10/sql-server-2019-java--external-libraries---i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 10:22:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/03/10/sql-server-2019-java--external-libraries---i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago I wrote a series of posts about one of the new features in SQL Server 2019; the ability to call out to Java code from inside SQL Server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see the posts, go to &lt;a href=&#34;/s2k19_ext_framework_java&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQL Server 2019 Extensibility Framework &amp;amp; Java&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the posts, we discussed how the Java extension differs from R and Python in that R and Python are an integrated part of the SQL Server install (when enabling in-database analytics), but Java is not. In other words, the use of the Java extension requires Java to be installed beforehand, and this then has implications on permissions. We also discussed how Java is a compiled language, and we execute against a method in a class, whereas with R and Python we send a script to the external engine. The consequence of this is that when we execute Java code, we need to indicate where the compiled code resides, and those locations need specific permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this creates a level of complexity, and it would potentially be easier if we load the Java code from a well-known place, where we do not need to worry about permissions and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the first of a couple where we see how new functionality in SQL Server 2019 CTP 2.3 can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>