<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Streaming on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/streaming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Streaming on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 07:49:43 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/streaming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 51, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-12-22-interesting-stuff---week-51-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2024 07:49:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-12-22-interesting-stuff---week-51-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup dives into the latest AI, streaming, and cloud innovation breakthroughs. From OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s new o3 models and ChatGPT Projects feature to Kafka&amp;rsquo;s queue support and Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s AIOpsLab, these developments transform workflows, enhance scalability, and push the boundaries of AI reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whether it&amp;rsquo;s managing complex systems or tackling real-world challenges, the future of tech is brighter than ever. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore these exciting advancements together!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 49, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-12-08-interesting-stuff---week-49-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 07:57:05 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-12-08-interesting-stuff---week-49-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup dives into groundbreaking innovations shaping the future of AI and data. From SQL Server 2025&amp;rsquo;s AI-ready capabilities transforming databases to LangChain and Large Action Models redefining application development and decision-making, the possibilities are limitless.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Explore hybrid strategies for optimizing LLM performance and seamlessly integrating real-time intelligence with proactive agents. These advancements highlight how technology continues to empower creativity and efficiency in unprecedented ways!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 44, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-11-03-interesting-stuff---week-44-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2024 11:42:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-11-03-interesting-stuff---week-44-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup dives into the latest in Generative AI, streaming tech, and the revival of intelligent agents. From Indrajit Kar&amp;rsquo;s advanced multi-agent Q&amp;amp;A systems and GitHub Universe&amp;rsquo;s AI-powered tools to Hamel Husain&amp;rsquo;s guide on building LLM judges, it&amp;rsquo;s all about pushing boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, discover how to transform PDFs into podcasts and why SlateDB might just be the next big thing in stream processing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 43, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-10-27-interesting-stuff---week-43-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 08:12:57 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-10-27-interesting-stuff---week-43-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup, I explore the latest advancements in AI-ML, Generative AI, and Streaming. From mastering contextual bandits for real-time personalization to the evolving challenges of the Transformer architecture, these posts provide deep insights into AI&amp;rsquo;s growing impact.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I also discuss the practicalities of building LLMs with simple math and the debate between Apache Kafka, Azure Event Hubs, and Confluent Cloud for cloud-based data ecosystems. Let&amp;rsquo;s get started!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 42, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-10-20-interesting-stuff---week-42-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 09:35:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-10-20-interesting-stuff---week-42-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup dives into exciting developments in AI and streaming technology. From Actionable AI, where systems move from passive language models to action-driven capabilities, to OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s new Swarm paradigm, which enables AI agents to collaborate like a hive mind.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, we continue the deep dive into Kafka internals, focusing on how it optimizes data-fetching for real-time streams. Get ready to explore how these advancements are shaping the future of tech!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 39, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-09-29-interesting-stuff---week-39-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2024 09:46:52 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-09-29-interesting-stuff---week-39-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup, where we explore groundbreaking innovations shaping the industry! Discover insights into RAG AI agents and their future implications; look at Hamza Farooq&amp;rsquo;s hands-on approach to building custom AI agents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Learn how Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s RD-Agent is transforming research and development processes. We&amp;rsquo;ll also highlight the exciting features in RisingWave v2.0 and the merging of streaming platforms with Lakehouse architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 36, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-09-08-interesting-stuff---week-36-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 08:09:06 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-09-08-interesting-stuff---week-36-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week’s blog dives into some of the most exciting tech advancements in generative AI and real-time data streaming. From Google DeepMind’s GameNGen, which simulates DOOM in real-time, to a scalable multi-agent framework for decision-making in large systems, these developments are pushing the boundaries of AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I also explore innovative approaches to Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) using Flink and Kafka, along with clustering techniques to improve chunking in RAG systems. Dive in to see how these technologies are shaping the future!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 33, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-08-18-interesting-stuff---week-33-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 09:37:29 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-08-18-interesting-stuff---week-33-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup explores groundbreaking developments in AI and data streaming. From the innovative MindSearch framework that enhances AI-driven web searches to the evolution of SQL Generator 2.0, which simplifies complex database queries, these advancements are pushing the boundaries of technology.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also dive into the rapidly growing concept of &lt;strong&gt;Multi-Agent-as-a-Service&lt;/strong&gt; and highlight the must-attend &lt;strong&gt;Current 2024&lt;/strong&gt; event for data streaming professionals. Plus, a quick update on my upcoming presentations at the &lt;strong&gt;Season of AI&lt;/strong&gt; events in Cape Town and Johannesburg!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 30, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-07-28-interesting-stuff---week-30-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 12:59:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-07-28-interesting-stuff---week-30-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🚀 This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup covers Netflix&amp;rsquo;s innovative Maestro workflow orchestrator, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s advancements in self-adapting AI agents, and a hands-on guide to building streaming AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also explore TaskGen&amp;rsquo;s AI-driven task automation and the latest enhancements in real-time data streaming from Microsoft Fabric and Confluent Cloud. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss my prep for an upcoming presentation on Generative AI in Johannesburg!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 28, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-07-14-interesting-stuff---week-28-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2024 12:28:44 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-07-14-interesting-stuff---week-28-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup delves into the latest advancements in Generative AI and Streaming technologies. Explore seamless graph construction with Neo4j and LangChain, the revolutionary potential of synthetic data for LLM training, and the power of in-memory analytics with DuckDB and Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, get insights into building robust full-stack applications and scalable notification systems. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss the exciting updates on the upcoming &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aimldatadurban.org/events/2024/season-of-ai-1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban: Season of AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; event!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 24, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-06-16-interesting-stuff---week-24-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 09:38:32 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-06-16-interesting-stuff---week-24-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, dive into the latest tech innovations, including OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s official .NET library release and its integration with Apple devices, enhancing user experiences with advanced AI capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Learn from Andrew Ng&amp;rsquo;s new course on building AI assistants and explore the power of data streaming for customer loyalty programs. Check out updates on the upcoming Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban: Season of AI, where speaker selections are underway. Secure your spot now and be part of the excitement! 🚀&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 23, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-06-09-interesting-stuff---week-23-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 09:57:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-06-09-interesting-stuff---week-23-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup delves into Netflix&amp;rsquo;s advanced use of causal inference for data-driven decision-making, the efficiency of small language models over larger counterparts, and the importance of dynamic prompting for domain adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we explore the Generative AI Handbook for learning resources and best practices for reliable GenAI apps. Lastly, discover how to integrate Flink SQL, Streamlit, and Kafka for real-time data applications. Dive into these insights to stay ahead in the tech landscape!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 22, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-06-02-interesting-stuff---week-22-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 08:36:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-06-02-interesting-stuff---week-22-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🚀 This week in tech news: Discover KQL&amp;rsquo;s new capabilities in Azure Data Explorer, empowering data management with update and delete statements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Explore FinRobot, an open-source AI platform for financial tasks, and Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s synthetic data techniques ensuring AI privacy. Learn how RAG, Kafka, and Flink reduce AI hallucinations with real-time data.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, dive into Confluent&amp;rsquo;s best practices for Terraform and solutions to the dual-write problem, plus exciting updates for the upcoming Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban! 🌟&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-05-19-interesting-stuff---week-20-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 07:40:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-05-19-interesting-stuff---week-20-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post, I dive into the exciting advancements in Generative AI and Streaming Databases. Discover the transformative potential of LLM-based SQL agents for SAP HANA, the impressive capabilities of OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s GPT-4o, and the seamless integration of LangChain with Azure Container Apps.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Learn how venture capital firms leverage GenAI with Databricks and explore the latest enhancements in ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s data analysis. Finally, understand the revolutionary impact of streaming databases in handling real-time data across various industries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 18, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-05-05-interesting-stuff---week-18-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 15:19:44 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-05-05-interesting-stuff---week-18-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🚀 Dive into this week&amp;rsquo;s tech highlights! From GitHub&amp;rsquo;s game-changing Copilot Workspace to Confluent Cloud&amp;rsquo;s revolutionary Freight Clusters, discover how cutting-edge advancements in Generative AI and streaming are shaping the future of technology.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, get a sneak peek into the upcoming Season of AI event, promising a day filled with AI, Data, ML, and more! Don&amp;rsquo;t miss out on the latest innovations driving the tech landscape forward. 💡🌐&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 13, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-31-interesting-stuff---week-13-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 08:31:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-31-interesting-stuff---week-13-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s blog post delves into the latest advancements in Generative AI and data streaming, spotlighting transformative frameworks like LlamaFactory and Mora, and groundbreaking tools such as DBRX and Apache Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We explore Andrew Ng&amp;rsquo;s insights on the potential of agentic workflows and the strategic shifts revealed at Kafka Summit 2024. Plus, a sneak peek into the upcoming Data and AI Community Day in Durban, promising a day packed with learning and networking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 12, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-24-interesting-stuff---week-12-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 08:47:07 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-24-interesting-stuff---week-12-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s exploration dives into the transformative realms of tech, from the evolution of OLTP databases to meet growing transactional demands to the innovative &amp;ldquo;Self-Learning GPTs&amp;rdquo; that adapt and grow through user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also delve into Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s AutoDev, an AI-driven leap towards autonomous software development. We wrap up with highlights from Kafka Summit London 2024, where the fusion of data streaming platforms and Gen AI took the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 10, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-10-interesting-stuff---week-10-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 13:54:27 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-03-10-interesting-stuff---week-10-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s blog post delves into the fascinating world of Generative AI and Streaming, showcasing innovations like SalesGPT&amp;rsquo;s transformative sales conversations, the future of coding with Multi-Agent LLM Frameworks, and the intricacies of real-time sentiment analysis in Yelp reviews.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We also spotlight Uber&amp;rsquo;s journey to scaling real-time chat for improved customer service. Plus, exciting news for the local tech community: the Data and AI Community Day Durban is on the horizon, promising a day filled with insightful sessions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 07, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-02-18-interesting-stuff---week-07-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 14:12:38 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-02-18-interesting-stuff---week-07-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s blog takes you on an exhilarating journey through the latest in Generative AI and Streaming Data Mesh, showcasing groundbreaking advancements from the practical insights of LLMs with &lt;code&gt;llama.cpp&lt;/code&gt; to the innovative Functionary model.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We delve into how GraphRAG transforms document analysis and how SORA reshapes text-to-video creativity. Plus, get a glimpse into the transformative world of Streaming Data Mesh with Kafka &amp;amp; RisingWave,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, join me at the &lt;strong&gt;Global Power Platform Bootcamp 2024&lt;/strong&gt; for a deep dive into Microsoft Copilot Studio and the wonders of Generative AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 06, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-02-11-interesting-stuff---week-06-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 08:27:29 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-02-11-interesting-stuff---week-06-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s blog post delves into the fascinating realms of data architecture, generative AI, and streaming systems. I explore James Serra&amp;rsquo;s insightful book on navigating complex data architectures.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the GenAI space I look at Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s groundbreaking AI Controller Interface for enhancing LLM control. Finally Neil Avery&amp;rsquo;s compelling take on the synergy between Data Mesh and Hexagonal Architecture using Kafka. I hope you find these articles as intriguing as I did. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 04, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-28-interesting-stuff---week-04-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 10:07:51 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-28-interesting-stuff---week-04-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s blog post is a whirlwind tour through the latest in tech innovation, from the seamless integration of C# and Python for text-to-speech applications to the collaborative power of AI with platforms like CrewAI.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll explore cutting-edge frameworks for building AI teams and delve into the architectural blueprints for enterprise chat applications using Azure OpenAI.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, get an insider&amp;rsquo;s look at how Confluent leverages its own platform for real-time alerting, setting new standards in data streaming and operational agility. Join me!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 02, 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-14-interesting-stuff---week-02-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 07:13:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-14-interesting-stuff---week-02-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s blog post is a journey through the latest advancements in Generative AI and Streaming Technologies. We explore the transformative integration of Ray Autoscaling with Databricks and Apache Spark, a game-changer in scaling AI and Python workloads efficiently. The post also delves into the innovative use of GPT-4&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Custom Instructions&amp;rdquo; for enhancing Python code creation, showcasing its potential in data visualization.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the streaming domain, we highlight Confluent&amp;rsquo;s strides in trade settlements with the T+1 industry regulation, and the remarkable performance leap of Confluent Cloud&amp;rsquo;s Kora engine, now 10x faster than Apache Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Xmas, New Year 2023, Week 1 2024</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-07-interesting-stuff---xmas-new-year-2023-week-1-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 09:38:19 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2024-01-07-interesting-stuff---xmas-new-year-2023-week-1-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this week&amp;rsquo;s whirlwind of tech discoveries! From the art of crafting impactful tutorials to the innovative depths of databases and generative AI, we&amp;rsquo;re diving deep into the realms of technical clarity, database robustness, and AI&amp;rsquo;s potential.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, explore the transformative collaboration between RisingWave and MindsDB for real-time ML solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 48, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-12-03-interesting-stuff---week-48-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2023 11:02:06 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-12-03-interesting-stuff---week-48-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post where we delve into the fascinating realms of Generative AI and Data Streaming! 🌟&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Explore the transformative power of coding assistants like GitHub Copilot and ChatGPT, learn how to create your own Custom GPT model, and uncover the innovative approach of Programming with Representations (PwR).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dive into the world of data streaming with insights on librdkafka for Apache Kafka and the intriguing intersection of physics and data science in stream processing. Plus, get a glimpse of my recent experience at the .NET Conf 2023 in Johannesburg, where I shared insights on Kafka for .NET Developers. 🚀💻&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 47, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-11-26-interesting-stuff---week-47-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2023 13:37:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-11-26-interesting-stuff---week-47-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dive into a week of tech discoveries! From Martin Fowler&amp;rsquo;s indispensable guide to effective distributed systems to the future of gaming with real-time generative AI, there&amp;rsquo;s a wealth of knowledge waiting for you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Explore Sam Altman&amp;rsquo;s return as OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s CEO, shaping the AI landscape, and the game-changing partnership between Confluent and Ably for seamless Kafka integration.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Join me on this tech journey as I share my recent experiences presenting at the .NET Conference and look ahead to future adventures. Stay tuned for a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of captivating tech tales!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 45, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-11-12-interesting-stuff---week-45-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 10:00:11 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-11-12-interesting-stuff---week-45-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post, I delve into the fascinating world of Generative AI and Streaming technologies, sharing key insights and developments. We explore the complexities and innovations in building data pipelines for Large Language Models (LLMs), and the transformative role of Apache Kafka, Flink, and Vector Databases in real-time AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I reflect on the resounding success of the recent AI/ML &amp;amp; Data Infusion Roadshow in Durban, highlighting the enthusiastic response from attendees and the insightful contributions of our expert speakers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 44, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-11-05-interesting-stuff---week-44-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 09:31:45 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-11-05-interesting-stuff---week-44-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week we&amp;rsquo;re diving into the exciting world of Generative AI and Real-time Data Streaming.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Discover how Generative AI is reshaping the gaming landscape with personalized experiences and explore the fascinating landscape of Large Language Model (LLM) applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll also introduce you to NExT-GPT, a revolutionary multimodal model. Plus, don&amp;rsquo;t miss the future of business analytics with AI and Confluent Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally get a sneak peek into the upcoming AI/ML &amp;amp; Data Infusion Roadshow Durban. Get set for a tech adventure like no other!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 39, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-10-01-interesting-stuff---week-39-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 11:51:10 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-10-01-interesting-stuff---week-39-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Get ready for an exciting week in the world of data streaming! In this week&amp;rsquo;s blog, we&amp;rsquo;ll dive into the highlights from the recent Current 2023 conference, including the buzzworthy Confluent Cloud-Flink integration. Plus, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the game-changing addition of Apache Flink on Confluent Cloud and Confluent&amp;rsquo;s new initiative, &lt;strong&gt;Data Streaming for AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, let&amp;rsquo;s rewind to my recent adventure at Data Saturday Cape Town, and get a sneak peek at the upcoming &lt;strong&gt;AI/ML &amp;amp; Data Infusion Roadshow Durban&lt;/strong&gt; event. Stay tuned for some thrilling updates! 🚀&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 34, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-27-interesting-stuff---week-34-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 11:19:46 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-27-interesting-stuff---week-34-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embark on an exhilarating journey through this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post, where we unravel the latest frontiers in AI, GenerativeAI, and real-time data streaming. Uncover the dynamic world of Reinforcement Learning as agents master complex tasks through trial and error while demystifying the distinctions between AI, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, and Neural Networks.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Delve into the pursuit of Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) and its potential to reshape the future alongside the transformative impact of ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s human-AI interactions. Beyond AI, explore the revolutionary Streaming Plane, bridging real-time analytics and historical insights. From AGI&amp;rsquo;s challenges to the Streaming Plane&amp;rsquo;s promise, this week&amp;rsquo;s insights will ignite your tech curiosity. 🚀🤖🌐&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 33, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-20-interesting-stuff---week-33-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 16:43:46 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-20-interesting-stuff---week-33-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🚀 In this post: Unveil AI/ML marvels and streaming sensations! Python Vector Databases, Real-Time ML, Apache Flink, Confluent Platform, and more.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, relive the record-breaking Data Saturday Durban event! Join the innovation journey.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 32, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-13-interesting-stuff---week-32-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 09:32:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-08-13-interesting-stuff---week-32-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;🔍 In this week&amp;rsquo;s roundup: Discover the power of Big Data&amp;rsquo;s serving layers in James Serra&amp;rsquo;s post, unveiling the benefits of relational and physical layers for data accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;🚀 Speculate on the groundbreaking potential of OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s trademarked GPT-5, reshaping the AI landscape. 🌊 Stay ahead in the streaming world with Hubert&amp;rsquo;s newsletter, spotlighting rising stars like Redpanda and must-read Flink insights.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Join Niels at Data Saturday Durban for an Azure OpenAI deep-dive and seize the opportunity to learn from top speakers. Don&amp;rsquo;t miss out!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 28, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-16-interesting-stuff---week-28-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 07:24:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-16-interesting-stuff---week-28-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post, we dive into some exciting developments in the tech world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, we explore the Kusto Detective Academy, a valuable resource for mastering the Kusto Query Language (KQL) in Azure Data Explorer. Then, we discover GPT4Readability, a new tool powered by advanced language models like GPT-3.5 and GPT-4, designed to simplify the process of writing documentation and README files.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we delve into the integration of Kafka, Debezium, and BentoML to build a machine-learning streaming pipeline and a preview of a stream processing performance report comparing Apache Flink with RisingWave.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we get a glimpse into the upcoming Data Saturday Durban event and the intriguing topics under consideration. If you want to expand your knowledge and meet industry experts, don&amp;rsquo;t miss out on this exciting opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 27, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-09-interesting-stuff---week-27-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 13:05:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-09-interesting-stuff---week-27-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Unveil captivating discoveries: Explore vector databases, Azure OpenAI updates, generative AI insights, streaming trends, and more!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Join me on this knowledge-packed journey, filled with innovation and community contributions. Fuel your curiosity and read the full post now!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 26, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-02-interesting-stuff---week-26-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 11:48:53 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-07-02-interesting-stuff---week-26-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve got everything from data pipelines to streaming platforms in this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post: Hoptimator, the tool designed to streamline and optimize data pipelines. Mobile Premier League (MPL) and how they reduced player churn using Confluent Cloud. Materialized views and streaming tables for Databricks SQL.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;Data Saturday Durban&lt;/strong&gt; on August 19. It is still time to submit a talk.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-06-26-interesting-stuff---week-25-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 07:17:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-06-26-interesting-stuff---week-25-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You who read my blog are probably used to how the &amp;ldquo;Interesting Stuff&amp;rdquo; posts are published on a Sunday. This week, however, I am a bit late. I have been busy with other things (travelling) and have not had time to write this post until now.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, some of the &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; I cover this week is Microsoft Fabric, some cool AI/ML and LLM (Large Language Model) things.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is a very interesting article on the real-time streaming ecosystem by &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/hkdulay/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hubert Dulay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 20, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-05-21-interesting-stuff---week-20-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2023 09:35:25 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-05-21-interesting-stuff---week-20-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s post, I will share with you some of the most interesting and relevant articles I have read this week on various topics related to data and streaming. You will find links to:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The latest research developments in reinforcement learning and how they can be applied to different domains and challenges.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The real-time streaming ecosystem and how to design and implement a streaming solution using various tools and technologies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The performance and latency improvements of Apache Spark Structured Streaming and how they enable more use cases for real-time data processing.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The highlights of Kafka Summit 2023, the largest conference for Apache Kafka users and enthusiasts, and the new features and announcements from Confluent, the leading provider of Kafka solutions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Saturday&lt;/strong&gt; in Johannesburg in August and planning for the upcoming &lt;strong&gt;Data Saturday - Durban&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about these topics and want to stay updated on the latest trends and innovations in the data and streaming world, read on!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 10, 2023</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-12-interesting-stuff---week-10-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 08:33:19 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2023-03-12-interesting-stuff---week-10-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week only streaming topics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You see an excellent introduction to Apache Flink, followed by more Flink. In this case, it is related to Confluent&amp;rsquo;s acquisition of Immerok and how this has the potential of &amp;ldquo;shaking&amp;rdquo; up the stream processing market.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I finish off with a link to a post looking at the benefits of event streaming. Quite interesting!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 40, 2022</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-10-09-interesting-stuff---week-40-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2022 09:09:35 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-10-09-interesting-stuff---week-40-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth that has to do with things that interest me:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;AI/data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data architecture&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;streaming&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This blog post is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me for the week just ending.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Stream Data to Event Hubs from Databases Using Kafka Connect &amp; Debezium in Docker - II</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-14-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 05:25:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-14-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a two-post series, this second post looks at streaming data from a database to &lt;strong&gt;Azure Event Hubs&lt;/strong&gt; using Kafka Connect and Debezium, where Kafka Connect and Debezium run in Docker.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first post:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-10-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---i/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Stream Data to Event Hubs from Databases Using Kafka Connect &amp;amp; Debezium in Docker - I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This post mainly looks at the configuration of Kafka Connect&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file to allow us to connect to Event Hubs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This series came about as I in the post &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-02-how-to-use-kafka-client-with-azure-event-hubs/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Use Kafka Client with Azure Event Hubs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, somewhat foolishly said:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An interesting point here is that it is not only your Kafka applications that can publish to Event Hubs but any application that uses Kafka Client 1.0+, like Kafka Connect connectors!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I wrote the above without testing it myself, so when I was called out on it, I started researching (read &amp;ldquo;Googling&amp;rdquo;) to see if it was possible. The result of the &amp;ldquo;Googling&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t give a 100% answer, so I decided to try it out, and this series is the result.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-10-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---i/&#34;&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;, - as mentioned - we configured Kafka Connect to connect into Event Hubs. In this post, we look at configuring the Debezium connector.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Stream Data to Event Hubs from Databases Using Kafka Connect &amp; Debezium in Docker - I</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-10-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---i/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 19:05:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-10-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the first of two looking at if and how we can stream data to Event Hubs from Debezium. Initially I had planned only one post covering this, but it turned out that the post would be too long, so therefore I split it in two.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The second post in the series is:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-14-how-to-stream-data-to-event-hubs-from-databases-using-kafka-connect--debezium-in-docker---ii/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Stream Data to Event Hubs from Databases Using Kafka Connect &amp;amp; Debezium in Docker - II&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Here we look at the Debezium connector configuration needed if we want to stream data to Event Hubs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It started with the post, &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2022-01-02-how-to-use-kafka-client-with-azure-event-hubs/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Use Kafka Client with Azure Event Hubs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In that post, I looked at how the Kafka client can publish messages to - not only - &lt;strong&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/strong&gt; but also &lt;strong&gt;Azure Event Hubs&lt;/strong&gt;. In the post, I said something like:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;An interesting point here is that it is not only your Kafka applications that can publish to Event Hubs but any application that uses Kafka Client 1.0+, like Kafka Connect connectors!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Obviously, for you who know me, I said that without having tested it properly, but: &lt;em&gt;how hard can it be? What could possibly go wrong?&lt;/em&gt;. Well, I was called upon it by a guy who had read the post. He told me he had tried what I said at one time or the other, and it hadn&amp;rsquo;t worked.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this post (the first), we look at configuring Kafka Connect to connect to Event Hubs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 8, 2019</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2019-02-24-interesting-stuff---week-8-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 10:08:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2019-02-24-interesting-stuff---week-8-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, and so forth, that has to do with things that interest me:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This blog-post is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the things that have been most interesting to me, for the week just ending.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Install Confluent Platform (Kafka) on Windows</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-07-10-install-confluent-platform-kafka-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 18:43:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-07-10-install-confluent-platform-kafka-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You who follows my blog and have read my weekly roundups you know that I am quite (that is an understatement) interested in Apache Kafka and I am curious to find out what &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; things one can do with it. For that, I want to be able to test &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; quickly. When I test and try out new things, I usually do it on my development box which contains everything I need: &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;RabbitMQ&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;RStudio&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Machine Learning Server&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Visual Studio&lt;/strong&gt; and the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So seeing that I have most of my &amp;ldquo;tools of the trade&amp;rdquo; on my machine I obviously also would like to have Kafka on the box. Herein lies a problem, I am a Windows dude and Kafka, and Windows do not gel. Yes, some people are running Kafka on Windows, but it is a chore. OK, so what to do? Sure, I could potentially run Kafka on a virtual machine, or in a Docker image, but it is not as transparent as I would like it to be (yeah, I am lazy).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hmm, Microsoft did introduce the ability to run Linux binary executables (in ELF format) natively on Windows 10 in Windows 10 version 1607. The feature is called &lt;strong&gt;Windows Subsystem for Linux&lt;/strong&gt; (WSL), and since I am now running version 1803, maybe I should try and install Kafka in &lt;em&gt;WSL&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 14</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-09-interesting-stuff---week-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2017 14:51:31 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-09-interesting-stuff---week-14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, etc., that has to do with things that interest me&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the posts that has been most interesting to me, this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 13</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-02-interesting-stuff---week-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 16:39:25 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-04-02-interesting-stuff---week-13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, etc., that has to do with things that interest me&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the posts that has been most interesting to me, this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 8</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-26-interesting-stuff---week-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 07:11:45 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-26-interesting-stuff---week-8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, etc., that has to do with things that interest me&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the posts that has been most interesting to me, this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 7</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-19-interesting-stuff---week-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 18:48:02 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-19-interesting-stuff---week-7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, etc., that has to do with things that interest me&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the posts that has been most interesting to me, this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RabbitMQ - SQL Server</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-11-rabbitmq---sql-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 12:39:51 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-11-rabbitmq---sql-server/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A week or two ago I came across a &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!searchin/rabbitmq-users/sql$20server%7Csort:relevance/rabbitmq-users/T8fA1KdVtYE/bkRz3JkOCwAJ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on the &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/rabbitmq-users&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RabbitMQ Users&lt;/a&gt; forum, about how to communicate from SQL Server to RabbitMQ. Seeing that we do that a lot at &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/Derivco&#34;&gt;Derivco&lt;/a&gt;, I came with some suggestions, and also said that I was writing a blog-post about how it can be done. The part of writing was not entirely correct - at least not until now (sorry Jim, it&amp;rsquo;s been hectic at work).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 5</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-05-interesting-stuff---week-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 09:58:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-02-05-interesting-stuff---week-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout the week, I read a lot of blog-posts, articles, etc., that has to do with things that interest me:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data science&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;data in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;distributed computing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;transactions (both db as well as non db)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;and other &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;roundup&amp;rdquo; of the posts that has been most interesting to me, this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
