<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NVIDIA on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/nvidia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in NVIDIA on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 08:24:48 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/nvidia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 39, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-09-28-interesting-stuff---week-39-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 08:24:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-09-28-interesting-stuff---week-39-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 39, 2025, brought some reality-checking insights about building production AI systems, along with infrastructure announcements that could reshape the entire industry. From Mayank Bohra&amp;rsquo;s brutal takedown of the 10 myths killing LLM projects to OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s jaw-dropping $100 billion partnership with NVIDIA for 10 gigawatts of computing power, this week highlighted both the practical challenges and astronomical ambitions driving AI development.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;OpenAI also launched ChatGPT Pulse, shifting from reactive Q&amp;amp;A to proactive research assistance. At the same time, thoughtful analysis from Calvin French-Owen reminded us that even with sophisticated AI coding tools, human thinking remains irreplaceable. Plus, exciting updates on our October 11 &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aimldatadurban.org/events/2025/ready-player-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; event, where we&amp;rsquo;re creating a dedicated space for students and recent graduates to showcase their innovations to industry professionals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 02, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-01-12-interesting-stuff---week-02-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2025 08:55:38 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-01-12-interesting-stuff---week-02-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AI and tech innovations are moving at lightning speed, and this week&amp;rsquo;s roundup dives into the breakthroughs shaping our future. From Nvidia&amp;rsquo;s portable powerhouse redefining AI workflows to Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Large Action Models bringing real-world task execution to LLMs, the possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Explore how open-source frameworks like PRIME and AG2 are democratizing advanced AI while Sam Altman reflects on OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s journey to superintelligence. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into these exciting developments!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
