<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PostgreSQL on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/postgresql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PostgreSQL on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:19:04 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/postgresql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 48, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-30-interesting-stuff---week-48-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 06:19:04 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-30-interesting-stuff---week-48-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup showcases the infrastructure layer that&amp;rsquo;s transforming AI coding from impressive demos to genuinely trustworthy production tools. Tiger Data open-sourced &lt;code&gt;pg-aiguide&lt;/code&gt; to teach LLMs production-ready PostgreSQL, Anthropic released Claude Opus 4.5 with dramatic efficiency gains and frontier-level capabilities, researchers mapped the architectural gulf between shallow and deep AI agents, and Anthropic&amp;rsquo;s engineering team revealed how they solved long-running agent consistency by borrowing practices from effective software engineering teams.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I delivered my &lt;strong&gt;C# MCP Servers and Azure AI&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;** talk at the &lt;strong&gt;.NET Conf 2025 Johannesburg&lt;/strong&gt; yesterday (literally blowing attendees away in the windy outdoor venue!). We&amp;rsquo;re putting final touches on &#xD;&#xA;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aimldatadurban.org/events/2025/season-of-ai-mcp/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day Durban: Season of AI - Merry Christmas People (MCP)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on December 13, CfS closes today. We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few tickets left for what promises to be an epic Year-End Finale!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 36, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-09-07-interesting-stuff---week-36-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 08:20:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-09-07-interesting-stuff---week-36-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech roundup captures a fundamental shift from band-aid solutions to systematic transformation across multiple domains. TimescaleDB demonstrates how specialised infrastructure can deliver 979x performance gains over traditional databases for time-series workloads, while agentic AI is revolutionising both coding workflows and customer experience systems by moving beyond simple automation to true orchestration. The common thread connecting these developments is the transition from piecemeal fixes to unified platforms that treat complex problems holistically.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whether that&amp;rsquo;s Boris Cherney&amp;rsquo;s vision of Claude Code evolving from autocomplete to autonomous engineering teams, or the replacement of chatbot proliferation with agentic systems that actually complete end-to-end workflows. These aren&amp;rsquo;t just incremental improvements; they represent architectural paradigm shifts that fundamentally change how we approach software development, data management, and customer service at scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 25, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-06-22-interesting-stuff---week-25-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 08:30:15 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-06-22-interesting-stuff---week-25-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s tech landscape reveals a fascinating convergence: while HTAP databases officially die and give way to modular data stacks, OpenAI proves that PostgreSQL mastery can handle ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s massive scale with just one primary instance and dozens of replicas. Meanwhile, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Code Researcher demonstrates AI agents evolving from simple code completion to autonomous system-level debugging. At the same time, OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s O3 family introduces true reasoning models that think through problems rather than relying on pattern matching.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The meta-narrative emerging is clear: traditional engineering excellence is converging with AI-native approaches, while organisational dynamics continue to trump pure technical merit in enterprise adoption. From self-evolving agents that develop strategic planning autonomously to comprehensive frameworks democratising AI development, we&amp;rsquo;re witnessing the early stages of Software 3.0&amp;rsquo;s promised transformation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
