<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Control Center on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/control-center/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Control Center on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 18:43:48 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/control-center/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Install Confluent Platform (Kafka) on Windows</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-07-10-install-confluent-platform-kafka-on-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 18:43:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2018-07-10-install-confluent-platform-kafka-on-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You who follows my blog and have read my weekly roundups you know that I am quite (that is an understatement) interested in Apache Kafka and I am curious to find out what &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; things one can do with it. For that, I want to be able to test &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; quickly. When I test and try out new things, I usually do it on my development box which contains everything I need: &lt;strong&gt;SQL Server&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;RabbitMQ&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;RStudio&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Machine Learning Server&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Visual Studio&lt;/strong&gt; and the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So seeing that I have most of my &amp;ldquo;tools of the trade&amp;rdquo; on my machine I obviously also would like to have Kafka on the box. Herein lies a problem, I am a Windows dude and Kafka, and Windows do not gel. Yes, some people are running Kafka on Windows, but it is a chore. OK, so what to do? Sure, I could potentially run Kafka on a virtual machine, or in a Docker image, but it is not as transparent as I would like it to be (yeah, I am lazy).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hmm, Microsoft did introduce the ability to run Linux binary executables (in ELF format) natively on Windows 10 in Windows 10 version 1607. The feature is called &lt;strong&gt;Windows Subsystem for Linux&lt;/strong&gt; (WSL), and since I am now running version 1803, maybe I should try and install Kafka in &lt;em&gt;WSL&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
