<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TRUSTWORTHY on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/trustworthy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in TRUSTWORTHY on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2017 09:53:57 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/trustworthy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2017 SQLCLR - Whitelisting Assemblies</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-23-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-white-listing-assemblies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2017 09:53:57 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-23-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-white-listing-assemblies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A little while ago I wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-02-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-and-permissions/&#34;&gt;blog-post&lt;/a&gt; about the changes in the SQLCLR security model in SQL Server 2017. I wrote about how Microsoft has changed the relation between CAS and security boundaries, and CAS is no longer supported as a boundary! And also how Microsoft introduced an &lt;code&gt;sp_configure&lt;/code&gt; option called &lt;code&gt;clr strict security&lt;/code&gt;, which by default is set to 1 (on). When the setting is on, SQL Server treats all assemblies (&lt;code&gt;SAFE&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;EXTERNAL_ACCESS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;UNSAFE&lt;/code&gt;) as if they were marked &lt;code&gt;UNSAFE&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The release I wrote the post against was CTP 2.1, and earlier this week Microsoft released SQL Server 2017 RC1. Some days ago I received a comment from &lt;em&gt;Paul Vestuto&lt;/em&gt; on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-02-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-and-permissions/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, pointing out that in RC1 there has been some more changes to the security model. I thought those changes would earn their own blog-post, instead of just editing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-02-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-and-permissions/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQL Server 2017, SQLCLR and Permissions</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-02-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-and-permissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 08:18:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-02-sql-server-2017-sqlclr-and-permissions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I was writing the post about &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-01-sqlclr--certificates/&#34;&gt;SQLCLR and Certificates&lt;/a&gt;, I came across some strange behavior when I accidentally ran my code on an SQL Server 2017 instance. I quickly connected back to my SQL Server 2016 instance and continued. However, afterwards I started to look into the differences between SQLCLR in SQL Server 2017 and SQL Server 2016, and this post is the result of me &lt;del&gt;playing around&lt;/del&gt; investigating the changes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SQLCLR and Certificates</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-01-sqlclr--certificates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 06:21:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-07-01-sqlclr--certificates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post originates, like the one about &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2017-06-25-creating-r-stored-procedures-in-sql-server-2016-using-sqlrutils/&#34;&gt;sqlrutils&lt;/a&gt;, from a question on a Microsoft forum - this time the &lt;a href=&#34;https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/sqlserver/en-US/home?forum=sqlnetfx&#34;&gt;.NET Framework inside SQL Server&lt;/a&gt; forum. As the name implies, the forum cover questions about the usage of SQLCLR (.NET inside SQL Server), and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://social.msdn.microsoft.com/Forums/sqlserver/en-US/35b8bce5-8ea9-4fd4-aa87-1764a2071e92/long-lasting-pfx-file-for-sqlclr-externalaccess-signing?forum=sqlnetfx&#34;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; was about signing of SQLCLR assemblies in order to assigning other permission sets than &lt;code&gt;SAFE&lt;/code&gt; to the assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I, back in the day, taught SQLCLR as part of Developmentor&amp;rsquo;s SQL Server curriculum, I thought that it&amp;rsquo;d be interesting if I tried to answer the question, and also make a blog-post about it. That way I&amp;rsquo;d remember what to do the next time the question came up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; In another post, I wrote this about Developmentor: &lt;em&gt;Developmentor were back in the day THE training company to go to if you wanted highly, highly technical training about COM, .NET, SQL Server, etc. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.javaworld.com/article/2073792/core-java/a-eulogy--developmentor--rip.html&#34;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; by my old colleague &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.tedneward.com/&#34;&gt;Ted Neward&lt;/a&gt; (@tedneward) sums DM up quite accurately (apart from the fact that DM hadn&amp;rsquo;t closed its doors when the article was written, ooops).&lt;/em&gt; Ted was probably more accurate than he at the time thought, since DM went out of business somewhat later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, let&amp;rsquo;s see what this is all about&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
