<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mono on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/categories/mono/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mono on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/categories/mono/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>F#, Mono and Mac - Take II</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-20-fsharp-mono-and-mac-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-20-fsharp-mono-and-mac-2/</guid>
      <description>So yesterday I wrote about how I have started using F# and Mono on my MacBook.&#xA;I wrote about how I downloaded the F# bits, unzipped and put them in a specific directory I had created. Today after having browsed around a bit more I realized I had done it the hard way. To install the required bits for F# for Mac, you only have to download a zip file with an install package for Mac from the F# Cross Platform site on CodePlex.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>F#, Mono and Mac</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-19-fsharp-mono-and-mac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 09:27:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-19-fsharp-mono-and-mac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a first post about my experiences with running F# and Mono on a Mac.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nielsberglund.com/post/2010-11-15-using-fsharp-in-sqlclr/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote about how I have started to play with F#. As that post also covered SQLCLR it was obvious I was on Windows. Even though I make my living from development in a Windows environment, my main machine is a MacBook, and I run OSX as my main OS. I have previously also been running Linux (ArchLinux) on this machine as my main OS. Naturally I have heard about Mono (and also installed it a couple of times - and quickly un-installed again, but I have not really done anything with it. I have always run Windows in a VM on my MacBook for development etc. However after the announcement that F# was going &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/dsyme/archive/2010/11/04/announcing-the-f-compiler-library-source-code-drop.aspx&#34;&gt;Open Source&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomasp.net/blog&#34;&gt;Tomas P&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://tomasp.net/blog/fsharp-in-monodevelop.aspx&#34;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about his F# MonoDevelop plug-in&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;, I decided that I should have a look at what it would be like to do F# &amp;ldquo;stuff in OSX.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
