<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Async Programming on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/async-programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Async Programming on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 12:53:09 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/async-programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 46, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-16-interesting-stuff---week-46-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 12:53:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-11-16-interesting-stuff---week-46-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s roundup explores the foundational research papers that transformed AI from an academic curiosity into production-ready technology, covering everything from the revolutionary Transformer architecture to the Model Context Protocol, which enables standardised tool integration. We examine critical performance optimisation techniques for Azure OpenAI deployments, where asynchronous programming delivers 11x speed improvements by parallelising tasks instead of processing them sequentially.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The spotlight then shifts to a paradigm-challenging analysis of why small language models with fewer than 10 billion parameters are proving architecturally superior for agentic AI systems, potentially delivering 30 times the cost savings while matching the performance of their trillion-parameter cousins on specialised tasks. Finally, I share updates from the successful .NET Conf 2025 Durban event and preview the upcoming roadshow, which will visit Cape Town and Johannesburg, where I&amp;rsquo;ll explore Model Context Protocol integration with C# and Azure AI.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
