<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dotnetconfsa on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/dotnetconfsa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dotnetconfsa on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 09:09:16 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/dotnetconfsa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 42, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-19-interesting-stuff---week-42-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2025 09:09:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-10-19-interesting-stuff---week-42-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 42 delivers a masterclass in engineering honesty and AI accessibility that cuts through the usual tech hype. Netflix&amp;rsquo;s Adrian Taruc and James Dalton reveal how they built a Real-Time Distributed Graph processing system capable of handling 5 million records per second, candidly admitting their initial monolithic Flink job was an &amp;ldquo;operational headache&amp;rdquo; before pivoting to a more complex but maintainable architecture. Andrej Karpathy proves AI training doesn&amp;rsquo;t require enterprise budgets with nanochat. Training a GPT-2-calibre model in under four hours for approximately $92. GitHub&amp;rsquo;s Andrea Griffiths tackles the COBOL crisis, showing how AI agents can modernise 65-year-old mainframe systems without developers learning COBOL. Anthropic dominates with Claude Haiku 4.5 (frontier performance at one-third the cost) and Agent Skills, an elegantly simple filesystem-based approach to agent specialisation that treats domain expertise like employee onboarding through progressive disclosure and structured folders.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I found myself in Johannesburg delivering &lt;strong&gt;Generative AI for Beginners: Build Your First Agent with Azure AI Foundry&lt;/strong&gt; at the Data &amp;amp; AI Community Day event to an almost-full house. There&amp;rsquo;s no rest ahead, though, for the first time ever, &lt;strong&gt;.NET Conf South Africa Community Edition&lt;/strong&gt; is coming to Durban on November 15 at &lt;strong&gt;Richfield College&lt;/strong&gt;, and we&amp;rsquo;re actively seeking speakers with .NET, C#, Blazor, MAUI, ASP.NET Core, or Azure expertise to share with the KwaZulu-Natal developer community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 35, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-08-31-interesting-stuff---week-35-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 09:20:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-08-31-interesting-stuff---week-35-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 35 brings a fascinating paradox in AI development: while Anthropic pilots Claude for Chrome with impressive capabilities but sobering security vulnerabilities, researchers discover that the most human-sounding AI model costs just pennies compared to premium alternatives. From Claude Code&amp;rsquo;s meteoric rise among developers to Google&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;nano-banana&amp;rdquo; image generation model, this week highlights how the AI landscape is being shaped as much by user experience design and cost-effectiveness as raw technical performance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The developments span from browser automation and coding assistants to image generation and market research, revealing an industry where authenticity and accessibility often trump expensive computational power. On the local front, after years without a dedicated .NET conference in Durban due to venue constraints, &lt;strong&gt;.NET Conf SA&lt;/strong&gt; is tentatively scheduled for November 15 at the Umhlanga Campus of &lt;strong&gt;Richfield College&lt;/strong&gt;, marking a significant milestone for the regional developer community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
