<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dotnetconfsa on Niels Berglund</title>
    <link>https://nielsberglund.com/tags/dotnetconfsa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dotnetconfsa on Niels Berglund</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 09:20:30 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nielsberglund.com/tags/dotnetconfsa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interesting Stuff - Week 35, 2025</title>
      <link>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-08-31-interesting-stuff---week-35-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 09:20:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nielsberglund.com/post/2025-08-31-interesting-stuff---week-35-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 35 brings a fascinating paradox in AI development: while Anthropic pilots Claude for Chrome with impressive capabilities but sobering security vulnerabilities, researchers discover that the most human-sounding AI model costs just pennies compared to premium alternatives. From Claude Code&amp;rsquo;s meteoric rise among developers to Google&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;nano-banana&amp;rdquo; image generation model, this week highlights how the AI landscape is being shaped as much by user experience design and cost-effectiveness as raw technical performance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The developments span from browser automation and coding assistants to image generation and market research, revealing an industry where authenticity and accessibility often trump expensive computational power. On the local front, after years without a dedicated .NET conference in Durban due to venue constraints, &lt;strong&gt;.NET Conf SA&lt;/strong&gt; is tentatively scheduled for November 15 at the Umhlanga Campus of &lt;strong&gt;Richfield College&lt;/strong&gt;, marking a significant milestone for the regional developer community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
